<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="categories">
  <title>Categories in Xaraya</title>

  <para><firstterm>Articles</firstterm> are placed into
  <firstterm>Publication Types</firstterm> which can contain
  <firstterm>Categories</firstterm>. Categories are an easy way to provide
  hierarchical categorization for all information on your site. You could use
  one or more common Categories across different Publication Types, or use
  specific Categories for each type of article, or any combination that you
  prefer for your site.</para>

  <para>Before specifying which Publication Types will be using what
  Categories, create the categorization you want via the Categories
  Administration Menu. To get you started, a default set of categories was
  defined for articles when Xaraya was installed. You can adapt the existing
  categories to your specific needs, of course, or remove them altogether.</para>

  <para>Once you have a set of categories you would like to use for your
  articles, go to <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Modify config</command>,
  and specify the number of categories that can be used for each Publication
  Type, and select the &#39;<firstterm>base categories</firstterm>&#39; to be
  used.</para>

  <para>A &#39;base category&#39; is any starting point somewhere in your tree
  of categories, below which you will have the actual list (or sub-tree) of
  categories people can choose from when they submit or view articles.</para>

  <para>For example, you could have a &#39;base category&#39; called Topics,
  with a list of different topics relevant to your site below it, and another
  &#39;base category&#39; called Cities, with a list of cities or places for
  which you would provide regional news. One topic might be &#39;Good
  Restaurants&#39;, and one category might &#39;Brussels&#39;, so people would
  be able to browse through any articles about good restaurants in Brussels,
  for instance.</para>

  <sect1 id="editcats">
    <title>Editing and Creating Categories</title>

    <para>In this section, we explore how to edit pre-configured categories
    and create new categories. Categories are displayed to the site
    administrator in a &#34;<firstterm>category tree</firstterm>&#34;, a
    listing that shows categories and sub-categories in an easy-to-understand
    format.</para>

    <para><command>Admin-&#62;Categories-&#62;Modify config</command>:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you wish to display categories in a Windows Explorer-like tree
        view, click &#34;<guibutton>Yes</guibutton>&#34;. Displaying
        categories in this way requires a JavaScript-enabled browser. If you
        use this display method, the icons in <command>Admin-&#62;Categories-&#62;View
        Categories</command> have the following meaning:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The &#34;<guibutton>+</guibutton>&#34; icon to the left of
            the category name &#38; description expands or collapses the tree
            for the category.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The &#34;<guibutton>X</guibutton>&#34; icon to the right of
            the category name &#38; description deletes the category and any
            sub-categories under it. If you wish to delete the category and
            any sub-categories, click &#34;<guibutton>Yes</guibutton>&#34; on
            the confirmation screen.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The &#34;<guibutton>pencil</guibutton>&#34; icon to the
            right of the &#34;<guibutton>X</guibutton>&#34; icon allows
            modification of category properties.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Submit</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>

        <figure id="categoriestree">
          <title>Windows Explorer-like tree</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="sourceimages/categoriestree.jpg"
              format="JPG" width="450" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><command>Admin-&#62;Categories-&#62;View Categories</command>:</para>

    <para>This panel displays all the Categories that are pre-configured by
    the Xaraya Base installation. Let&#39;s edit an existing category, and
    then add a few new categories from scratch.</para>

    <sect2 id="editingexistingcat">
      <title>Editing an existing Category</title>

      <para>To edit an existing category, click on the &#34;<guibutton>Modify</guibutton>&#34;
      link on the same line as the Name of the category you wish to edit. For
      this example, click &#34;<guibutton>Modify</guibutton>&#34; on the
      &#34;Topics&#34; line. This edits the top-level category called
      &#34;Topics&#34;.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: The name of the category. For this example, change it to
          &#34;Topics of Interest&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Description: A description of the category that is displayed
          to users. For this example, change it to &#34;<userinput>Interesting
          topics on this website.</userinput>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The next two options determine the position of the new/edited
      category in the category tree, and specifies if the category is a
      top-level category or a sub-category.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>In relation to this category</emphasis>: Select an
          existing category from the drop-down list. This existing category
          serves as the reference point for the Position function, below. For
          this example, since we don&#39;t want to move this category, just
          leave this field as it is.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Position</emphasis>: Determines the placement of the
          new/edited category in conjunction with the &#34;In relation to this
          category&#34; field above. For this example, since we don&#39;t want
          to move this category, just leave this field as it is.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Right before, in the same level</emphasis>: If
              you want the new/edited category to be placed ABOVE the category
              specified in &#34;In relation to this category&#34; and be on
              the same level (for example, if the category selected in &#34;In
              relation to this category&#34; is a top-level category, this
              new/edited category will also be top-level), select this option.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>Right after, in the same level</emphasis>: If
              you want the new/edited category to be placed BELOW the category
              specified in &#34;In relation to this category&#34; and be on
              the same level (for example, if the category selected in &#34;In
              relation to this category&#34; is a top-level category, this
              new/edited category will also be top-level), select this option.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>The first child category</emphasis>: If you want
              the new/edited category to be placed ABOVE the category
              specified in &#34;In relation to this category&#34; and to be a
              child category of the category referenced in &#34;In relation to
              this category&#34;, select this option.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis>The last child category</emphasis>: If you want
              the new/edited category to be placed BELOW the category
              specified in &#34;In relation to this category&#34; and to be a
              child category of the category referenced in &#34;In relation to
              this category&#34;, select this option.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Optional image: From this drop-down list, select the image
          associated with this category. The image format can be any popular
          image file format (JPG, GIF, PNG, etc) and must exist in one of two
          directories:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>&#34;<filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/categories/xarimages</filename>&#34;
              or</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>&#34;<filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/themes/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/categories/images</filename>&#34;
              for theme-dependent versions</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Modify</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="addnewcat">
      <title>Adding a new Category</title>

      <para>To add a new Category, click <command>Admin-&#62;Categories-&#62;Add
      Category</command>. Complete the fields on the next panel, and click
      &#34;<guibutton>Add</guibutton>&#34; to create the new category. If you
      are adding a large number of categories at one time, you can do so in a
      batch. Enter the number of categories you&#39;d like to create in the
      &#34;<guibutton>Create in a Batch</guibutton>&#34; field and click &#34;<guibutton>Reassign</guibutton>&#34;.
      This will refresh the panel with the specified number of category slots.
      Complete the fields and click &#34;<guibutton>Add</guibutton>&#34; to
      batch-create the categories.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>EXAMPLE: Add your own Categories</title>

        <para>For this example, using the methods detailed above (editing or
        adding categories as necessary), create the following categories under
        &#34;Topics of Interest&#34; (to create this category, see
        &#34;Editing an Existing Category&#34;, above):
        <userinput>News</userinput>, <userinput>Announcements</userinput>,
        <userinput>System Information</userinput>, <userinput>Xaraya</userinput>,
        and <userinput>Internet</userinput>. Enter any text in the Description
        field. Also, put these new categories in alphabetical order under
        &#34;Topics of Interest&#34; either by manipulating the placement
        using the available category positioning tools or by creating them in
        alphabetical order.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="catsconclusion">
    <title>Categories Conclusion</title>

    <para>Once you have defined your site&#39;s Categories, they can be
    assigned to one or more Publication Types. We&#39;ll learn how to assign
    Categories to Publication Types, and what that means, later in this Guide.
    First, though, let&#39;s look at the modules of Xaraya.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
