<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>General Configuration</title>

  <para>Now that we&#39;ve installed Xaraya, we should begin to configure it.
  The Community Site installation, by default, does not permit Registered
  users to change their theme, to post comments, or to submit articles for
  publication (all features that we set forth as configuration goals in
  Assumptions, above) so these features need to be implemented.
  <command>Admin-&#62;Themes-&#62;Modify config</command>:</para>

  <para>See the section on the Themes Module (below) for more information
  about these settings.</para>

  <para>Let&#39;s personalize the site a bit before we get started --
  we&#39;ll do additional personalization later on. For now, we can change the
  name, slogan, copyright statement, footer, and default theme of the site
  from the <command>Admin-&#62;Themes-&#62;Modify config</command> panel.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Select default theme from drop-down list. The Xaraya Base
      installation provides only one theme, so until you&#39;ve installed
      additional themes, this should be an easy selection.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In the title bar of your browser window, you should see the following:
  <guilabel>Your Site Name :: Your Site Slogan</guilabel></para>

  <para>This is your Site Name &#38; Site Slogan, respectively, separated by
  the Title Separator. Edit these using the Site Name &#38; Site Slogan fields
  below.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Type your <emphasis>Site Name</emphasis> -- whatever you&#39;d
      like the name of your site to be.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Type your <emphasis>Site Slogan</emphasis> -- this field defines
      the site&#39;s slogan. This slogan is displayed at the top of the page
      under the site name in some themes, and in the title bar of the browser
      by default.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Type the <emphasis>Copyright statement</emphasis> -- defaults to
      &#34;<userinput>&#38;copy; Copyright 2003 &#60;administrator name&#62;</userinput>&#34;.
      Change it as necessary.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Edit the <emphasis>Footer</emphasis>. The &#39;footer&#39; is
      displayed at the bottom (the &#39;foot&#39;) of each and every page on
      your site. This is an excellent place to give credit, state copyright,
      or put links that you wish to appear on every page of the site. While we
      appreciate credit being given to Xaraya in the footer, it is by no means
      compulsory so the &#34;Powered by Xaraya&#34; graphic can be removed if
      you wish.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>Page Title Separator</emphasis>: Default is &#34; ::
      &#34;, but you can make it anything you wish by editing this field.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis>Page Title Order</emphasis>: Determines how the page
      title is displayed. You can experiment wiht the page display order to
      find the one that suits your site best. For now, though, leave it set to
      the default.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click &#34;<command>Submit</command>&#34; to save changes</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Modify config</command>:</para>

  <para>See the section on the Base Module (below) for more information about
  these settings.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Website display configuration:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For this example, set the <emphasis>Default Module</emphasis>
          to &#34;<guibutton>articles</guibutton>&#34; so that the articles
          module is displayed when a visitor hits the site. Select &#34;<guibutton>articles</guibutton>&#34;
          from the drop-down list of available modules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Module Type</emphasis>: From the drop-down
          list, &#34;<guibutton>User</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Module Function</emphasis>: &#34;<guibutton>main</guibutton>&#34;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Theme Directory</emphasis> (relative to
          <command>&#60;xarroot&#62;</command>): &#34;<guibutton>themes</guibutton>&#34;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CHECK &#34;<emphasis>Enable Short URL Support</emphasis>&#34;
          -- this is the &#39;master switch&#39; for Short URL support on your
          site.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CHECK &#34;<emphasis>Fix HTML Entities</emphasis>&#34; -- this
          will ensure that characters such as the copyright sign and
          international symbols like umlauts are displayed correctly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sessions and Security</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Security level: From this drop-down list, configure the
          general security level for your site. If a user CHECKS the
          &#34;Remember Me&#34; box displayed in the login panel when logging
          in, the user&#39;s session is not purged for the duration set in the
          settings below. If a user does NOT check the &#34;Remember Me&#34;
          box when logging in, they must log into the site each time they
          visit. For our example, select &#34;Medium&#34; security.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>High: Users must log on each time they return to the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Medium: Users stay logged on for the number of days
              specified in Session Duration, below.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Low: Users stay logged in &#39;forever&#39; (well,
              it&#39;s not actually <emphasis>FOREVER</emphasis>, but a really
              long time!).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Session duration (in days): This setting determines how long
          (in days) a user&#39;s session will last before it expires, forcing
          the user to re-log in with their existing username and password. Set
          the session duration to &#34;<userinput>7</userinput>&#34; days.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Session inactivity time out: If Xaraya detects that a
          user&#39;s session has been idle for a certain period of time and
          that the Security level is High or Medium, it will expire the
          session. This setting determines how many minutes Xaraya will wait
          before expiring the session due to inactivity. Set the inactivity
          time to &#34;<userinput>90</userinput>&#34; minutes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Base Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
          to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;System Information</command>: This panel
  displays a variety of information about the PHP installation on the site.
  Should you ever need to determine what version of PHP the site is running,
  or what modules are compiled into PHP, this is where to find that
  information. This information may be helpful if you need to submit a Xaraya
  bug report or a feature request.</para>
</chapter>