<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="config">
  <title>General Configuration</title>

  <para>Now that we've installed Xaraya, we should begin to configure it.
  The pages in this section should help guide you through some of the more basic configuration options and start you on the path to customizing your Xaraya site.</para>

 <sect1 id="baseconfig">
  <title>Base Module Config</title>

  <para>This section describes some of the settings and options available from the base module.</para>

  <para><command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Modifyconfig</command>: This panel allows you to change some of the settings controlling the core behaviour of the site.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Website display configuration:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For this example, set the <emphasis>Default Module</emphasis>
          to &#34;<guibutton>articles</guibutton>&#34; so that the articles
          module is displayed when a visitor hits the site. Select &#34;<guibutton>articles</guibutton>&#34;
          from the drop-down list of available modules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Module Type</emphasis>: From the drop-down
          list, &#34;<guibutton>User</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Module Function</emphasis>: &#34;<guibutton>main</guibutton>&#34;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Default Theme Directory</emphasis> (relative to
          <command>&#60;xarroot&#62;</command>): &#34;<guibutton>themes</guibutton>&#34;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CHECK &#34;<emphasis>Enable Short URL Support</emphasis>&#34;
          -- this is the &#39;master switch&#39; for Short URL support on your
          site.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CHECK &#34;<emphasis>Fix HTML Entities</emphasis>&#34; -- this
          will ensure that characters such as the copyright sign and
          international symbols like umlauts are displayed correctly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Sessions and Security</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Security level: From this drop-down list, configure the
          general security level for your site. If a user CHECKS the
          &#34;Remember Me&#34; box displayed in the login panel when logging
          in, the user&#39;s session is not purged for the duration set in the
          settings below. If a user does NOT check the &#34;Remember Me&#34;
          box when logging in, they must log into the site each time they
          visit. For our example, select &#34;Medium&#34; security.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>High: Users must log on each time they return to the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Medium: Users stay logged on for the number of days
              specified in Session Duration, below.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Low: Users stay logged in &#39;forever&#39; (well,
              it&#39;s not actually <emphasis>FOREVER</emphasis>, but a really
              long time!).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Session duration (in days): This setting determines how long
          (in days) a user&#39;s session will last before it expires, forcing
          the user to re-log in with their existing username and password. Set
          the session duration to &#34;<userinput>7</userinput>&#34; days.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Session inactivity time out: If Xaraya detects that a
          user&#39;s session has been idle for a certain period of time and
          that the Security level is High or Medium, it will expire the
          session. This setting determines how many minutes Xaraya will wait
          before expiring the session due to inactivity. Set the inactivity
          time to &#34;<userinput>90</userinput>&#34; minutes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Base Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
          to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Languages and Locales</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Other</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;System Information</command>: This panel
  displays a variety of information about the PHP installation on the site.
  Should you ever need to determine what version of PHP the site is running,
  or what modules are compiled into PHP, this is where to find that
  information. This information may be helpful if you need to submit a Xaraya
  bug report or a feature request.</para>

  <para><command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Extension Releases</command>: This panel syndicates a news feed from www.xaraya.com listing recent module and theme releases.</para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
