<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="dynamicdata">
  <title>Dynamic Data in Xaraya</title>

  <sect1 id="ddintro">
    <title>Introduction to Dynamic Data</title>

    <para>Xaraya provides the ability for site administrators to add data
    fields to the site to serve a number of different purposes, from extending
    the basic Xaraya configuration to adding completely new features. Using
    <firstterm>Dynamic Data</firstterm>, fields can be added and manipulated
    on the site. This ability is available through Dynamic Data, which can be
    considered &#39;building blocks&#39; for data manipulation on the site.</para>

    <para>With other Content Management Systems products, if you wanted to
    display Recipes on your site, for example, you had to wait for a Recipes
    module to be developed and then hope it met your needs. As a Content
    Management System, Xaraya is capable of showing almost any data in almost
    any way that you desire -- usually without the need to develop (or wait
    for) an external module. No more waiting for someone else to create a
    guestbook; no more waiting for someone else to develop that recipe module;
    no more waiting for someone to add categories to the reviews module; no
    more waiting for a module to display portraits or additional information
    in user information screens. Xaraya gives the site administrator the power
    to be self-sufficient and the flexibility to extend Xaraya -- without
    coding. Dynamic Data allows Xaraya&#39;s site administrators to customize
    Xaraya specifically for their needs.</para>

    <para>Using Dynamic Data, site administrators can add fields to Xaraya
    that customize the site.</para>

    <para>Here&#39;s a general overview illustrating how to add dynamic data
    to a Xaraya module:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enable the Dynamic Data HOOK for the module you wish to extend</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Create the Dynamic Data OBJECT</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>OTTO: * Define how the Dynamic Data object is DISPLAYED</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>EXAMPLE: Dynamic Data: Adding a Picture to User Info</title>

      <para>For a specific example, we&#39;ll add a picture to user&#39;s
      information on the site. The user&#39;s picture file must be accessible
      via the web; this feature does not allow the uploading of picture.
      Let&#39;s walk through the steps to set this up...</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable the Dynamic Data HOOK for the module you wish to extend</para>

          <para>The first thing to do is to enable the dynamic data hook for
          the module you wish to extend. For this example, we wish to extend
          the roles module. OTTO: How to determine WHICH module to enable DD
          for? To enable Dynamic Data for the roles module, follow these
          steps:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure Hooks</command></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>dynamicdata</guibutton>&#34;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>CHECK the box next to &#39;<guibutton>roles</guibutton>&#39;
              to enable Dynamic Data for the roles module</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>&#34;</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create the Dynamic Data OBJECT</para>

          <para>Now we need to create the dynamic data object that will hold
          the picture information for the roles module. To do this:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Dynamicdata-&#62;View Objects</command></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Under &#34;<guibutton>Other Modules/Users &#38; Groups</guibutton>&#34;,
              click on &#34;<guibutton>View Properties</guibutton>&#34; for
              the roles module</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In Label, type &#34;My Picture&#34; (or whatever text you
              want displayed to your users)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In Property Type, select &#34;<guibutton>Image</guibutton>&#34;
              from the drop-down list.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In status select &#34;<guibutton>Display Only</guibutton>&#34;.
              This will stop it showing in the membership list but will still
              make it visible in the user info.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Properties</guibutton>&#34;
              to save changes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>You are returned to a similar-looking screen with your new
          Dynamic Data object displayed. Your Dynamic Data object has been
          added.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Adding a picture to your user info</para>

          <para>You&#39;ll need a picture that is accessible via the web to
          add a picture to your user info. To add the picture, follow these
          steps:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>As Administrator, go to <command>Main
              Menu-&#62;Modules-&#62;Roles</command> (NOTE: Do
              <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> click <command>Admin-&#62;Roles</command>
              for this option).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Your Details</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Add the URL of your picture to the &#34;<guibutton>My
              Picture</guibutton>&#34; field. Be sure it begins with &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;
              unless the picture is on your local webserver.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Submit</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Viewing the picture</para>

          <para>There are two ways to do this. Once you&#39;ve added your
          picture&#39;s URL click the &#34;<guibutton>show</guibutton>&#34;
          link next to it in &#34;<guibutton>Your Basic Details</guibutton>&#34;,
          or click on the user&#39;s name in the membership list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>KNOWLEDGE REVIEW: Dealing with Dynamic Data</title>

      <para>OTTO</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
