<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Introduction &#38; Information about Xaraya</title>

  <para>This chapter will give you an introduction to Xaraya, it&#39;s
  features, the format of this Guide, and the assumptions under which this
  Guide was written. Also included is a handy Xaraya pronunciation guide!</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction by John Cox</title>

    <para><emphasis>Building a better mouse trap</emphasis> has always been a
    desire for inventors since the beginning of time.</para>

    <para>For the Xaraya team that was the motivation. Our desire and drive
    came from the idea of doing something that has not been done before, which
    in my opinion has been accomplished. Xaraya is the culmination of the work
    of several of the world&#39;s best software designers working within the
    PHP language at this time.</para>

    <para>The Official Xaraya Installation &#38; Getting Started Guide will
    introduce you to concepts that are, most likely, unfamiliar to you. Having
    complete control over the output of the software is the nirvana that most
    designers of Open Source Content Management Systems only dream of. Beyond
    the control of the output, though, is the control of the
    <emphasis>input</emphasis> as well, which to my knowledge has not been
    attempted.</para>

    <para>Xaraya will ask you to re-examine your expectations as to what
    Content Management Systems can -- <emphasis>and should</emphasis> -- offer
    you.</para>

    <para>The Official Xaraya Installation &#38; Getting Started Guide itself
    is the culmination of well over a year&#39;s worth of work to not only
    document what can be done, but to explain in common terms and phrases what
    Xaraya will do for you. It is not only the comprehensive guide to Xaraya,
    but it is a narrative which will walk you through the collective knowledge
    of the Xaraya team. The guide has been written by Drew Vogel (and others)
    who have likely spent more time documenting than others have spent coding.</para>

    <para>Welcome to the Official Xaraya Installation &#38; Getting Started
    Guide.</para>

    <para><emphasis>And welcome to Xaraya -- the next generation of Content
    Management Systems.</emphasis></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Document Disclaimer</title>

    <para>While every reasonable precaution has been taken in the preparation
    of this document, neither the author nor the Xaraya development team
    assumes responsibility for errors or omissions, or for damages resulting
    from the use of the information contained herein.</para>

    <para>The information contained in this document is believed to be
    accurate. However, no guarantee is provided. Use this information at your
    own risk.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>About this Guide</title>

    <para>This Guide will assist you with installing, configuring, running,
    and maintaining a Xaraya Community Site. It is intended for Xaraya
    installers or those individuals interested in Xaraya installation and
    configuration issues.</para>

    <para>This Guide is designed to be read from start to finish. Certain
    sections may be skipped (for example, if you&#39;re upgrading, you may not
    need to read the first-time installation instructions). However, reading
    this entire Guide from start to finish will provide the maximum
    educational benefit.</para>

    <para>Throughout the Guide, there are examples for you to follow. The
    examples add new features or illustrate concepts and are all designed to
    work together. Generally, the examples include Animals, Music, or Food but
    the concepts that they teach can be customized to your particular tastes.</para>

    <para>Throughout this Guide, we use several terms that you should
    understand. <itemizedlist><listitem><para>&#34;<firstterm>Anonymous users</firstterm>&#34;
    are defined as users that have not registered/logged into an account on
    the site.</para></listitem><listitem><para>&#34;<firstterm>Registered
    users</firstterm>&#34; are defined as users that have registered for an
    account on the site and have logged into the site with their username and
    password.</para></listitem><listitem><para>&#34;<firstterm>Site
    Administrators</firstterm>&#34; are defined as one or more individuals who
    have administrative access to the site. Many sites have only one site
    administrator while some sites have an site administration team.</para></listitem><listitem><para><firstterm>&#60;webdir&#62;</firstterm>:
    This is the local directory on your site from which pages are served by
    the webserver. For example, if you&#39;re using a modern Red Hat
    installation your &#60;webdir&#62; is usually /var/www/html. Consult your
    operating system manual for information on determining your
    &#60;webdir&#62;.</para></listitem><listitem><para><firstterm>&#60;xarroot&#62;</firstterm>:
    This is the local directory on your site in which Xaraya is installed. If
    you choose to install your &#60;xarroot&#62; into your &#60;webdir&#62;,
    then the two terms have the same meaning -- they point to the same
    directory. However, if your &#60;webdir&#62; is /var/www/html, and you
    install Xaraya into a sub-directory called &#34;xaraya&#34;, then your
    &#60;xarroot&#62; is /var/www/html/xaraya.</para></listitem><listitem><para><firstterm>&#60;theme_dir&#62;</firstterm>:
    This is the local directory on your site in which Xaraya themes are
    stored. This directory location is defined in the
    Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Modify config, Default Theme Directory field.</para></listitem><listitem><para><firstterm>&#60;theme_name&#62;</firstterm>:
    This is the name of a theme on your Xaraya site.</para></listitem><listitem><para><firstterm>http://www.mywebsite.com</firstterm>:
    This URL is used as a stand-in for your site&#39;s URL. If you install
    Xaraya into a sub-directory of &#60;webdir&#62;, your site&#39;s URL will
    include the sub-directory. So, for example, if your &#60;webdir&#62; is
    /var/www/html, and you install Xaraya into a sub-directory called
    &#34;xaraya&#34;, then your site&#39;s URL will be
    http://www.mywebsite.com/xaraya.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Document Thanks</title>

    <para>Xaraya was written by the Xaraya Team. Xaraya is, as with many
    successful open-source projects, a huge collaborative effort relying on
    many talented contributors from across the globe. Without their vision,
    this document would not exist.</para>

    <para>The Official Xaraya Installation and Getting Started Guide was
    written by Drew Vogel. Abundant thanks to the Xaraya development team for
    answering Drew&#39;s endless questions. Thanks to the contributing
    authors, reviewers, Greg Allen (adam_baum), John Cox, mikespub, Doug
    Daulton (Apakuni), Skribe, Craig Hamlin, Chris Dudley (Miko), Carl Corliss
    (Rabbitt), Mahmood Al-Yousif, Michael Cortez (mcortez), marcinmilan,
    Joanna Dalle Nogare (jojodee), Marcel van der Boom (MrB), Jason Judge,
    Marjolein Katsma, SpiritTech, and Pedro Innecco. Special thanks to Gregor
    Rothfuss (thalinor) for many things.</para>

    <para>If this Guide is sucessful, proving to be useful in helping you
    install, configure, and manage your Xaraya site, a healthy measure of
    credit will be due the individuals listed above. If not -- if the Guide is
    somewhat off the mark -- the author accepts full responsibility for the
    shortcomings.</para>

    <para>This document was written using TextPad for Windows (<ulink
    url="http://www.textpad.com">http://www.textpad.com</ulink>) and XMLmind
    XML Editor (<ulink url="http://www.xmlmind.com">http://www.xmlmind.com</ulink>).</para>

    <para>Thank you to the Xaraya Team for declaring this to be the
    &#34;Official&#34; guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Files Included with this Guide</title>

    <para>The following files are included with this guide.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>callouts directory</command> -- These are files used by
        this Guide. It is not necessary to copy these files to your Xaraya
        installation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>resources directory</command> -- These are files used
        by this Guide. It is not necessary to copy these files to your Xaraya
        installation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>html.css</command> -- This file is used by this Guide.
        It is not necessary to copy this file to your Xaraya installation.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>images/recipes/NoPhoto.gif </command>-- Used in the
        Recipe Publication Type example (see EXAMPLE: Adding a new Publication
        Type that uses Dynamic Data). Displayed when no recipe photograph is
        available. Copy to <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/images/recipes</filename>
        directory, creating directories as necessary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>images/recipes/applechestnutsoup.jpg</command> -- Used
        in the Recipe Publication Type example (see EXAMPLE: Adding a new
        Publication Type that uses Dynamic Data). Photograph for the
        <filename>SampleRecipe.txt</filename> file. Copy to
        <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/images/recipes</filename> directory,
        creating directories as necessary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>modules/articles/xartemplates/user-display-recipes.xd</command>
        -- Used in the Recipe Publication Type example (see EXAMPLE: Adding a
        new Publication Type that uses Dynamic Data). Template for displaying
        the new Recipe Publication Type. For a default site-wide template,
        copy to <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/articles/xartemplates</filename>
        directory, creating directories as necessary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>modules/articles/xartemplates/user-summary-recipes.xd</command>
        -- Used in the Recipe Publication Type example (see EXAMPLE: Adding a
        new Publication Type that uses Dynamic Data). Template for displaying
        the new Recipe Publication Type. For a default site-wide template,
        copy to <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/articles/xartemplates</filename>
        directory, creating directories as necessary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>modules/categories/xarimages/*.jpg</command> --
        Category files for use with the categories created in the new Recipe
        Publication Type (see EXAMPLE: Adding a new Publication Type that uses
        Dynamic Data). For site-wide use, copy these files to the
        <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/categories/xarimages</filename>
        directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><command>Tutorials/PubType/SampleRecipe.txt</command> -- Used in
        the Recipe Publication Type example (see EXAMPLE: Adding a new
        Publication Type that uses Dynamic Data). A sample recipe to add at
        the end of the Recipe Publication Type example (and a darned good
        recipe by Drew Vogel, too!).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>An Introduction to Content Management Systems</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>A glance toward the past...</title>

      <para>As the internet and world-wide web started to emerge as a major
      repository for storage, retrieval, and display of data, the main avenue
      for accessing that data was static, hand-coded, <firstterm>HTML</firstterm>
      (Hyper-Text Markup Language). <firstterm>Static HTML</firstterm> means
      that each and every web page on a site is created individually; links
      between content elements are managed by hand; and changes can be made
      only by a site administrator following a multiple-step process involving
      the downloading, editing, and uploading of new or modified pages.</para>

      <para>For users with moderate technical skills, the creation of web
      pages using static HTML is fairly easy. But because the
      <emphasis>content</emphasis> is not separated from the
      <emphasis>code</emphasis>, a lot of time is spent wrapping the content
      with HTML code so that it can be presented in a meaningful way.
      Composing pages in static HTML is time-intensive and can interfere with
      content; it’s comparable to asking a book author to tackle typesetting,
      printing, and binding, which would certainly detract from the writer’s
      primary goal: to provide content.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Challenges of developing and maintaining a static HTML website</title>

        <para>Without the separation of code and content, many aspects of
        managing a static HTML site are difficult. It is complicated to
        establish the ‘look’ of a site, and not easy to change that look once
        set. Searching for information on a site, even one with a limited
        number of pages, is an inaccurate, time-consuming task. It is
        impractical to collaborate on pages with colleagues unless additional
        administrative (FTP) accounts are configured or access codes are
        shared; both scenarios present a security risk.</para>

        <para>For many people, HTML editing programs like FrontPage and
        DreamWeaver present a better approach to website design,
        implementation, and maintenance. These programs offer tools for
        defining a site-wide ‘look’ using site templates, as well as
        additional features to make it easier to create and edit static HTML
        pages. However, even when using these tools, adding or modifying
        content still requires a combination of writing and coding, which can
        be tricky and time consuming difficult to accomplish for anyone with
        lower than moderate technical skills.</para>

        <para>For example typical publication cycle for a static HTML site
        might follow this pattern: An article is written; then passed to the
        web maintainer who creates a new page (following the site’s design)
        either from a template or from scratch. The article is converted to
        HTML code and pasted into the new page; which, depending on the
        maintainer’s workload may take several hours or more to be posted on
        the website. The new page is uploaded to the website and then manually
        linked to other pages as necessary, with related pages updated as
        necessary. That’s a lot of time and a lot of work.</para>

        <para>In a limited number of contexts, static HTML may be quite
        suitable for a website. If the content on the site does not get
        updated frequently, is updated by a limited number of individuals,
        does not need to be searchable, does not require pleasant
        presentation, and if there is a technical individual who is willing to
        edit HTML and download &#38; upload changes, you may not need the
        advanced features of a Content Management System. However, before you
        put this book down and walk away, understand this: on the same
        hardware that runs your static HTML site, you can have a
        full-featured, easy-to-use Content Management System that makes
        updating content much easier and allows a huge variety of advanced
        features that simply were not available with static HTML sites.</para>

        <para>This represents a glance toward the past -- or maybe this is a
        look at the way you’re currently doing things, and you have found
        yourself with too much data to manage effectively. But there is a
        better way. A way that will allow you create and present meaningful
        content on your website without downloading, coding, and uploading --
        from anywhere on the Internet. A way that will allow advanced features
        -- features like site-wide searches, user accounts, private messages,
        and much more -- features that are simply not possible with static
        HTML.</para>

        <para>A <firstterm>Content Management System</firstterm> could be the
        solution to your problems.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>...a step toward the future.</title>

      <para>The answer to all the wasted time and effort of maintaining static
      HTML websites is to use a Content Management System. Static HTML was
      insufficient for the management of content on even a modest website; it
      was clearly too much data and too much work. Though HTML editing tools
      streamlined the procedure for maintaining a static HTML site, a better
      method of data management was necessary.</para>

      <para>Web technology unveiled new competitive scenarios for companies:
      improved customer interaction, better business-to-business
      communication, and a more vibrant distribution of internal information.
      Today, many companies are turning to the web as a new playing field for
      innovation; tapping a wide variety of content and delivering it
      instantly to users around the globe. Some of the key goals of a Content
      Management System (CMS) are to provide users with personalized,
      transparent access to relevant information inside and outside of the
      organization; and to allow authors to easily contribute information to
      the knowledge base by managing content in a reliable, secure, and
      dependable way.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Dynamic Content Management as the way of the future</title>

        <para>Content Management Systems allow content to be handled and
        updated dynamically and makes it easy for non-technical people to
        create and modify content. What is ‘dynamic content’? Dynamic content
        is content that may change frequently, is separated from the display
        (HTML) code, and is made into an ‘element’ that can be manipulated by
        the Content Management System. Dynamic content elements are usually
        stored in a database which is running the website.</para>

        <para>Good Content Management Systems are designed so that nearly
        anyone can publish, browse, and revise information without knowing
        much more than how to use a browser or a word processor. The technical
        details are hidden from site users, thus eliminating their need to
        learn about software programming, HTML, network protocols, or how and
        where to publish and retrieve files to work on them. With a click of a
        button, authorized users can contribute any content to areas of the
        site to which they have been granted access.</para>

        <para>Compared with static HTML, Content Management Systems:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Separate code from content making it easier to focus on
            content</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Offer a consistent, non-technical, easy-to-use interface for
            both users and administrators. Content contributors log into a
            secure area of the website, enter the date, title, and body of
            their news submission, and click submit, and the news article is
            published to the website with no hassle.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The entire look and feel of a website can be changed very
            easily. Some CMS packages even allow users to customize the way
            they see a website -- everything from language to colors to the
            on-screen placement of features.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Are feature-rich, and support additional, specialized
            features -- forums, galleries, live chat boards, private
            messaging, local weather, and more.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Are searchable because they rely on a database. This feature
            alone makes CMS an exceptional choice when compared to static
            HTML.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allow for community involvement and collaboration. While
            CMS-based sites can be run effectively by one person, the
            community can easily comment on a website’s content without
            requiring special access.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Gives administrators complete control over what each user or
            group of users can do within a web site. Administrators can
            control access to sections of a site, and assign user privileges
            and permissions to individuals or groups as we’ll see in Chapter
            XX.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Once users have made the transition to a CMS, they will no
        longer feel incapacitated and unable to contribute to the website
        community. Often, the availability of all the new features provided by
        a CMS can be intimidating at first, and the learning curve can appear
        rather steep when compared to a static HTML page because while a
        static HTML page does not allow community involvement, CMS readily
        welcome it. CMS managed sites are simply so much easier to maintain
        than static HTML sites. To update a CMS site, all you need to do is
        surf to it and click on links to update the site. So, if you know how
        to surf the ‘Net, you can maintain the site; very little other work is
        necessary!</para>

        <para>So far in this discussion, we have discussed only the most basic
        functions of a CMS, but there are hundreds of different functions
        available in an advanced Content Management System like Xaraya.
        Fortunately, it&#39;s fairly easy to learn the main functions,
        ignoring the rest of the features until you need to use them. This is
        another advantage of using a CMS instead of ordinary HTML pages: the
        advanced functionality allows users to search the site, post on
        forums, leave user information which is easily manageable -- in short,
        anything that can be done with advanced database management.</para>

        <para>A CMS implementation provides a win-win solution for business
        end-users, webmasters, and business management. It provides a complete
        environment that brings the power of distributed content management
        down to the average end-user, while at the same time addressing the
        most important requirements of the IT department, webmasters, and
        business management to provide a secure, fast, and effective portal;
        however commercial CMS packages (like Microsoft Content Management
        Server, Vignette, Stellent, and Obtree) can be prohibitively
        expensive. A quick internet search for commercial CMS packages reveals
        prices ranging from less than $99 through hundreds of thousands of
        dollars. Fortunately, there are several Open Source Software CMS
        solutions that cost very little or are completely free to use. Xaraya
        is a robust, free Content Management System that runs on all platforms
        that support the PHP scripting language, a web server, and a
        relational database management system (RDBMS).</para>

        <para>Open Source software is software which may be freely distributed
        and whose programming code is available and also modifiable by anyone,
        within the terms of a particular license.</para>

        <para>The basic idea behind Open Source Software is very simple: When
        programmers can study, redistribute, and modify the source code for a
        piece of software, that software evolves. People improve it, people
        adapt it, and people fix bugs. These modifications can be folded back
        into the development community, benefiting everyone. And this can
        happen at a speed that, if one is used to the slower pace of
        conventional software development, may seem astonishing.</para>

        <para>And you guessed it: the Xaraya Content Management System and all
        the pieces of software required to make it work are Open Source!</para>

        <para>In the next section we’ll take a closer look at Xaraya and
        explore some of the many features that it has to offer.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>An Overview of Xaraya</title>

    <subtitle>A quick look at how Xaraya works.</subtitle>

    <para>The documentation for this part of the Guide is being developed.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What are the basic building blocks of Xaraya? How do they
        interoperate?</para>

        <para>The Core (the files in the <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/includes</filename>
        directory) handles each page request. Modules provide units of
        functionality, and can be added, extended, or disabled as required.
        Some modules are mandatory, meaning that the core expects them to be
        available on the site. Other modules are optional and can be turned on
        or off as needed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What is an Article?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What is a Publication Type?</para>

        <para>Publication Types are specific &#34;types&#34; of Articles on
        the site (for example, News Articles, Frequently Asked Questions,
        Pictures, or Recipes are all examples of specific Article
        &#34;types&#34;). See the overview on <command>Admin-&#62;Articles</command>
        for more information.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What is a Template?</para>

        <para>A Template is a file that defines how content items on the site
        are displayed (rendered). A Template receives output from a module and
        formats the output according to various rules. Templates can be very
        simple or very sophisticated. A normal page typically consists of many
        templates, each nested within another.</para>

        <para>Each module has a default set of templates that it uses, but
        templates can be over-ridden by creating a Theme. You can switch
        Themes at will, and each request for a particular page will check if
        there is an over-riding Template in the current Theme before using a
        default template.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What is a Theme?</para>

        <para>Themes are a collection of templates, images, etc. that
        represent a particular Theme (layout, style, or skin) for your site.
        Typically, you would have at least the page templates in the Theme
        directory, and possibly some overrides for default module and block
        templates.</para>

        <para>Special themes include the &#34;print&#34; theme, where the page
        template does not include any blocks and so will only show the output
        of the main module function, and the &#34;rss&#34; theme, that
        doesn&#39;t generate XHTML at all but XML for syndication by other
        sites.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Are Articles, Publication Types, and Templates related? If so,
        how?</para>

        <para>Each Publication Type uses a specific template to display
        content of a particular type. This means each Publication Type can
        have a different layout or format.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How are Articles sorted into Sections/Categories/Topics?</para>

        <para>Articles can be placed into Categories (one or more). The
        Categories may mean different things from site to site, depending on
        how they were configured. The default Xaraya installation of the
        Articles module contains a set of Categories familiar to
        administrators of other Open Source CMS products (PHP-Nuke, PostNuke,
        Envolution, etc.) where news articles are categorised in two
        independent ways (Topics &#38; Categories) and documents are
        categoriesed into Sections.</para>

        <para>New Xaraya sites will often use generic categories across all
        Publication Types, instead of having separate hierarchies for each of
        them. See overview on <command>Admin-&#62;Articles</command> for more
        information.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How, and by what, are Articles displayed?</para>

        <para>Articles are displayed by the Articles module, in cooperation
        with a bunch of &#39;hooked&#39; utility modules (categories,
        hitcount, ratings, comments, and other modules).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>What do Categories do? Are they the only way of sorting
        Articles, or are they just an example?</para>

        <para>You can organize your Categories however you see fit -- the
        Categories provided at installation are just an example which may be
        modified, extended, or completely removed as you require.</para>

        <para>Articles can be browsed by Publication Type, by Category, and/or
        by Author, and sort the results by date, title, and other criteria.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Do Articles need to be sorted into a simple hierarchy or can
        they be sorted into a multidimensional array with each Article fitting
        into several independent hierarchies simultaneously or using category
        flags instead of a hierarchy at all?</para>

        <para>Each &#34;base category&#34; is organised as a hierarchy, but
        several independent base categories (and their hierarchies) can be
        assigned to each of the Publication Types in Articles.</para>

        <para>For instance, a travel site might have one hierarchy with
        countries and cities, and another hierarchy with particular interests
        (for example, culture, sports, restaurants, etc.). An Article about a
        restaurant in Brussels can, for example, be placed in the category
        &#34;Brussels&#34; and <emphasis>also</emphasis> in the category
        &#34;Restaurants&#34;, and people can then view all articles about
        Brussels, about restaurants, or about restaurants in Brussels.</para>

        <para>And if you work by Publication Type, you could let people browse
        only through reviews (a particular Publication Type) about restaurants
        in Brussels.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Features of Xaraya</title>

    <para>Xaraya is a buzzword-compliant, extensible, open source
    web-development software platform written in PHP and licensed under the
    GNU General Public License. Xaraya utilizes robust permissions, data
    management, and multilingual systems to dynamically integrate and manage
    content.</para>

    <para>Xaraya&#39;s modular, database-independent architecture provides
    tools which separate form, function, content, and design on the site.
    Xaraya delivers the requisite infrastructure for a fully dynamic
    multi-platform Content Management Solution (CMS).</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Database-driven website engine (PHP-ADODB compliant)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Extensible through a variety of third-party modules</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Powerful security module for multi-level user/administrator
        logins</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Distribute workload using User/Administrator management tools</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Robust article management system</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fully editable &#38; manageable News, Links, Downloads, and FAQ
        Sections</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>BlockLayout Theme Engine: Display your site your way</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>News Feed Manager: Access thousands of RSS-compliant news feeds</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Site Statistics: Tracks browser &#38; operating system, top news
        &#38; articles, and more</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Easy install on most Unix/Linux and Windows platforms</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Import information from PostNuke and Moveable Type installations</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Xaraya is compliant with RSS, CSS, XHTML, and W3C accessibility
        standards.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Xaraya reduces web site development costs by introducing
    sophisticated administration tools &#38; services which separate form,
    function, content, and design. With Xaraya, you work in a simple,
    structured environment to rapidly develop your website with diverse
    content, including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>News Articles</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Web Links Directory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Job Boards</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Frequently Asked Questions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>File Downloads</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Photo Gallery</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Member profiles</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Web forums (message boards)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Articles Repository (i.e.: Knowledge base, cooking recipes,
        product reviews, news articles, etc.)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>With more than forty active developers spanning five continents and
    ten languages, the Xaraya Development Team is a blend of some of the best
    and brightest developers in the open source community. We expect the best
    of one another. As a result, you can expect the best from Xaraya.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>What does Xaraya mean?</title>

    <para>The name <firstterm>Xaraya</firstterm> was selected by the
    development team after an internal contest. Submitted by Marty Vance
    (Dracos), Xaraya does not really mean anything. We were looking for a name
    which was both interesting and unique. Xaraya certainly fit the bill.</para>

    <para>That said, the word Xaraya is reminiscent of &#39;<foreignphrase>raya</foreignphrase>&#39;,
    the Spanish word for Manta Ray. The development team rather likes the
    nautical feel of that reference, particularly when one thinks of the
    Internet as an &#34;ocean&#34; of information. The Xaraya logo concept by
    Marty Vance, logo design by LaDalle Hunt.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>How is Xaraya pronounced?</title>

    <para>It is not as difficult as it may look. In fact, saying Xaraya is
    actually sort of fun. Phonetically, it looks like this:
    <firstterm>Zuh-rye-ah</firstterm>.</para>

    <para>To hear Xaraya pronounced by Xaraya Team member Marie Altobelli
    (LadyofDragons), visit <ulink
    url="http://www.xaraya.com/xcommon/media/xaraya.wav">http://www.xaraya.com/xcommon/media/xaraya.wav</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Assumptions</title>

    <para>Xaraya allows unprecedented levels of customization, it is therefore
    impossible to list every possible configuration. To provide familiarity
    with how Xaraya functions this Guide makes the following assumptions:</para>

    <para>* That you plan to run a Community Site and:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do not permit anonymous users to submit articles or post
        comments until they register.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Allow ALL users to read all articles &#38; related comments on
        the site.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Allow Registered users to:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Submit articles to the site.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Post comments.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Site Administrator(s) have complete access to the site.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>That you have created a web-readable &#34;<filename>images</filename>&#34;
        directory in your Xaraya installation directory (<filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/images</filename>).
        We will store any non-core and non-module images needed by the site in
        this directory.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>That you already have a working webserver (Apache or IIS), PHP
        4.1.2 or higher (4.2.x or higher is strongly recommended), an email
        subsystem, and a database (currently MySQL) installed, configured, and
        operating correctly. The installation and configuration of these tools
        are beyond the scope of this Guide. See <ulink
        url="http://www.php.net">http://www.php.net</ulink> and <ulink
        url="http://www.mysql.com">http://www.mysql.com</ulink> for assistance
        with these issues.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>