<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="hooks">
  <title>Hooks in Xaraya</title>

  <subtitle>An Introduction to Hooks</subtitle>

  <para>Hooks extend the functionality of modules by allowing site resources
  to be re-used in a variety of ways across the site. Hooks increase the
  interoperability and efficiency of Xaraya. For example, a site resource is
  BBCODE (which allows bbcode-style formatting to be used in text entry).
  Rather than code BBCODE for articles and re-code it again for comments, we
  can simply &#34;hook&#34; BBCODE functionality into the articles and
  comments modules, as well as any other modules we wish! Xaraya provides
  unparalleled levels of interoperability by truly modularizing functions.</para>

  <para>Xaraya provides two different methods to view or edit hooks.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;View All</command>: Click &#34;<guibutton>On/Off</guibutton>&#34;
      under the Hooks heading for the module to view or edit hooks that are
      enabled for the particular module. So, for example, if you wanted to
      view the active hooks for the Articles module, click &#34;<guibutton>On/Off</guibutton>&#34;
      under the Hooks heading for the Articles module. You see the modules
      that are &#39;hooked&#39; into this module, and can add or remove hooks.
      Be sure to click &#34;<guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
      changes.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure Hooks</command>: The
      simplest way to determine the order in which to click items to activate
      hooks is to fill in the blanks of this sentence: &#34;<userinput>I want
      to enable ____ in ____.</userinput>&#34; So, for example, if you wanted
      to enable <emphasis>comments</emphasis> in <emphasis>articles</emphasis>,
      you would first click <guibutton>comments</guibutton>, then CHECK
      <guibutton>articles</guibutton>. Be sure to click &#34;<guibutton>Save
      Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>These two methods serve the same purpose -- to display hooked modules
  and allow modification of hooks. Work with each of them to determine which
  of the methods suits you best.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure Hooks</command>:</para>

      <para>Using &#39;hooks&#39; in Xaraya, you can extend the functionality
      of your modules.</para>

      <para>Select the hook module providing the extra functionality and then
      check the box(es) of the module(s) in which you would like to enable
      that functionality (For example, select &#34;<command>Comments</command>&#34;
      and then check &#34;<command>Articles</command>&#34; to enable
      <emphasis>Comments</emphasis> within the <emphasis>Articles</emphasis>
      module.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect1 id="kr-hooks">
    <title>KNOWLEDGE REVIEW: Handling Hooks</title>

    <para>OTTO:</para>

    <para>(optional: The below should be included LATER in the docs, after the
    user has had a chance to read all the module overviews)</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><command>Admin-&#62;Adminpanels-&#62;Modify config</command>:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>CHECK Disable Module Overviews</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click &#34;Submit&#34; to save changes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
