<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Templates in Xaraya</title>

  <para>Xaraya displays information to site visitors by using
  <firstterm>TEMPLATES</firstterm>. Templates are available in the following
  varieties: &#34;function templates&#34;, &#34;block templates&#34;,
  &#34;page templates&#34;, &#34;block group templates&#34;, or module
  templates.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>&#34;<firstterm>Function Templates</firstterm>&#34; are Content
      Layout templates that display a view of a particular function of Xaraya.
      Xaraya separates function templates for users and administrators. User
      function templates have &#34;user-&#34; at the beginning of the template
      filename, and administrator function templates have &#34;admin-&#34; at
      the beginning of the template filename. For example, one of Xaraya&#39;s
      default function templates is called &#39;<filename>user-display-news</filename>&#39;.
      This template defines the layout of the news area in your page as it is
      displayed to users of the site. The administrator view is defined by the
      &#39;<filename>admin-display-news</filename>&#39; template).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#34;<firstterm>Page Templates</firstterm>&#34; are Content Layout
      templates that display a view of a whole page, which can include
      function and block templates. These files reside in the
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/pages</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#34;<firstterm>Block Templates</firstterm>&#34; are Block Layout
      templates that display a view of a particular block within Xaraya. Block
      templates exist in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates/blocks</filename>,
      creating directories as necessary (give new directories appropriate
      permissions). So, for the articles module, the block templates exist in
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/articles/xartemplates/blocks</filename>.</para>

      <para>Customize default block templates with the equivalent &#34;<filename>.xt</filename>&#34;
      override template in the <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/blocks</filename>
      directory, creating directories as necessary (give new directories
      appropriate permissions). You also have specific override custom block
      templates that you name when you create a new block. The name of the
      template file (without the &#34;<filename>.xt</filename>&#34; extension)
      is entered into the custom template field when creating a block
      instance. These specific override template files are in the
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/blocks</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#34;<firstterm>Block Group Templates</firstterm>&#34; are Block
      Layout templates that contain a collection of individual block
      templates. The Block Group template files reside in the
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/blocks</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>&#34;<firstterm>&#60;module_name&#62;.xt Template</firstterm>&#34;
      is a Content Layout template that overrides the default page template
      for &#60;module_name&#62;. These files reside in the
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/pages</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Function templates, block templates, page templates, and block group
  templates can be defined as either site-wide or theme-specific. It is
  advisable to make template files theme-specific by default. By doing so, you
  minimize the amount of work necessary if you decide to add additional themes
  to the site later.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><firstterm>Site-Wide templates</firstterm>: A site-wide template
      is used to change the look &#38; feel of the site, no matter what theme
      is being used. Site-wide templates are overridden by theme-specific
      templates, if one exists. These files exist in the <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><firstterm>Theme-specific templates</firstterm>: Theme-specific
      templates change the look &#38; feel of the site only when displayed
      through a particular theme. These files exist in the
      <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename>
      directory.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>If template files exist in both site-wide, theme-specific locations,
  the theme-specific templates take precedence over site-wide templates.</para>
</chapter>