<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Articles Module</title>

  <subtitle>Display articles. <command>Admin-&#62;Articles</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Articles module is possibly the most often-accessed part of a
  community site, since nearly all of the site&#39;s content will be placed
  into Article sub-categories.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Articles</command></para>

      <para>Click View Articles to view a listing of articles on the site by
      Publication Type. If there are multiple pages of articles, navigation
      links are displayed at the bottom of the panel. (The number of articles
      displayed per page is defined in <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Modify
      config</command>. Click the Publication Type and set &#34;<guibutton>Items
      per page</guibutton>&#34; to the number of articles to be displayed.
      Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Configuration</guibutton>&#34; to save
      changes.)</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Publication Type: From the listing of available Publication
          Types, click the Publication Type for which you would like to
          display articles. For example, to display articles in the Web Links
          Publication Type, click &#34;<guibutton>Web Links</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Status: This is a filter that displays articles in the
          selected Publication Type that match one of the following options.
          Following our example above, to display Approved articles in the Web
          Links Publication Type, click &#34;<guibutton>Approved</guibutton>&#34;.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>All: Display all articles in the currently-selected
              Publication Type.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Submitted: Display articles in the currently-selected
              Publication Type that have been submitted for publication.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rejected: Display articles in the currently-selected
              Publication Type that have been rejected for publication.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Approved: Display articles in the currently-selected
              Publication Type that have been approved for publication.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Frontpage: Display articles in the currently-selected
              Publication Type that have been approved for publication and are
              displayed on the front page of the module. If this module is the
              current default starting module (set in <command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Modify
              config</command>), then articles with this status will also be
              displayed on the front page of the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Browse in: This is a filter that displays articles in the
              selected Publication Type based on the Category to which the
              article is assigned. Click the Category next to &#34;Browse
              in&#34; to display a panel with available Categories. Click a
              Category to display its articles.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>New Article: Click New Article to add a new article to the
          site as administrator. In the panel that appears, select the
          Publication Type for the new article. Enter the article in the text
          fields. The available text fields may be different between
          Publication Types, but Publication Types will have a Categories box
          at the bottom of the panel. From the Categories box, select the
          Categories to which the new article will be assigned. Click &#34;<guibutton>Preview</guibutton>&#34;
          to display the article without saving, and click &#34;<guibutton>Add
          Article</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>List of articles on the site. The bottom of this panel
          displays a listing of articles on the site for the
          currently-selected Publication Type.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Title: The title of the article.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Publication Date: The article&#39;s publication date and
              time.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Status: The status of the article. Status can be
              &#34;Submitted&#34;, &#34;Rejected&#34;, &#34;Approved&#34;, or
              &#34;Frontpage&#34;. See below for information about these
              statuses.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Checkbox: To change the status of currently-listed
              articles in a batch, place a CHECK in this box next to each
              article you wish to add to the batch. From the &#34;Change
              checked article status to&#34; drop-down list, below, select the
              status to which the checked articles will be changed. Click
              &#34;Change Status&#34; to change the status of all checked
              articles.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Options:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>View: Click this link to view the article as it is
                  displayed to a user of the site. An &#34;[Edit]&#34; link
                  displayed at the top of the article is shown only to users
                  with appropriate editing privileges.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Edit: Click this link to edit the article. Make
                  changes to the article in the panel and click
                  &#34;Preview&#34; to display the modified article without
                  saving, and click &#34;Update Article&#34; to save changes.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Delete: To delete a specific article, click this link
                  next to the article. Confirm your intention to delete the
                  article on the following panel. If you choose to delete an
                  article, all comments associated with the article are
                  deleted at the same time.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Change checked article status to:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Submitted: The article has been submitted to the site,
                  but has not yet been rejected or approved. This article is
                  visible only to the site administrator; it is not visible to
                  users.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Rejected: The article has been submitted to the site,
                  but has not been approved for publication. This article is
                  visible only to the site administrator; it is not visible to
                  users.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Approved: The article has been submitted to the site
                  and has been approved for publication. This article is
                  visible to site visitors and the site administrator. To view
                  this article, navigate to the Publication Type and Category
                  of the article, then click the title of the article to
                  display.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Frontpage: The article has been submitted to the site
                  and has been approved for publication. This article is
                  visible to site visitors and the site administrator. The
                  article is displayed on the front page of the module, and if
                  this module is the default starting module, then it will be
                  on the front page of the site. Articles with this status may
                  also be displayed by navigating to the Publication Type and
                  Category of the article, then clicking the title of the
                  article.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Click &#34;<command>Change Status</command>&#34; to
                  save changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Add Article</command></para>

      <para>Click Add Article to add a new article to the site as
      administrator. In the panel that appears, select the Publication Type
      for the new article. Enter the article in the text fields. The available
      text fields may be different between Publication Types, but Publication
      Types will have a Categories box at the bottom of the panel. From the
      Categories box, select the Categories to which the new article will be
      assigned. Click &#34;<guibutton>Preview</guibutton>&#34; to display the
      article without saving, and click &#34;<guibutton>Add Article</guibutton>&#34;
      to save changes.</para>

      <para>If you wish to insert a PAGE BREAK in an article, enter
      <userinput>&#60;!--pagebreak--&#62;</userinput> in the article text
      (either the Introduction or Body Text) where you&#39;d like the break to
      appear. Xaraya automatically manages the page break.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Import Webpages</command></para>

      <para>If you need to import any existing HTML pages into your Xaraya
      site (for example, if you are converting your site from a &#39;flat&#39;
      HTML site to a content management system), the Import Webpages tool will
      facilitate the process. Use this tool to define existing HTML page(s) to
      import into the Xaraya database structure. The imported pages become
      available as articles in the Publication Type selected during import.
      The Import Webpages tool provides filtering and replacement options
      during import.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Base Directory: This is the local directory which is
          recursively searched for pages ending with &#34;<filename>HTML</filename>&#34;
          or &#34;<filename>HTM</filename>&#34; (<emphasis>case insensitive</emphasis>).
          The resulting HTML pages are listed in this box. If you change the
          directory, click &#34;<guibutton>Refresh</guibutton>&#34; to reload
          the listing of available files.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Available HTML Pages: Highlight the HTML page or pages you
          would like to import in this box. You can select multiple individual
          pages by holding the CTRL key down and left-clicking on the desired
          HTML pages. To select a range of pages, left-click the first page in
          the range, hold the SHIFT key down while left-clicking the last page
          in the range. Selected pages are highlighted.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Publication Type: From this drop-down list, select the
          Publication Type to which the imported HTML page will be assigned.
          Once the Publication Type is selected, the panel will refresh,
          showing additional options.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Insert Page Title into field: From this drop-down list of
              fields available in the selected Publication Type, select the
              field into which the HTML page&#39;s title will be inserted.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Insert Content into Field: From this drop-down list of
              fields available in the selected Publication Type, select the
              field into which the HTML page&#39;s content will be inserted.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Initial Categories: Select the categories to which the
              imported article will be assigned. If multiple HTML pages are
              imported, all will be assigned to the same category.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Filter Start of Page: This page indicates material to be
          filtered (removed) from the imported webpage. The default regular
          expression is &#34;<userinput>#^.*&#60;body[^&#62;]*&#62;#is</userinput>&#34;
          (no quotes), which removes everything before the HTML &#60;body&#62;
          tag. The original HTML page is not modified.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Filer End of Page: The default regular expression is &#34;<userinput>#&#60;/body.*$#is</userinput>&#34;
          (no quotes), which removes everything after the HTML &#60;/body&#62;
          tag. The original HTML page is not modified.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Find Page Title: The default regular expression is &#34;<userinput>#&#60;title&#62;(.*?)&#60;/title&#62;#is</userinput>&#34;
          (no quotes), which indicates that the page title is between the
          &#60;title&#62; and &#60;/title&#62; HTML tags.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Replacement Rules: Xaraya will search your source HTML page
          and replace matching search text with replacement text. This is
          useful, for example, if you&#39;ve changed the path to graphic
          files.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Search for: Enter the text to be replaced.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Replace with: Enter the text to replace found text.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Test Import button: Click this button to perform a test import
          of the HTML page without adding the article to the site. Examine the
          resulting page to insure that everything worked as expected.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Import Webpages button: When ready to perform the import of
          HTML pages into Xaraya, click this button. The HTML pages are
          imported and the article is added to the site. The original HTML
          pages are not modified.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Publication Types</command></para>

      <para>This portion of the panel displays existing Publication Types with
      options to edit or delete.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>New Publication Type: Click this link to add a new Publication
          Type.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>New Publication Type</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Type: The title of the new Publication Type. This is
                  the &#34;system&#34; name of the Publication Type, and is
                  also the name used when referring to this Publication Type
                  in a Short URL.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Description: A description of the Publication Type.
                  The description is used on the site to denote the
                  Publication Type. The contents of this field are displayed
                  to site visitors.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Configuration</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Field: The field name for the new Publication Type.
                  This field name is used by themes to denote where pieces of
                  content are displayed within the theme. For example, the
                  field named &#34;title&#34; is displayed through placement
                  of the string &#34;#$title#&#34; within the theme
                  definition.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Label: The label for the new Publication Type. The
                  label serves as a description of the Publication Type, and
                  is displayed to users. Leave the Label field blank if you do
                  not want to use a particular field in your new Publication
                  Type.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Format: From this drop-down list, select the format
                  for the field.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Static Text:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Text Box:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Small Text Area:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Medium Text Area:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Large Text Area:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Username:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Calendar:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>File Upload:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Status:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>URL:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Image:</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>HTML Page:</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Input: CHECK this box if you would like the field to
                  accept input. If you do not with for the field to accept
                  input, UNCHECK this box.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Type: A reference area displaying the database type
                  for the field.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create</guibutton>&#34; to save
                  changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Existing Publication Types</para>

          <para>Existing Publication Types are listed in the bottom portion of
          this panel, with the following information &#38; options.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Name: The name of the Publication Type.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Description: A description of the Publication Type.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Options:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Edit:</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Delete: To delete a Publication Type, click this link
                  next to the Publication Type to be deleted. Confirm your
                  intention to delete on the next panel. If you delete a
                  Publication Type, all articles contained in the Publication
                  Type are also deleted.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Article Config:</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Global Configuration (&#39;Default&#39;
                      Publication Type only)</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Default Publication Type for the Articles
                          &#34;Front Page&#34;: From this drop-down list,
                          select the Publication Type to which a
                          &#34;frontpage&#34; alias will be assigned.
                          Generally, &#34;<guibutton>News</guibutton>&#34; is
                          an appropriate Publication Type for this field.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Support Short URLs: This box is the
                          &#39;master switch&#39; for Short URL support in
                          articles. CHECK this box to enable Short URL support
                          for articles. UNCHECK this box to disable Short URL
                          support for modules. Short URL support may be
                          enabled or disabled for individual Publication
                          Types, so it is possible to have some Publication
                          Types support Short URLs while others do not. In
                          order for Short URL support to function, the
                          &#39;master switch&#39; for Short URLs must be
                          CHECKED in <command>Admin-&#62;Base-&#62;Modify
                          config</command>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Website Configuration</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Use &#60;alias&#62; as alias in Short URLs:
                          CHECK this box to use the Publication Type&#39;s
                          type as the Short URL for this Publication Type. The
                          Type is configured when adding a new Publication
                          Type under <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Publication
                          Types</command>. To turn off Short URL support for
                          this specific Publication Type, UNCHECK this box.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Use different page template: You can define
                          custom display templates for each Publication Type.
                          To tell Xaraya to use a different template for a
                          Publication Type, enter the name of the template
                          file in this field. Enter the filename without the
                          &#34;<userinput>.xt</userinput>&#34; extension. To
                          use the default page template, leave this field
                          blank. See TEMPLATES IN XARAYA for a thorough
                          discussion of templates.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Overview Configuration</para>

                      <note>
                        <para>The ($...) indicates the name of the variable
                        used to display this feature in site templates. If you
                        wish to enable a specific feature to a template, add
                        the name of the variable to the template at the
                        location where you want the feature to appear.</para>
                      </note>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Default start view: From this drop-down list,
                          select the default behavior of Xaraya when a user
                          clicks on the name of a Publication Type from the
                          user&#39;s (not the Administration) main menu.</para>

                          <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                              <para>Latest items:</para>
                            </listitem>

                            <listitem>
                              <para>Browse in...: <emphasis>(recommended)</emphasis></para>
                            </listitem>
                          </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Number of columns ($numcols): The number of
                          columns that will display the data to site visitors.
                          If you would like a traditional, single-column
                          display, enter &#34;<userinput>1</userinput>&#34; in
                          this field. If you would like a two-column display,
                          enter &#34;<userinput>2</userinput>&#34; in this
                          field, and so on.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Items per page ($number): Determines the
                          maximum number of items to display per page in the
                          overview panel. If you would like to display 25
                          items per page, enter &#34;<userinput>25</userinput>&#34;
                          here. Xaraya provides page navigation links if there
                          are more than this number of items.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show category links in article summaries
                          ($categories): If CHECKED, category links are
                          displayed in article summaries in the overview
                          panel. If UNCHECKED, category links are not
                          displayed in article summaries.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show previous/next category ($showprevnext):
                          If CHECKED, previous/next category links are
                          displayed on the overview, which allow a site
                          visitor to move more easily between categories. If
                          UNCHECKED, previous/next category links are not
                          displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show number of comments ($comments): If
                          CHECKED, the number of comments associated with the
                          article are displayed in the overview panel. If
                          UNCHECKED, the number of comments are not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show hit counts ($counter): If CHECKED, the
                          number of hits received by the article are displayed
                          in the overview panel. If UNCHECKED, the
                          article&#39;s hits are not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show ratings ($rating): If CHECKED, article
                          ratings are displayed on the article overview panel.
                          If UNCHECKED, article ratings are not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show links to Publication Types ($showpublinks
                          + includes/publinks.xd): If CHECKED, a link-bar is
                          displayed near the top of the center panel of the
                          site that displays quick links to Publication Types
                          and, in parenthesis, the number of articles within
                          the Publication Type, for example:</para>

                          <para><emphasis>News Articles (403) - Documents (28)
                          - FAQs (16) - Web Links (310)</emphasis></para>

                          <para>If UNCHECKED, the links are not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show link to archives ($archivelink +
                          $archivelabel): If CHECKED, a link to the site&#39;s
                          archives is displayed in the overview. In the
                          default Xaraya theme, this link is at the bottom of
                          the page. The Archives show a listing of the stories
                          published per month. If UNCHECKED, the link to the
                          archives is not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show link to article map ($maplink +
                          $maplabel): If CHECKED, a link to the site&#39;s
                          article map is displayed in the overview. In the
                          default Xaraya theme, this link is at the bottom of
                          the page. If UNCHECKED, the link to the article map
                          is not displayed.</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Call transform hooks in summaries: To display
                          text with the output of any &#39;transforming&#39;
                          hooks, CHECK this box. For example, if you have
                          hooked BBCODE into ARTICLES and would like the
                          Article summary page (typically Frontpage or Article
                          overview) to show the output of BBCODE, CHECK this
                          box. If you wish to show the raw text, UNCHECK this
                          box.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Article Display Configuration</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Show link to previous/next article in display
                          ($prevart + $nextart): OTTO</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Configuration of Hooked Modules</para>

                      <para>OTTO</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Categories</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>[New]:</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Number of possible categories:</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Base category for articles (#):</para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
                          to save changes.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Modify config:</para>

      <para>This panel allows modification of configuration options for this
      module.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Adding a new Publication Type</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Adding a new Publication Type that uses Dynamic Data</title>

    <para>In this advanced example, we will configure a new Publication Type
    for Recipes. We will add the new Publication Type, enable Dynamic Data,
    add Dynamic Data fields to our new Publication Type, add appropriate
    Categories, attach the new Publication Type to the new Categories, add
    Templates for the new Publication Type, and finally, add an article (a
    recipe!) to the new Publication Type. This example assumes you are
    starting from a fresh, brand-spanking-new, just-installed Xaraya Base
    installation.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>LOG IN AS A XARAYA ADMINISTRATOR: This is done any time you wish
        to have Administrator access to your Xaraya site.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CREATE A NEW PUBLICATION TYPE: This is done for each custom
        Publication Type you create.</para>

        <para>To create the new Publication Type, go to
        Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Publication Types. Click &#34;New&#34;.
        Complete the fields as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Type: recipes <emphasis>(NOTE: Lower case.)</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Description: Recipe Collection</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Field: title</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Label: Recipe Title</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Format: Text Box</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Input: CHECKED</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Field: summary</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Label: Description</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Format: Small Text Area</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Input: CHECKED</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Field: bodytext</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Label: Ingredients</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Format: Large Text Area</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Input: CHECKED</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Field: bodyfile</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Label: <emphasis>(this field should be blank)</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Format: <emphasis>(as long as Label, above, is blank and
                Input, below is UNCHECKED, it does not matter what this field
                contains)</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Input: UNCHECKED</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Field: notes</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Label: Instructions</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Format: Large Text Area</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Input: CHECKED</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Do not modify the last 3 fields (authorid, pubdate, and status);
        leave them as they are. Click &#34;<guibutton>Create</guibutton>&#34;
        to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ENABLE DYNAMIC DATA FOR ARTICLES/RECIPES: This is done for each
        custom Publication Type using Dynamic Data you create, unless Dynamic
        Data has previously been enabled for the module.</para>

        <para>To enable Dynamic Data for a Publication Type, go to
        <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure Hooks</command>. We want to
        enable Dynamic Data within Articles, so click &#34;<guibutton>dynamicdata</guibutton>&#34;
        and CHECK the box for Articles and the &#39;Recipe Collection&#39;
        sub-category under Articles. Click &#34;<guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ADD DYNAMIC DATA FIELD(S) TO THE NEW PUBLICATION TYPE: This is
        done for each custom Publication Type using Dynamic Data you create.</para>

        <para>To add dynamic data field(s) to the new publication type, go to
        <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Publication Types</command>. Find
        the &#39;recipes&#39; Publication Type that we created in CREATE A NEW
        PUBLICATION TYPE, above, and click Article Config next to it. Near the
        bottom of the next screen, you&#39;ll see &#34;Dynamic Data Fields
        [modify]&#34;. Click &#34;<guibutton>[modify]</guibutton>&#34; and in
        the new window that opens, enter the Dynamic Data as follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Label: photo <emphasis>(NOTE: Lower case.)</emphasis></para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Property Type: Image</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Data Source: dynamic_data</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Status: Active</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Properties</guibutton>&#34; to save
        changes. Close the window and return to the previous browser window
        for the rest of the steps.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ADD A NEW CATEGORY (AND OPTIONAL SUB-CATEGORIES) FOR THE NEW
        PUBLICATION TYPE: This is done for each custom Publication Type you
        create.</para>

        <para>To add the new category (and optional sub-categories), go to
        <command>Admin-&#62;Categories</command>. Click &#34;<guibutton>Add
        Category</guibutton>&#34; to add a new Category. For this example:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create a new Category called &#34;Recipes Category&#34; by
            following the steps below.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Name: Recipes Category</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Description: This is the recipes category for this site.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In relation to this category: Generic1</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Position: Right before, in the same level</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Optional image: categoryrecipes_top.jpg</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Add</guibutton>&#34; to add the
                new category.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create three sub-categories: &#34;Appetizers &#38;
            Soups&#34;, &#34;Breads &#38; Baked Goods&#34;, and finally
            &#34;Desserts&#34;. To create the &#34;Appetizers &#38; Soups&#34;
            sub-category, click &#34;Add Category&#34; and follow these steps:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Name: Appetizers &#38; Soups</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Description: Soups and Appetizer recipes go here.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In relation to this category: Recipes Category</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Position: The first child category</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Optional image: categorysoups.jpg</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Add</guibutton>&#34; to add the
                new category.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To create the next two sub-categories, click &#34;Add
            Category&#34; and follow these steps:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Name: Breads &#38; Baked Goods</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Description: Breads &#38; baked goods recipes go here.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In relation to this category: Recipes Category /
                Appetizers &#38; Soups</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Position: Right after, in the same level</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Optional image: categorybaked.jpg</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Click &#34;Add&#34; to add the new category.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create another sub-category, typing &#34;Desserts&#34; in
            the Name field, &#34;Dessert recipes go here&#34; for the
            Description, and &#34;categorydesserts.jpg&#34; as the image.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ADD THE NEW PUBLICTION TYPE TO A CATAGORY: This is done for each
        custom Publication Type you create.</para>

        <para>To add Publication Types to Categories, go to
        <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Modify config</command> and click on
        the description of the Publication Type we created (in this example,
        it&#39;s &#34;Recipe Collection&#34;). Scroll down, and you&#39;ll
        see:</para>

        <para><emphasis>Number of possible categories: 0</emphasis></para>

        <para>Change the &#34;<userinput>0</userinput>&#34; to &#34;<userinput>1</userinput>&#34;.</para>

        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Configuration</guibutton>&#34; to
        save changes.</para>

        <para>After the screen refreshes, scroll to the bottom of the center
        section and select the Category for the new Publication Type. In this
        example, if it&#39;s not already selected, select &#34;Recipes
        Category&#34; that we created above. Click &#34;<guibutton>Update
        Configuration</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CONFIGURE THE NEW PUBLICATION TYPE: This is done for each custom
        Publication Type you create.</para>

        <para>Still in <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Modify config</command>,
        click on the description of the publication type we just created (in
        this example, it&#39;s &#34;Recipe Collection&#34;). Make the
        following changes:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use &#39;recipes&#39; as alias in short URLs: CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Default start view: Browse in Recipes Category</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Number of columns ($numcols): 1</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Items per page ($number): 10</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show category links in article summaries ($categories):
            CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show previous/next category ($showprevnext): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show number of comments ($comments): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show hit counts ($counter): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show ratings ($rating): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show links to publication types ($showpublinks +
            includes/publinks.xd): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show link to archives ($archivelink + $archivelabel):
            CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show link to article map ($maplink + $maplabel): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Call transform hooks in summaries: UNCHECKED</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Show link to previous/next article in display ($prevart +
            $nextart): CHECKED</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>NOTE: Items enclosed in parenthesis above are the names of the
        variables used in templates.</para>

        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Configuration</guibutton>&#34; to
        save changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ADD TEMPLATES FOR THE NEW PUBLICTION TYPE: This can be done for
        each custom Publication Type you create.</para>

        <para>We can create up to three custom display templates to tell
        Xaraya specifically how to display this new Publication Type. Example
        files are included in this tutorial distribution. If you do not create
        a template, Xaraya will attempt to display the Publication Type using
        a default template.</para>

        <para>Template files are placed into the <filename>&#60;webdir&#62;/modules/articles/xartemplates</filename>
        directory, and should be called &#39;<filename>user-display-&#60;pubtype&#62;.xd</filename>&#39;,
        &#39;<filename>user-summary-&#60;pubtype&#62;.xd</filename>&#39;, and
        (optionally) &#39;<filename>user-view-&#60;pubtype&#62;.xd</filename>&#39;,
        where <filename>&#60;pubtype&#62;</filename> is the name of the
        Publication Type (in this tutorial, <filename>&#60;pubtype&#62;</filename>
        is &#34;recipes&#34; as created in step #2 above):</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>user-display-recipes.xd -- this is the main view of the data</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>user-summary-recpies.xd -- this is a summary view of the
            data</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>user-view-recipes.xd <emphasis>(optional)</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you wish to create theme-specific versions of these files,
        rename the files from <filename>*.xd</filename> to
        <filename>*.xt</filename> and place the theme-specific version in the
        <filename>&#60;webdir&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/articles</filename>
        directory, creating directories as necessary. It is recommended that
        you begin by examining the example files included with this tutorial,
        or open one of the sample templates provided with Xaraya and make
        changes as necessary using your favorite HTML editor. Where ever you
        want to display the fields in the new Publication Type, enter
        &#34;#$fieldname#&#34; (no quotes) in the template. Xaraya will
        replace &#34;#$fieldname#&#34; with the contents of the field as
        stored in the database. In this tutorial, we created the following
        fields, which are available for display in the template using the
        #$fieldname# indicated in parenthesis:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>title (#$title#)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>summary (#$summary#)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>bodytext (#$bodytext#)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>notes (#$notes#)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>photo (#$photo#)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The templates included with this tutorial distribution expect to
        find a file called &#34;<filename>NoPhoto.gif</filename>&#34; in the
        <filename>&#60;webdir&#62;/images/recipes/</filename> directory of
        your website. This file is displayed if a Photograph URL is not
        provided in the article submission, and is included with this tutorial
        distribution. Copy <filename>NoPhoto.gif</filename> to the
        <filename>&#60;webdir&#62;/images/recipes/</filename> directory,
        creating directories as necessary.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ADD AN ARTICLE TO THE NEW PUBLICATION TYPE: This is done for
        each custom Publication Type you create.</para>

        <para>Now you can add articles to the new publication type. Click
        <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Add Article</command> and click on
        the name of the new Publication Type (in this example, it&#39;s Recipe
        Collection). A sample recipe is included with this tutorial (<filename>SampleRecipe.txt</filename>).</para>

        <para>Enter the Recipe Title, Description, Ingredients, Directions,
        and a URL for the photograph for the recipe. Select the appropriate
        Category for the recipe, and click &#34;<guibutton>Preview</guibutton>&#34;
        to see what the recipe will look like, or click &#34;<guibutton>Add
        Article</guibutton>&#34; to save it.</para>

        <para>On the following page, approve the article by putting a CHECK in
        the STATUS box, and selecting &#34;<guibutton>Approved</guibutton>&#34;
        from the drop-down list at the bottom of the page. Click &#34;<guibutton>Change
        Status</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>LOGOUT FROM THE ADMINISTRATOR ACCOUNT: It is a wise idea, though
        technically not required, to log out of your administrator account at
        the end of each session. To log out of your Xaraya administrator
        account, click <guibutton>[admin logout]</guibutton>, which appears at
        the bottom of the Administration menu. Confirm your intention to log
        out by clicking &#34;<guibutton>Logout</guibutton>&#34;, or click
        &#34;<guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>&#34; to abort the logout.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Extending the Gallery Publication Type</title>

    <para>OTTO: Speak with mcortez about adding thumbnails, importing, etc.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>