<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>BBCode Module</title>

  <subtitle>Enables BBCode formatting.</subtitle>

  <para>This module does not have an administration panel.</para>

  <para>Enables BBCode formatting markup tags in text fields on the site. When
  BBCode is activated for a module, that module will allow entry &#38; display
  of BBCode tags. BBCode is a markup language that allows, among other
  options, making text bold by enclosing it in &#34;[b]&#34; and
  &#34;[/b]&#34; markups (for example, &#34;[b]Bold Text[/b]&#34;).</para>

  <para>When this module has been hooked to another module (for example, if
  you enable BBCode in Articles), an editor page will display BBCode
  formatting quick-buttons. If text in a text field is highlighted, it can be
  transformed by clicking one of the BBCode quick-buttons. For example, if
  text was highlighted in a text area and the &#34;I&#34; (italics) BBCode
  quick-button was clicked, the italics tags would be added before and after
  the highlighted text.</para>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Adding BBCode / BBClick to a Publication Type</title>

    <para>To add BBCode formatting capability or BBClick transformation to a
    Publication Type, follow these steps:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure Hooks</command>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click BBCode to select it as the module providing extra
        functionality. The panel will refresh, and you will see a list of
        modules to which the BBCode module can be hooked.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CHECK the module(s) in which you would like to enable BBCode
        formatting. For our example, CHECK &#34;<guibutton>all articles</guibutton>&#34;
        and &#34;<guibutton>comments</guibutton>&#34;. Click &#34;<guibutton>Save
        Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Articles-&#62;Add Article</command>. Click
    the &#34;<guibutton>News Articles</guibutton>&#34; Publication Type. On
    the resulting panel, the BBCode Form Controls are displayed above the
    Category selector box. Using these controls, or by manually entering
    BBCode formatting markup, BBCode can be used in articles.</para>

    <para>To add BBClick capability, just go through the steps again
    substituting BBClick for BBCode.</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>