<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Addressbook Module</title>

  <subtitle>Modules Distribution, Xaraya address book module.
  <command>Admin-&#62;Addressbook</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Addressbook module provides a configurable address book for your
  site. Entries in the address book can be made private (viewable only by the
  person who entered the item) or public (viewable by all users with access to
  this module).</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Modify config</command>:</para>

      <para>This panel allows modification of configuration options for this
      module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Access level:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Grant Rights for an unregistered user:</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Grant Rights for a registered user:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>View: To give unregistered/registered users VIEW
                  access to the address book, CHECK this box. To prohibit
                  unregistered/registered users from VIEWING the address book,
                  UNCHECK this box.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Create: To allow unregistered/registered users to
                  CREATE entries in the address book, CHECK this box. To
                  prohibit unregistered/registered users from CREATING entries
                  in the address book, UNCHECK this box.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Edit/Delete: To allow unregistered/registered users
                  EDIT/DELETE access to the address book, CHECK this box. To
                  prohibit unregistered/registered users from EDITING/DELETING
                  items from the address book, UNCHECK this box.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Other settings:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Title of this Address book: In this field, enter the name
              of the address book as it will be displayed to users.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default sort order / List View: Select two columns of your
              choice. This setting affects not only the sort order but also
              the display of columns in the list view. Users may select
              between the Default and Alternate sort orders.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Alternate sort order / List View: Select two columns of
              your choice. This setting affects not only the sort order but
              also the display of columns in the list view. Users may select
              between the Default and Alternate sort orders.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Name display in list view and sort order for name
              information: This setting determines the sort order and display
              of names in the list view. You can change the default «Last
              Name, First Name» to «First Name Last Name».</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Special character (Umlauts) replacement for sort columns:
              Names and companies are stored in special sort columns for
              correct sorting when special characters (such as Umlauts) are
              used. This Admin setting allows you to set up the character
              replacement to correct the sort for each language.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Personal address book mode: The Address Book module may be
              used as a Global address book (UNCHECKED (default)) or a
              Personal address book (CHECKED). As a Global address book
              (UNCHECKED) all users with appropriate access may view records
              that are NOT marked Private. As a Personal address book
              (CHECKED) users may only view entries they have created and
              unregistered users may not view or create any entries.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Do you want to use a prefix field?: Prefix/Title (Mr.,
              Mrs., etc.) values can be set in <command>Admin-&#62;Addressbook-&#62;Name
              Prefixes</command> panel and are optionally selected via a
              drop-down list when creating/editing an entry. This field is
              hidden (UNCHECKED) by default. If you wish to use a prefix
              field, CHECK this box.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Do you want to use images/logos?: Administrators will see
              a selection box of all files in the <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/Addressbook/xarimages</filename>
              and can assign an image to a record. The image is shown in the
              upper right corner of the detail page. Currently, all pictures
              must be manually uploaded into the <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/Addressbook/xarimages</filename>
              directory. This field is hidden (UNCHECKED) by default. If you
              wish to use images/logos, CHECK this box.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Disable the menu: If you wish to use the Addressbook
              module as a simple contact list, you can disable the menu
              completely. You can also disable it for guests only. Note,
              Administrators always see the full menu, regardless of this
              setting. Select from the drop-down list.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Enabled for all: Everyone can see the menu.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Disabled for all: No one can see the menu.
                  Administrators always see the full menu.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Disabled only for guests: The menu is disabled for
                  unregistered users, but displayed to registered users.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Disable the second line of the main menu: Disables the
              display of the second menu line only. Users have access to the
              categories, sort order, and the search field, but not to Private
              records, A-Z / Complete list view switch, and the Add New Record
              link.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show zip before city: If you would like to display the
              postal/zip code before the city, CHECK this box. Otherwise,
              UNCHECK this box.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Records viewed per page: How many Addresses would you like
              to display per page? Enter that value into this field, for
              example, &#34;<userinput>25</userinput>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Hide the Copyright and Version Note: If you wish to hide
              the version number and copyright notice of this module, CHECK
              this box. To display the version number and copyright notice of
              this module, UNCHECK this box.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Custom labels:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Custom tab (if empty, no custom fields are displayed):
              Name of the Custom Fields tab and the headline for custom fields
              in the detail panel. Leave blank if you do not use custom
              fields.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Width of TEXTAREA fields: The width of the TEXTAREA field
              can change depending on the settings of your theme. Sometimes
              this results in a very bad layout for your form. You can set the
              HTML COLS of a TEXTAREA field in this box. Valid size ranges
              from 4 to 100.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Format for date entries: Select the format for date entry
              and display.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>MM.DD.YYYY: Displays September 14, 1971 as
                  &#34;09.14.1971&#34;.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>DD.MM.YYYY: Displays September 14, 1971 as
                  &#34;14.09.1971&#34;.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Format for numeric values: Select the format for numeric
              entry and display, either &#34;9,999.99&#34; or
              &#34;9.999,99&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Administrative Messages</para>

          <para>Administrative messages are sent whenever Addressbook catches
          an error that forces the user to start over.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Send messages to Site Admin if error encountered?: This
              option enables error messages to be emailed directly to the site
              administrator email account. UNCHECK to disable this feature.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Different email address if not the default Site Admin:
              Choose an alternate email address if the Site Administrator does
              not wish to receive error notifications from Addressbook.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Send error reports to Addressbook developer?: Recommended
              for quality assurance purposes. Only the contents of the error
              message are sent. This option sends an email to the Addressbook
              developers with the error message, date &#38; time of
              occurrence, and the fully qualified host name of the server
              running the Addressbook module. NO OTHER INFORMATION IS SENT.
              This information is used solely for the purpose of fixing issues
              encountered in the Addressbook module. UNCHECK to disable this
              feature.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34; to
              save changes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Categories</command>:</para>

      <para>Your Addressbook entries can be assigned to a single category for
      organizational purposes. Example categories: &#34;Business&#34;,
      &#34;Personal&#34;, etc. You may add as many categories as necessary.
      The category is assigned to an entry by selecting it from the drop-down
      listing during entry creation or editing.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Category: Enter the name of the category you wish to add.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Delete: To delete an existing category, CHECK the box on the
          line with the category to be deleted.</para>

          <note>
            <para>When you click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34;
            to delete an existing category, you are NOT asked for confirmation
            before deletion.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Contact labels</command>:</para>

      <para>Contact labels allow specification of different contact methods
      for an entry in the address book. Example contact labels: Phone, Mobile,
      Pager, Fax, E-Mail, Web, Other. You may add as many contact labels as
      necessary. The contact labels are available as drop-down lists when
      adding/editing a contact.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Label: Enter the name for the contact label you wish to add.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Delete: To delete an existing contact label, CHECK the box on
          the line with the contact label to be deleted.</para>

          <para><note><para>When you click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34;
          to delete an existing contact label, you are NOT asked for
          confirmation before deletion.</para></note></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Name Prefixes</command>:</para>

      <para>Honorary titles, or name prefixes, such as &#34;Mr.&#34;,
      &#34;Sir&#34;, &#34;Mrs.&#34;, &#34;Professor&#34;, or &#34;Dr.&#34; can
      be specified in these fields. You may add as many name prefixes as
      necessary. You must have CHECKED &#34;Do you wish to use a prefix
      field?&#34; in <command>Admin-&#62;Addressbook-&#62;Modify config</command>
      for this field to be displayed during creation/editing of a contact.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prefix: Enter the prefix in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Delete: To delete an existing prefix, CHECK the box on the
          line with the prefix to be deleted.</para>

          <note>
            <para>When you click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34;
            to delete an existing prefix, you are NOT asked for confirmation
            before deletion.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Custom Fields</command>:</para>

      <para>If you wish to add custom fields for your contacts, do so using
      this panel.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Custom label: Enter the display text for the custom label in
          this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Data type: From the drop-down list, select the data type for
          the new custom field. A special data type, &#34;<guibutton>Horizontal
          Rule</guibutton>&#34;, simply draws a horizontal line and does not
          accept data entry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Delete: To delete an existing custom data type, CHECK the box
          on the line with the custom field to be deleted.</para>

          <note>
            <para>When you click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34;
            to delete an existing custom field, you are NOT asked for
            confirmation before deletion.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Order: Set the order in which the custom fields are displayed
          by clicking the UP arrow to move a field up in the order. Click the
          DOWN arrow to move a field down in the order.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Commit Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Admin Docs</command>: Click this link to view
      administration documentation for this module.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>
