<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Headlines Module</title>

  <subtitle>Generates a list of RSS news feeds. <command>Admin-&#62;Headlines</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>RSS is a Web content syndication format. Using RSS, your site can
  &#39;pull&#39; content in the form of headlines from selected websites and
  display that content on your site. If a user of your site is interested in
  reading the article, they can click a link to be taken to the other site.
  The Headlines modules facilitates this process.</para>

  <para>Your site can be syndicated assuming that you have configured
  <command>Admin-&#62;Bloggerapi</command>. The link for syndication of your
  site is
  &#34;www.yoursite.com/index.php?module=articles&#38;func=view&#38;theme=rss&#34;.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>Add</guibutton>: In this section of the Headlines
      module, we specify the news feeds that we want to syndicate.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>List of available feeds: Click this link to open a new browser
          window with <ulink url="http://www.syndic8.com">http://www.syndic8.com</ulink>.
          Click &#34;<guibutton>Feeds</guibutton>&#34; at the top of the
          Syndic8 site to display a list of available feeds, or enter search
          criteria and search for feeds. Once you have found a feed you wish
          to syndicate, copy the Feed URL from Syndic8 into Xaraya&#39;s URL
          field, below.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>URL: Once you know the URL for the news feed you wish to
          syndicate, enter the complete URL (including &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;)
          in this space.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Headline</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes. The news feed is added to the site&#39;s Headlines list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>View</guibutton>: This link allows you to view news
      feeds which you are syndicating, and to edit or delete them.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>URL: The complete URL for the news feed, including &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Order: Defines the order in which syndicated news feeds are
          displayed in the module. News feeds are displayed in ascending
          numeric order by order number. From 0 to 999, you may assign an
          order number to your news feeds to arrange them in your preferred
          order. These numbers do not need to be consecutive; it is perfectly
          acceptable to number your news feeds by 5&#39;s or 10&#39;s as you
          see fit. If you do not assign order numbers, sites are displayed in
          the order in which they were added.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Options:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Edit: Permits modification of a news feed.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>URL: Enter the complete URL (including &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;)
                  for the news feed.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Alternate Title: To override the title of the feed
                  that is provided by the feed, enter the title of the feed in
                  this field. Leave this field blank to use the feed-supplied
                  title information.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Alternate Description: To override the description of
                  the feed that is provided by the feed, enter the description
                  of the feed in this field. Leave this field blank to use the
                  feed-supplied description information.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Order: Modify the order number of the news feed in
                  this field. Enter a number, from 0-999, in this field.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Modify Headline</guibutton>&#34;
                  to save changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: To delete a news feed from your site, click this
              link next to the feed to be deleted. You will be asked to
              confirm your intention to delete, and the feed will be deleted
              from your site.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>Modify config</guibutton>: This panel allows
      modification of configuration options for this module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Items per page: In this field, enter the number of headlines
          to display per page. For example, to display 20 headlines per page,
          enter &#34;<userinput>20</userinput>&#34; in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Headlines Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
          to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>