<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Polls Module</title>

  <subtitle>Conduct polls. <command>Admin-&#62;Polls</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>Polls allow you to gather information from your site visitors using a
  &#39;voting booth&#39; method. Xaraya supports an unlimited number of
  different polls, and polls optionally support selection of multiple options
  (for example, for surveys like &#39;Which of these items do you own?&#39;).</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>New Poll</guibutton>: To create a new Poll for the
      site, click &#34;<guibutton>New Poll</guibutton>&#34;. The next panel
      offers the following options.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Poll title: Enter the name of the poll in this field, which is
          displayed to site visitors.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Poll type: If you want your users to be able to select only
          one option, choose &#34;<guibutton>Single vote</guibutton>&#34; (for
          example, &#34;Ringo&#34;). If you want your users to be able to
          select multiple options (for example, &#34;John&#34; and
          &#34;Paul&#34;), choose &#34;<guibutton>Multiple vote</guibutton>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Private: CHECK this box to make this poll private. UNCHECK
          this box to make the poll public, which means any site visitor with
          privileges can view and vote in this poll.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Poll options: Enter each available poll option, one option per
          line. Move from field to field using the TAB key.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Poll</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>List Polls</guibutton>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Title: The title of the poll.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Actions:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Edit Options: To add, modify, or delete options for the
              selected Poll, click the &#34;<guibutton>Edit options</guibutton>&#34;
              link.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Option: The poll option.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Order: To move a poll option up or down, click the
                  corresponding arrow next to it.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Actions:</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Modify: To modify a poll option, click the &#34;<guibutton>Modify</guibutton>&#34;
                      link next to the option to be modified. Make any
                      modifications and click &#34;<guibutton>Modify Option</guibutton>&#34;
                      to save changes.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Delete: To delete a poll option, click the &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34;
                      link next to the option to be deleted. Confirm your
                      intention to delete the poll option by clicking &#34;<guibutton>Delete
                      Option</guibutton>&#34; on the next panel. The poll
                      option is removed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>New option: Click &#34;<guibutton>New Option</guibutton>&#34;
                  to add a new poll option to an existing poll. Enter the
                  option text to be displayed to site visitors, and click
                  &#34;<guibutton>Create Option</guibutton>&#34; to save
                  changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Close: Closes the poll so no more votes can be submitted.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Modify: The modify option allows the title, type, privacy
              setting, and options to be changed on an existing poll. Click
              &#34;<guibutton>Modify Poll</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Reset: Click this option to reset the polling data for an
              exsiting poll. Confirm your intention on the next panel. If you
              click &#34;<guibutton>Reset Poll</guibutton>&#34;, any existing
              votes are removed for the selected Poll.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: Deletes the poll and all responses from the site.
              Click &#34;Delete Poll&#34; to confirm your intention to delete
              the poll.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>Modify config</guibutton>: This panel allows
      modification of configuration options for this module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Scale of result bar: OTTO</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Number of options for new polls: Sets the default number of
          options available when a new poll is created. If you only ask &#34;<userinput>Yes</userinput>&#34;
          or &#34;<userinput>No</userinput>&#34; polls, it is safe to set this
          to &#34;<userinput>2</userinput>&#34; options. Only the poll options
          that you use are displayed to site visitors. No matter the value in
          this setting, new options can be added to polls easily. A suggested
          setting for this field is &#34;<userinput>10</userinput>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Number of polls per list page: This setting defines the number
          of polls to display per page. To display 20 polls per page, enter
          &#34;<userinput>20</userinput>&#34; in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Activate comments in polls?: CHECK this box to permit comments
          on polls. The Comments module must be installed for this option to
          function.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use images for graph display: From this drop-down list, select
          if you would like to use images for poll results graphs.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Never: Select this option to NEVER display images in the
              poll results graph.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Blocks only: Select this option to display images in the
              poll results graph only when the poll is displayed within a
              block.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Module space only: Select this option to display images in
              the poll results graph only within the Polls module, but not in
              blocks. For example, selecting this option displays images in
              the poll results graph only when a site visitor clicks the Polls
              module.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Always: Always display images for the poll results graph.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow users to vote (per poll): From this drop-down list,
          select the frequency with which a site visitor is permitted to vote
          in a poll.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Once: The site visitor is permitted to vote in a poll only
              once.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Once per day: The site visitor is permitted to vote in a
              poll once per day.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Once per week: The site visitor is permitted to vote in a
              poll once per week.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Once per month: The site visitor is permitted to vote in a
              poll once per month.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow users to see results before voting: CHECK this box to
          allow site visitors to view poll results, even if they have not yet
          voted in a poll. UNCHECK this box to hide poll results until a user
          has voted in a specific poll.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Submit</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Creating a Poll</title>

    <para>To create a Poll, follow these steps:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Polls-&#62;New Poll</command>.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In Poll Title, type &#34;<userinput>Who is your favorite
            Beatle?</userinput>&#34;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select SINGLE in Poll Type, since we want our site visitors
            to select only ONE Beatle. If you wanted to allow them to select
            multiple options, set this field to Multiple vote. For this
            example, set it to Single vote.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Leave Private UNCHECKED.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Options: Add the following options, moving from field to
            field by pressing the TAB key.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>John</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Paul</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>George</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Ringo</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Poll</guibutton>&#34; to create the
        poll.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>