<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Comments Module</title>

  <subtitle>Allows users to post comments in any module that uses hooks.
  <command>Admin-&#62;Comments</command>.</subtitle>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Overview</command>: Displays the overview panel for this
      module. This panel contains information about the module and how to use
      it.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Statistics</command>: This panel displays statistics
      about all comments on the site. From this panel the administrator can
      see the total number of comments and where the comments are located.
      Additional actions allow deletion of comments, either selective or
      complete.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Module name: The name of the module containing comments. Click
          the module name to go to that module&#39;s statistics panel
          containing figures for each of that module&#39;s pages that have
          comments associated with them. From that panel, you can delete all
          comments associated with a particular page.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Module pages: Displays a count of the pages within a
          particular module which contain comments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Total comments: Displays a count of total comments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Inactive comments: Displays a count of inactive comments.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Action:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: By clicking &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34;
              you can delete all comments associated with a particular module.
              To delete all comments associated with a particular module,
              click &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34; and confirm your
              intention to delete on the following panel.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete All: Click this link to delete ALL comments
              associated with ALL modules. On the following panel, confirm
              your intention to delete all comments from all modules.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Modify config</command>: This panel allows modification
      of configuration options for this module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default rendering depth:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>1...9: From this drop-down list, select the default
              rendering depth for comments on the site. This setting
              determines how many levels of comments are displayed. For
              example, if you set it to &#34;<userinput>2</userinput>&#34;,
              Xaraya will show the top 2 levels of comments and a setting of
              &#34;<userinput>9</userinput>&#34; will show up to 9 levels of
              nested comments. It is unlikely that you&#39;ll experience 9
              nested levels of comments. An example of 9 nested comments is a
              reply to a reply to a reply to a reply to a reply to a reply to
              a reply to a reply to a reply!</para>

              <para>If a message&#39;s comments go beyond the default
              rendering depth, a message is displayed notifying the user that
              the particular message has additional comments that are not
              displayed, and that the user can click the message to display
              all the comments. Suggested setting is &#34;<userinput>9</userinput>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default rendering style:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Nested: Comments are displayed with child comments
              &#39;nested&#39; (indented slightly) underneath their parent
              comments. This is a recommended setting, as it is easy to
              visually track comments and sub-comments. Comments are displayed
              expanded.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Flat: Comments are displayed with child comments in the
              same level (no indentation) as their parents. Comments are
              displayed expanded.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Threaded: Threaded view displays comments in a tree-like
              structure with the parent comment at the top with child comments
              below. The threaded view is similar to the default view in many
              mail readers, along with cute threaded images. Comments are
              displayed collapsed.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>No comments: Do not display comments. If a user turns off
              comments while reading comments (not in user preferences but on
              an actual page with comments) the only way to turn them back on
              at the moment is by going to user preferences.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default sorting mode: Defines the default sorting mode for
          comments. Registered users can change their sort order if they wish.
          Default sorting mode relies on Default sorting order, below, to
          determine if the items are displayed in ascending or descending
          order.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Author: Sort comments by the author&#39;s username.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Date: Sort comments by the date/time of the comment.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Thread: Sort comments into threads.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Title: Sort comments by the title of the comment.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default sorting order: Defines the sorting order for comments.
          Registered users can change their sort order if they wish. Default
          sorting order relies on Default sorting mode, above, to determine if
          the mode for sorting.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Ascending: Display oldest-to-newest / alphabetical order.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Descending: Display newest-to-oldest / reverse
              alphabetical order.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow registered users to post anonymously?: If CHECKED, an
          option is provided whereby a registered user can post a comment
          anonymously. The user name is always displayed to the site
          administrator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<command>Update Configuration</command>&#34; to
          save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>