<sect2>
  <title>Adminpanels Module</title>

  <subtitle>Core Module, Displays the Administration menu block.
  <command>Admin-&#62;Adminpanels</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Adminpanels module configures how the Administration menu block is
  displayed to the site administrators.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Modify config</command>:</para>

      <para>This panel allows modification of configuration options for this
      module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Configure Adminmenu</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Always on top: Sets position of administration menu in
              block group. If CHECKED, the Administration menu is always at
              the top of the block group in which it is placed. If UNCHECKED,
              the Administration menu&#39;s position is determined by its
              order in <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View Instances</command>.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Mark active item: CHECK if you would like a marker
              displayed next to the active menu item. UNCHECK if you do not
              wish to have a marker displayed next to the active menu item.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Specify marker: Specify the marker to be used if &#34;Mark
              active item&#34; (above) is CHECKED. Default is &#34;[x]&#34;.</para>

              <para>AN EASTER EGG: What version of Xaraya was first the PUBlic
              release? Type your answer in this field. If your answer is
              right, as site administrator, you may catch sight of the elusive
              &#39;red manta&#39;. This Easter egg exists in versions .906 and
              later.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sort admin menu items:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>By Name: Displays the Administration menu sorted
                  alphabetically.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>By Category: The Administration menu is displayed by
                  category (Content, Global, Users &#38; Groups,
                  Miscellaneous, etc.).</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>By Weight: Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>By Group: Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sort order &#34;By Weight&#34; configuration: Not
              currently implemented.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sort order &#34;By Group&#34; configuration: Not currently
              implemented.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Groups configuration: Not currently implemented.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Add: Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Delete: Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Modify: Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Position admin menu: The Administration menu can be
              displayed in the center or on the left or right side of the
              page. Select the placement of the Administration by selecting
              from the drop-down list.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Left: Display the Administration menu on the left side
                  of the screen.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Center: Display the Administration menu in the center
                  of the screen. Not currently implemented.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Right: Display the Administration menu on the right
                  side of the screen.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Display &#34;Help&#34; link: Not currently implemented.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Submit</guibutton>&#34; to save
              changes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configure Overviews</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Disable Module Overviews: By default, Xaraya displays an
              overview panel when you click on any module in the
              Administration menu. This overview panel contains useful
              information about the module, but after you&#39;ve read it
              several times, you may wish to turn it off. CHECK this box to
              skip the module overview. UNCHECK the box to display module
              overviews.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Submit</guibutton>&#34; to save
              changes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>