<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Blocks Module</title>

  <subtitle>Blocks Module: Administration of block instances and groups.
  <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>Within Xaraya, Blocks act as building blocks to construct your site.
  Blocks are provided by the core Xaraya engine, or virtually &#39;bolted
  on&#39; by modules. Core Xaraya blocks provide basic system functionality
  such as menus, while modules provide enhanced functionality or additional
  features. Using Blocks, the Administrator can customize the look of the site
  by adding, removing, or changing the position of Blocks.</para>

  <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks</command> and use the sub-functions
  to add, edit, view, or delete Blocks from your website. The Blocks display
  is sorted by Group.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Types</command>: This panel displays every block
      type that is available on your site. View Instances (below) displays
      block types that you&#39;re currently using on your site.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Module: Click the name of the module to go to its
          Administration panel.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Type: The types of blocks provided by a particular module. See
          Add Instance, below, for a listing &#38; description of the block
          types included with a default Xaraya installation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Instances</command>: This panel displays block types
      that are currently in use on your site. View Types (above) displays
      every block type that is available for use on your site.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Group: The Block Group to which the block instance is
          assigned. To edit Block Groups (including the ordering of block
          instances within a Group), click the Group name. For example, to
          edit the &#34;center&#34; group, click &#34;<guibutton>center</guibutton>&#34;.</para>

          <note>
            <para>Block Groups are <emphasis>Theme dependant</emphasis>. The
            Block Groups listed below are based on the Xaraya_Classic theme.</para>
          </note>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Left: The new block instance is displayed on the left side
              of the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Right: The new block instance is displayed on the right
              side of the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Header: The header group gets put inside the
              &#60;head&#62;&#60;/head&#62; in the template. This is useful,
              for example, to place JavaScript or other miscellaneous features
              on the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Syndicate:</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Admin: The new block instance is displayed in the admin
              panel of the site. Items in this panel are available only to
              site administrators.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Center: The new block instance is displayed in the center
              panel of the site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Topnav: The new block instance is displayed in the menu
              navigation at the top of a site.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Title: The title for the block instance. Alphanumeric text,
          maximum of 256 characters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Type: The type of the block instance. To view a listing of all
          available block types, click any block type or click
          <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View Types</command>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Template: You can define custom display templates for each
          Block. To tell Xaraya to use a different template for a Block, enter
          the name of the template file in this field. Enter the filename
          without the &#34;<filename>.xt</filename>&#34; extension. To use the
          default page template, leave this field blank. See TEMPLATES IN
          XARAYA for a thorough discussion of templates.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>State: Default state for the block instance.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Hidden: The block instance is not displayed. Setting a
              block instance&#39;s state to &#34;Hidden&#34; makes the block
              instance inactive.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Minimized: Not all block instances support the Minimized
              state. The block instance is presented minimized. If the site
              visitor wishes to display the block instance, it can be
              maximized.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Maximized: Default. The new block instance is fully
              displayed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Operations: These functions permit editing or deleting of
          block instances.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Edit:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Title: Edit the title for the block instance in this
                  field. Alphanumeric text, maximum of 256 characters.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Type: Displays the type of the block instance.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Group: Modify the placement of the block instance by
                  selecting the group from this drop-down list. The block
                  instance will be displayed in this group.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to
                      save changes.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Template (optional): Type the filename of the template
                  to be used when displaying this block instance. The file
                  must exist in one of two places:</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Module-dependant: Module-dependant file must exist
                      in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates/blocks</filename></para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Theme-dependant: Theme-dependant file must exist
                      in: <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename>.</para>

                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Theme dependant templates override module
                          templates in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename></para>
                        </listitem>

                        <listitem>
                          <para>Theme dependant templates override module
                          blocks in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/blocks</filename></para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Default state: From this drop-down list, modify the
                  default state for the block instance.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: If you wish to delete a block instance, click the
              &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34; operation next to the
              block instance to be deleted. You are asked to confirm your
              intention to delete on the next page. Press the &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34;
              button to delete the block instance.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Groups</command>: Block Groups are Theme dependant.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: The name of the block group containing member block
          instances.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Members: The block instances that are contained in a group, in
          the order they are presented on the site.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Template: If a display template is used for the group, the
          name of the template is listed, otherwise this field is blank.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Operations: These functions permit editing or deleting of
          block groups.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Edit:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Name: Edit the group name in this field.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Members: Change the order of presentation of member
                  block instances by left-clicking on the block instance to be
                  moved and clicking on the UP or DOWN arrows to move the
                  block instance up or down.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Template: You can define custom display templates for
                  each Block Group. To tell Xaraya to use a different template
                  for a Blockl Group, enter the name of the template file in
                  this field. Enter the filename without the &#34;<filename>.xt</filename>&#34;
                  extension. To use the default page template, leave this
                  field blank. See TEMPLATES IN XARAYA for a thorough
                  discussion of templates.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save
                  changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: If you wish to delete a block group, click the
              &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34; operation next to the
              block group to be deleted. You are asked to confirm your
              intention to delete on the next page. Press the &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34;
              button to delete the block group. OTTO: What happens to Block
              Instances in a Group if the Group is deleted?</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Add Instance</command>: Click Add Instance to begin
      adding a new block instance to your site. Adding a block instance is a
      <emphasis>two-step</emphasis> process. First, complete the fields below
      in the following panel. Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Instance</guibutton>&#34;
      to add the new block instance. Secondly, in the new panel that appears,
      configure block-specific options.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Title: Enter the title for the block instance in this field.
          Alphanumeric text, maximum of 256 characters. The Title is not
          always displayed to site visitors; sometimes a block instance
          overrides this Title field and displays its own block title.
          However, Title text is displayed in <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View
          Instances</command>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Type: From this drop-down list, select the block type you wish
          to add. The contents of this drop-down list will vary based on the
          modules that are active in your Xaraya installation. View a listing
          of available block types by going to <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View
          Types</command>.</para>

          <note>
            <para>The following sub-items are common across all block types.
            These items are not repeated in the listing &#38; description of
            each block type, below.</para>
          </note>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Title: The title of the block instance.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Type: Selected when a new block instance is added, this
              indicates the block type.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Group: The group to which the new block instance will be
              added. See the description of Groups, above.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Template (optional): Type the filename of the template to
              be used when displaying this block instance. The file must exist
              in one of two places:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Module-dependant: Module-dependant file must exist in
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates/blocks</filename></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Theme-dependant: Theme-dependant file must exist in:
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename>.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Theme dependant templates override module
                      templates in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename></para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Theme dependant templates override module blocks
                      in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/blocks</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default state: The default state for the block instance.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Group: From this drop-down list, select the grouping to
              which the new block instance will be added. See the description
              of Groups, above.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Template (optional): Type the filename of the template to
              be used when displaying this block instance. The file must exist
              in one of two places:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Module-dependant: Module-dependant file must exist in
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates/blocks</filename></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Theme-dependant: Theme-dependant file must exist in:
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename>.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Theme dependant templates override module
                      templates in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename></para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Theme dependant templates override module blocks
                      in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/blocks</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default state: From this drop-down list, select the
              default state for the new block instance.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Instance</guibutton>&#34; to
              save changes.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Add Group</command>: Block Groups are Theme dependant.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: Enter the name for the new Block Group in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Default template (optional): Type the filename of the template
          to be used when displaying this block instance. The file must exist
          in one of two places:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Module-dependant: Module-dependant file must exist in
              <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;module_name&#62;/xartemplates/blocks</filename></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Theme-dependant: Theme-dependant file must exist in:
              <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename>.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Theme dependant templates override module templates in
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;</filename></para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Theme dependant templates override module blocks in
                  <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/&#60;module_name&#62;/blocks</filename></para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Group</guibutton>&#34; to save
          changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Below is a listing of the available block types that are available for
  use in <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;Add Instance</command> within the
  default Xaraya installation.</para>

  <sect3>
    <title>adminpanels/adminmenu</title>

    <para>Block instance containing the Administration menu. The
    Administration menu is displayed only to users with Administrative
    privileges.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>adminpanels/waitingcontent</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>articles/featureditems</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays featured articles on the site. The site
    administrator defines the articles to feature.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Articles Filter: The articles filter section of this panel
        allows the site administrator to filter the available articles on the
        site to simplify the task of finding the desired article.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Publication Type: From this drop-down list, select the
            Publication Type under which the featured article is published, or
            select &#34;<guibutton>All</guibutton>&#34; to deactivate this
            filter.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Category: From this drop-down list, select the Category in
            which the featured article is published, or select &#34;<guibutton>All</guibutton>&#34;
            to deactivate this filter.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Status: From this drop-down list, select the status of the
            featured article, or select &#34;<guibutton>All Published</guibutton>&#34;
            to deactivate this filter.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Limit: Enter the number of articles you wish to see in the
            Featured Article drop-down list &#38; Alternate Title box. For
            example, to return 25 articles, enter &#34;<userinput>25</userinput>&#34;
            into this box.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to filter
            articles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Featured Article: From this drop-down list, select the specific
        article to be featured.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Alternate Title: If you would like to display an alternate title
        for the featured article, enter the alternate title in this field and
        the alternate title is displayed instead of the article title in the
        block instance. If this field is empty, the article&#39;s title will
        be displayed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show Summary: If you would like to display a summary of the
        article (usually the Introduction block of the article), CHECK this
        box. The article title (or Alternate Title) is displayed followed by a
        summary. UNCHECK this box and only the article title (or Alternate
        Title) is displayed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Additional Headlines: To select additional featured headlines,
        select the headline(s) from this box.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select a single headline by left-clicking on it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select a range of headlines by left-clicking on the first
            headline in the range, holding down the SHIFT key, and
            left-clicking on the last headline in the range.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Select individual headlines by holding the CTRL key while
            left-clicking on the individual headlines to add.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sort by: This sort option defines the way items are displayed on
        this panel.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hit Count: Sort by the number of times an article has been
            viewed. Articles with more hits are displayed before articles with
            fewer hits.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rating: Sort by the rating of an article. Articles with
            higher ratings are displayed before articles with lower ratings.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date: Sort by the date of an article. Newer articles are
            displayed before older articles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show sort value: Displays the value of the &#34;<guibutton>Sort
        by</guibutton>&#34; parameter (above). For example, if &#34;<guibutton>Sort
        by</guibutton>&#34; is set to &#34;<guibutton>Hit Count</guibutton>&#34;
        and this field is CHECKED, the number of hits for an article is
        displayed after the article title in the block instance. If you do not
        want the sort value (hits, in this example) displayed, UNCHECK this
        field. Likewise, if &#34;<guibutton>Sort by</guibutton>&#34; is set to
        &#34;<guibutton>Date</guibutton>&#34; and this field is CHECKED, the
        publication date of an article is displayed after the article title in
        the block instance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show summary: If CHECKED, article titles are displayed with
        summaries. If UNCHECKED, article titles are displayed without
        summaries.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>articles/related</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays articles that are related (same
    category, same author) to the current article being displayed. This block
    instance functions only when an article is being displayed; it is not
    useful on the front page of a site.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Number of items: Enter the number of related items to be
        displayed in this field. For example, to display 5 related items,
        enter &#34;<userinput>5</userinput>&#34; here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>articles/topitems</title>

    <para>Block instance containing the top items for a particular Publication
    Type (or for the currently-displayed Publication Type) based on
    administrator-defined criteria.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Number of items: Enter the number of items to be displayed in
        this field. For example, enter &#34;<userinput>5</userinput>&#34; to
        display the top 5 items.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Publication Type: From this drop-down list, select the
        Publication Type for which the top items are displayed.</para>

        <para>Select &#34;<guibutton>Default / Current</guibutton>&#34; from
        the drop-down list to display the top items for whatever Publication
        Type the user is currently viewing. For example, if this field is set
        to &#34;<guibutton>Default / Current</guibutton>&#34; and the user is
        viewing the &#39;<guibutton>Documents</guibutton>&#39; Publication
        Type, Xaraya will display the top items in &#39;<guibutton>Documents</guibutton>&#39;.
        If the user then switches to the &#39;<guibutton>Reviews</guibutton>&#39;
        Publication Type, Xaraya will display the top items in &#39;<guibutton>Reviews</guibutton>&#39;.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Sort by: From this drop-down list, select the sort criteria that
        will be used to select articles for display in this block instance.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hit Count: Sort by the number of times an article has been
            viewed. Articles with more hits are displayed before articles with
            fewer hits.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rating: Sort by the rating of an article. Articles with
            higher ratings are displayed before articles with lower ratings.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Date: Sort by the date of an article. Newer articles are
            displayed before older articles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show sort value: Displays the value of the &#34;<guibutton>Sort
        by</guibutton>&#34; parameter (above). For example, if &#34;<guibutton>Sort
        by</guibutton>&#34; is set to &#34;<guibutton>Hit Count</guibutton>&#34;
        and this field is CHECKED, the number of hits for an article is
        displayed after the article title in the block instance. If you do not
        want the sort value (hits, in this example) displayed, UNCHECK this
        field. Likewise, if &#34;<guibutton>Sort by</guibutton>&#34; is set to
        &#34;<guibutton>Date</guibutton>&#34; and this field is CHECKED, the
        publication date of an article is displayed after the article title in
        the block instance.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show summary: If CHECKED, article titles are displayed with
        summaries. If UNCHECKED, article titles are displayed without
        summaries.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>base/finclude</title>

    <para>Block instance that includes a file from the website.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>File: OTTO -- where is the file location?</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>base/html</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays HTML-formatted code. Permitted HTML
    codes are defined in <command>Admin-&#62;HTML</command>.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Block Expiration: From this drop-down list, select the
        expiration date for this block instance.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Unlimited: This block instance does not expire, and will
            always be displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>1, 2, 5, 15, 30 Days: Select the number of days that this
            block instance will be displayed. When the block expires, it is
            not displayed anymore.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>HTML: Enter the HTML-formatted content in this block. Permitted
        HTML codes are defined in <command>Admin-&#62;HTML</command>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>base/menu</title>

    <para>Block instance that creates a new menu for the site. Menu items can
    be modules that exist on the site, URLs to other on-site resources, or
    complete URLs to off-site resources.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Display modules: CHECK this option to display all active modules
        that are installed in <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Marker: In this field, define the marker to be displayed next to
        the active menu item. Leave this field blank to disable display of a
        marker.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Menu Content:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Title: Enter the title of the menu item. The title is
            displayed to users.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>URL: Enter the URL to the resource. If the resource is on
            your site, you may enter the path to &#38; filename of the
            resource. If the file is external to your site, be sure to enter a
            complete URL, including &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;.
            If the resource is a module, enter the case-sensitive module name
            in brackets (&#34;<userinput>[</userinput>&#34; and &#34;<userinput>]</userinput>&#34;).
            For example, to add the Polls module, type &#34;<userinput>[Polls]</userinput>&#34;
            in the URL field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Description (optional): Enter an optional description of the
            menu item in this field. The description is presented as a
            mouse-over (if supported by the user&#39;s browser).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Delete: CHECK this box to delete a menu item.</para>

            <note>
              <para>No confirmation is requested before the menu item is
              deleted.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Child: CHECK this box to make the item a child of the item
            above it.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Insert blank after: To insert a blank menu line, CHECK this
            box on the line with the menu item after which you would like to
            insert a new line.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save
            changes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>base/php</title>

    <para>Block instance that executes a PHP script within the site. Meant to
    include small blocks of PHP code, like a Stock Ticker from <ulink
    url="http://www.hotscripts.com">http://www.hotscripts.com</ulink> or
    similar.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>base/text</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays the text contents of the Content field.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Block Expiration: From this drop-down list, select the
        expiration date for this block instance.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Unlimited: This block instance does not expire, and will
            always be displayed.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>1, 2, 5, 15, 30 Days: Select the number of days that this
            block instance will be displayed. When the block expires, it is no
            longer displayed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Text: Enter the text content in this block. This text will be
        displayed to site visitors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>categories/navigation</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a listing of site categories as defined
    in Admin-&#62;Categories.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Category Layout:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Tree (side block): Displays a vertical &#39;tree&#39;
            structure of the site&#39;s categories; most useful along the side
            of a page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Crumbtrail (top block): Displays a &#39;crumb
            trail&#39;-type horizontal structure of the site&#39;s categories;
            most useful at the top of a page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Prev/Next (bottom block): Displays previous- and next-type
            links; most useful at the bottom of a page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show count per category: If you would like to display the number
        of items per category, CHECK this box. If you do not want to display
        the number of items per category, UNCHECK this box.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Show children:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>None: Show no children.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Direct children only:</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>All children: Show all children.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>ephemerids/ephem</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays an ephemerid for today, if the
    Ephemerids module is active and if an entry exists for today. No
    additional configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>example/first</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>example/others</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>headlines/rss</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays an admin-selected RSS feed, if the
    Headlines module is active and has RSS feeds configured.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>RSS File URL: From this drop-down list, select the RSS feed to
        display in this block instance. See <command>Admin-&#62;Headlines-&#62;Add</command>
        to add an RSS feed to your site for syndication.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Display article descriptions: If this box is CHECKED and
        supported by the feed, short article descriptions are be displayed
        below the syndicated article titles. If UNCHECKED, only article titles
        are displayed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>messages/newmessages</title>

    <para>If the Messages module is active, this block instance displays
    notification of waiting private messages. If new private messages are
    waiting, a count of total and unread private messages is displayed with a
    link to read new private messages. If no new messages are waiting, &#34;No
    Unread messages in mailbox&#34; is displayed. No additional configuration
    options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>polls/poll</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a site Poll.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Poll to display: From this drop-down list, select the poll you
        wish to be displayed in this block instance, or select &#34;<guibutton>Latest
        Poll</guibutton>&#34; to select the most recently-added poll.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>quotes/daily</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a random quote from the site&#39;s
    quote database, if the Quotes module is active. No additional
    configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>roles/language</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>roles/login</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays the site login block. No additional
    configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>roles/online</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a count of users &#38; guests who are
    currently visiting the site. No additional configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>roles/user</title>

    <para>OTTO -- description. No additional configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>search/search</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a Search box on the site. No additional
    configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>smilies/smiley</title>

    <para>Block instance that displays a random smiley icon and the ASCII text
    needed to generate the smiley within site content. No additional
    configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>themes/meta</title>

    <para>Block instance that defines metadata for your site. Information in
    this block instance is not displayed to users. This block type is
    generally assigned to a &#34;header&#34; block group.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Meta description: Enter a description of your site in this
        field. The contents of this field are sent as a metadata
        &#34;Description&#34; for the site.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Meta keywords: One of the challenges when running a web site is
        letting external search engines know that your site exists. Meta
        keywords categorize your site. Many search engines send out robots
        (also called &#39;<firstterm>spiders</firstterm>&#39;) to search the
        Web for content. When you define Meta Keywords for your site though
        this configuration option, you make it easier for the search-engine
        robots to categorize your site, and your site will be categorized more
        appropriately since you are defining the options. Enter words &#38;
        phrases, separated by commas, that describe the focus of your web
        site. Capitalization is not important in this field. Many search
        engines limit the number of keywords that you can use. Therefore, you
        should choose your words carefully and use no more than 10-15 keywords
        that best describe your site&#39;s content.</para>

        <para>If your site is all about rock and roll music, for example, you
        might enter the following information in this field: &#34;<userinput>music,
        rock, roll, beatles, aerosmith, guitar, drum, bass, sing, singer,
        singing</userinput>&#34;</para>

        <para>For additional information on Meta Keywords, please visit Web
        Developer-META Tag Resources (<ulink
        url="http://www.webdeveloper.com/html/html_metatag_res.html">http://www.webdeveloper.com/html/html_metatag_res.html</ulink>)
        or The META Tag Builder (<ulink
        url="http://vancouver-webpages.com/META">http://vancouver-webpages.com/META</ulink>).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use GeoURL (<ulink url="http://www.geourl.org">http://www.geourl.org</ulink>):
        GeoURL is a location-to-URL reverse directory. This will allow you to
        find URLs by their proximity to a given location. Find your
        neighbor&#39;s blog, perhaps, or the web page of the restaurants near
        you. GeoURL&#39;s page provides tools for determining your
        location&#39;s latitude and longitude.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Your Longitude: In this field, enter your longitude in the
            format &#34;<userinput>W 84.520407</userinput>&#34;.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Your Latitude: In this field, enter your latitude in the
            format &#34;<userinput>N 39.283899</userinput>&#34;.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Use Dynamic Keywords: In addition to defining your own keywords
        for your site (in Meta keywords, above), you can choose to have meta
        keywords generated dynamically. When this option is CHECKED, meta
        keywords are generated dynamically whenever the full text of an
        article is displayed. All the words in the article are used as meta
        keywords. CHECKING this function has a small performance cost.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Copyright page: OTTO</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Help page: OTTO</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Glossary: OTTO</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>themes/syndicate</title>

    <para>No additional configuration options.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Adding, modifying, and deleting block instances</title>

    <para>Within this example, we explore methods for adding, modifying, and
    deleting block instances.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adding block instances</para>

        <para>For these examples, we&#39;ll add a few block instances to work
        with. Following the instructions in <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;Add
        Instance</command> (above), add the following three blocks:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Block 1:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Title: <userinput>Base HTML Block 1</userinput></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Type: Base \ HTML</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Group: Center</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Leave the other items set at their default.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Instance</guibutton>&#34;
                to save changes.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In the HTML field that appears in the next panel, type:</para>

                <para>&#34;<userinput>&#60;b&#62;This is BASE HTML BLOCK #
                1.&#60;/b&#62;</userinput>&#34; <emphasis>(no quotes)</emphasis></para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save
                changes.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Block 2:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Do the same steps as with Block #1, substituting &#34;<userinput>Base
                HTML Block 2</userinput>&#34; for the title and &#34;<userinput>&#60;b&#62;This
                is BASE HTML BLOCK # 2.&#60;/b&#62;</userinput>&#34; for the
                HTML field.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Block 3:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Do the same steps as with Block #1, substituting &#34;<userinput>Base
                HTML Block 3</userinput>&#34; for the title and &#34;<userinput>&#60;b&#62;This
                is BASE HTML BLOCK # 3.&#60;/b&#62;</userinput>&#34; for the
                HTML field.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you go to the front page of the site (click the Xaraya logo
        in the top left corner of the default theme), you&#39;ll see these
        three blocks displayed in ascending numerical order.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Modifying block instances</para>

        <para>If you wish to modify a block instance, go to
        <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View Instances</command>. Click &#34;<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>&#34;
        on the line next to the block instance you wish to modify. On the next
        panel, make your changes and click the &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34;
        button to save changes.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For our example, edit Block #2&#39;s title to read &#34;<userinput>The
            Second Base HTML Block</userinput>&#34; and the HTML to read &#34;<userinput>Here&#39;s
            the &#60;i&#62;second&#60;/i&#62; HTML block</userinput>&#34;. Be
            sure to &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; to save your
            changes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Deleting block instances</para>

        <para>To delete a block instance, go to <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View
        Instances</command>. Click &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34; on
        the line next to the block instance you wish to delete. On the next
        panel, confirm your intention to delete.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Changing the order of blocks within Groups</title>

    <para>Follow this example, using the three blocks we added in &#34;Adding
    block instances&#34;, above, to learn how to change the order of block
    instances within Groups.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you don&#39;t have the three sample block instances from
        &#34;Adding block instances&#34;, above, create them now.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Blocks-&#62;View Groups</command>.
        Click &#34;<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>&#34; on the line next to the
        block group you wish to modify. In this example, click &#34;<guibutton>Edit</guibutton>&#34;
        on the line next to the &#34;<guibutton>Center</guibutton>&#34; block
        group. On the next panel, modify the order of block instances.
        Left-click on an instance to select it, then use the UP and DOWN arrow
        icons to change the placement of the selected block instance in the
        block group. Click the &#34;<guibutton>Update</guibutton>&#34; button
        to save changes.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>For our example, move the block instances we created into
            the following orders, saving changes between each:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>3, 2, 1</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>1, 3, 2</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>2, 1, 3</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>When you have finished this example, delete the three block
        instances. Follow instructions in &#39;Deleting block instances&#39;,
        above.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Manipulating Block Groups</title>

    <para>OTTO</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adding a Block Group</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Modifying a Block Group</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Deleting a Block Group</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>