<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Mail Module</title>

  <subtitle>Mail handling utility module. <command>Admin-&#62;Mail</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Mail module controls how your Xaraya system sends mail to users or
  groups of users. This module is a utility module that takes information from
  other modules installed on your Xaraya system and formats mail messages for
  them. This module allows you to use SMTP, SendMail, or the normal PHP Mail
  functions to send mail to site visitors.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>Modify config</guibutton>: This panel allows
      modification of configuration options for this module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Modify Mail Configuration</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Admin Name: Enter the name of the site administrator here.
              For example, &#34;<userinput>Joe Admin</userinput>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Admin Email: Enter the site administrator&#39;s complete
              email address in this field.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Add different reply-to: If CHECKED, email messages from
              the site are sent with a different Reply-To Name &#38; Address.
              Two additional fields become available:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Reply To Name: Enter the name that replaces the Admin
                  Name, above.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Reply To Email: Enter the email address that replaces
                  the Admin Email, above.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Send HTML Emails?: If CHECKED, HTML formatted emails will
              be sent, and two additional fields become available after
              clicking the &#34;<guibutton>Update Mail Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
              button.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>HTML Email Header: In this field, enter the complete
                  HTML header for emails sent from this site.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>HTML Email Footer: In this field, enter the complete
                  HTML footer for emails sent from this site.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default Word Wrap Size: Set the word-wrap size for emails
              sent from this site in this field. For example, set to &#34;<userinput>78</userinput>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default Priority to send messages: From the drop-down
              list, select the default priority for messages that are sent
              from the site. Some email readers handle messages with higher
              priorities in different ways, marking them with a flag or
              playing a sound, for example.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>High: Send email messages from the site marked as high
                  priority.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Normal: Send email messages from the site marked as
                  high priority. This is the recommendation, and the default.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Low: Send email messages from the site marked as low
                  priority.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Default method to send mail: From the drop-down list,
              select the default method to be used for sending messages from
              the site. Use the email sub-system on the site, or select Mail
              to use PHP&#39;s built-in mail handling system.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>SMTP: Use SMTP to send email from the site.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sendmail: Use Sendmail to send email from the site.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Mail: Use PHP&#39;s mail functions to send email from
                  the site.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>QMail: Use QMail to send email from the site.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Filtering Options</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Strings for search: You can specify custom strings of text
              that will be replaced in site emails. Enter each string on a
              single line. Do not separate with commas or other punctuation.
              Suggested format is &#34;<userinput>%%string%%</userinput>&#34;
              (without quotes) to ensure that no conflict exists.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Strings for replacement: Enter each string on a single
              line in the same order as the search (above). Do not separate
              with comma, etc.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Mail Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
          to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>