<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Hitcount Module</title>

  <subtitle>Count displays of module items. <command>Admin-&#62;Hitcount</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Hitcount module is a utility module that counts the number of hits
  on items on the site.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>View Statistics</guibutton>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Module name: Click on a module name to go to that module&#39;s
          statistics page containing figures for each of that module&#39;s
          items that have hit counts associated with them.</para>

          <para>If you click the name of a module, the next panel displays a
          listing of items (and, if you&#39;ve CHECKED &#34;Show the item
          title in statistics&#34; in <command>Admin-&#62;Hitcount-&#62;Modify
          config</command>, the title of the item).</para>

          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Total hits</guibutton>&#34; to sort the
          list by hits.</para>

          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34; to delete the
          hit counts associated with a particular module or item. Note that
          the module and module contents <emphasis>are not deleted</emphasis>
          by this function. On the next panel you are asked to confirm your
          intention to delete. Once you confirm, the hit counts are deleted
          for the item.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Module items: The total number of items associated with the
          module.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Total hits: The total hits for all items within the module.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Grand total: The grand total of each column.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Action:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: By clicking <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> you can
              delete the hit counts associated with a particular module or
              item. Note that the module and module contents
              <emphasis>are not deleted</emphasis> by this function. On the
              next panel you are asked to confirm your intention to delete.
              Once you confirm, the hit counts are deleted for the item.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete All: By clicking <guibutton>Delete All</guibutton>
              you can delete all hit counts. Note that module and module
              contents <emphasis>are not deleted</emphasis> by this function.
              On the next panel you are asked to confirm your intention to
              delete. Once you confirm, the hit counts are deleted for
              <emphasis>all</emphasis> items.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><guibutton>Modify config</guibutton>: This panel allows
      modification of configuration options for this module.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Count Administrator Hits: If you would like for the
          Administrator&#39;s hits to increment the counter, CHECK this box.
          If you do not wish for the Administrator&#39;s hits to increment the
          counter, UNCHECK this box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Number of top items shown to users: In this field, select the
          number of top items to display to site visitors. For example, if you
          wish to display the top 10 items, enter &#34;<userinput>10</userinput>&#34;
          in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Number of items shown in statistics: In this field, enter the
          number of items shown per page in the administrator&#39;s statistics
          view (<command>Admin-&#62;Hitcount-&#62;View
          Statistics-&#62;&#60;category_name&#62;</command>). If you wish to
          display 50 items per page, enter &#34;<userinput>50</userinput>&#34;
          in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Show the item title in statistics: CHECK this box to display
          the item title in <command>Admin-&#62;Hitcount-&#62;View
          Statistics-&#62;&#60;category_name&#62;</command>. If this box is
          UNCHECKED, only the item number (and not the title) is displayed in
          the statistics view.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Users Configuration</guibutton>&#34;
          to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>