<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>SiteTools Module</title>

  <subtitle>Set of tools for site and database maintenThis option allows you
  to flush (delete) cache files in either of all of your Template, RSS or
  adodb cache directories. <command>Admin-&#62;Sitetools</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>The Site Tools Module provides a set of utilities to assist in
  managing cache files, and databases for your site, from within Xaraya. As
  time progresses, other site utilities may be added to this module, so you
  should check for an upgrade in <command>Admin-&#62;Modules</command>
  listings when installing new versions of Xaraya or this module.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>Optimize database</command>:</para>

      <para>This utility allows you to optimize your database. Tables are
      listed with optimization status, and the amount of space saved through
      an optimization. At this time only MySQL databases are supported, but we
      expect this will be expanded to other database types with time, as well
      as the ability to choose from one or more databases.</para>

      <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Optimize Now!</guibutton>&#34; to optimize
      your database. Optimization totals are displayed on the next panel when
      optimization has completed.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Backup database</command>:</para>

      <para>Before this option can be used, a Backup Path must be configured
      in <command>Admin-&#62;Sitetools-&#62;Modify config</command>. The path
      must exist and be world-writable. The backup database utility allows you
      to create one of four different types of database backups:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Full backup with complete inserts</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Full backup with standard inserts (a smaller file)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Partial backup: all tables are listed with their number of
          records and you can choose the tables to backup.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Structure only: only the structure of your database will be
          backed up. No content.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In all options, you can choose to create a compressed gz file, or
      text sql file. The gz option will only be effective if your server has
      gz option available.</para>

      <para>At this time only MySQL databases are supported, but we expect
      this will be expanded to other database types with time, as well as the
      ability to choose from one or more databases.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Do not leave your backup file on the server in a web browsable
        directory. Remember to move it to a secure directory, or delete the
        file when you have saved it to your local computer.</para>
      </note>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Clear Cache files</command>:</para>

      <para>This option allows you to flush (delete) cache files in any/all of
      your Template, RSS, or ADODB cache directories. To select the caches to
      be flushed, CHECK the box. If a box is left UNCHECKED, the cache files
      for that directory will not be removed. Click &#34;<guibutton>Confirm
      deletion</guibutton>&#34; to perform the deletion of cache files.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Browse Cache files</command>:</para>

      <para>This option allows you to list and browse all cache files in your
      Template cache directory, with the corresponding template file listed.
      By clicking on a listed file you can browse the contents which are
      displayed with line numbering. This is useful when debugging new
      templates, or isolating problems with existing templates.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Modify config</command>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Cache file options: Set paths to your template, RSS, and ADODB
          caches. These should not be changed unless you physically configure
          new directories for cache files. Unless you did this through the
          Multisite Module, you would have to make changes to the Xaraya code
          for this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Backup Options: You must enter the path to the directory where
          your backup files will be created. The default is the
          <filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/var/uploads</filename> directory as this
          is writeable (chmod 777). If you change this, make sure your backup
          directory exists and is writeable.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use timestamps in backup files: By checking this, a time stamp
          will be written into the name of any backup files that are created.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Columns for display: For partial backups, all tables are
          displayed for selection and inclusion into the backup. This option
          allows you to change the number of columns used for display.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Update Configuration</guibutton>&#34; to
          save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>