<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect2>
  <title>Autolinks Module</title>

  <subtitle>TRANSFORM. Automatically link key words. <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks</command>.</subtitle>

  <para>Autolinks is a feature that, when installed, generates web links
  related to text content on-the-fly. If you have Autolinks turned on &#38;
  configured properly, &#34;Beatles&#34; defined as a Keyword, and &#34;<ulink
  url="http://www.beatles.com">http://www.beatles.com</ulink>&#34; as the
  auto-link URL, Autolinks in Xaraya can automatically replace occurrences of
  &#34;Beatles&#34; within your articles with &#34;&#60;a
  href=&#34;http://www.beatles.com&#34;&#62;Beatles&#60;/a&#62;&#34;.</para>

  <para>When the Autolinks module is installed, the option to hook Autolinks
  into particular modules appears in <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure
  Hooks</command>. Hook Autolinks into the modules you wish (such as Articles,
  Comments, Ephemerids, Messages, and XarBB). See the section on Hooks for
  information about hooking modules together.</para>

  <para>There are five &#39;levels&#39; of use for the Autolinks module on
  your site.</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Beginner: Create Autolinks based on previously-defined Autolink
      Types without using Dynamic Data. If you just want to create Autolinks,
      this is the simplest level. The default Autolink Types &#38; templates
      are reasonably comprehensive.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Intermediate #1: Using Dynamic Data to allow over-ride of global
      settings for individual links (for example, named targets for links,
      etc).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Intermediate #2: Using dynamic data to access optional features of
      the standard templates (features such as an alternative icon in the
      &#39;external&#39; link type).</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Advanced #1: Adding new Autolink Types and creating templates for
      the new types.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Advanced #2: Using regular expression (regex) matching.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>Let&#39;s examine the options available within Autolinks.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Links</command></para>

      <para>To view, edit, or delete Autolinks, click <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;View
      Links</command>. On the next panel, the following options are displayed.
      Autolinks in your database are displayed sorted by Name.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type: Displays the Autolink Type. Click the Autolink Type text
          to go to the Modify Autolink Type panel.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Name: Displays the name of the Autolink. Names are unique
          across all Autolinks on a site. Click the Name text to go to the
          Modify Autolink panel.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matching key: Xaraya searches content items for this text. If
          matching text is located, it is replaced with an autolink. If the
          Autolink has the &#34;Match as regular expression&#34; field
          CHECKED, the matching key is considered to be a
          <firstterm>regular expression (regex)</firstterm> and, so that you
          can tell it&#39;s a regex, is displayed on the listing as emphasised
          (which may be italics or other text formatting based on the theme).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>URL: The URL to which this autolink points.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Options:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Disable: If you wish to disable an Autolink but not delete
              it from the Autolinks database, click &#34;Disable&#34;. The
              Autolink will not appear as a link when matching text is found.
              To enable an Autolink, click &#34;Enable&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Edit: If you wish to edit an Autolink, click on the
              &#34;Edit&#34; link for that Autolink. A panel is displayed
              allowing you to edit all the information about the selected
              Autolink.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Type: Displays the Autolink Type. If you wish to move
                  an existing Autolink to a different Autolink Type, select
                  the &#34;Move&#34; command under <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;View
                  Links-&#62;Options</command>.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Edit: If you wish to edit the Autolink Type, click
                      this link to go to the Modify Autolink Type panel.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Security</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Name: Type the name of the Autolink as it will be
                      displayed in the Autolink administration panels of the
                      site. Names are unique across all Autolinks on a site.
                      The name field exists because the Keyword may be a
                      regular expression (see below) instead of a simple name.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Enabled: If this box is CHECKED, the Autolink.is
                      enabled and will be displayed if a matching key is found
                      content. If this field is UNCHECKED, the Autolink is not
                      displayed if a matching key is found in content. The
                      &#34;Example&#34; field is displayed regardless of the
                      setting of this field. Toggling this field will
                      recompile the autolink from the template.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Matching</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Matching key: Xaraya searches content items for
                      this text, which must be enclosed by white space, tags,
                      or punctuation. The punctuation characters are defined
                      in <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;Modify config</command>.
                      If matching text is located, it is replaced with the
                      autolink.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Match as regular expression: This is an advanced
                      option within Xaraya. CHECK this box to cause the
                      Autolink to be evaluated as a regular expression instead
                      of a string. UNCHECK this box (default) to evaluate the
                      Autolink as a string. A regular expression (frequently
                      abbreviated to &#34;regex&#34;) is a way for a site
                      administrator to express how Xaraya should look for a
                      specified pattern in Autolink text and then what to do
                      when each pattern match is found. For example, a regular
                      expression could tell a program to search for all text
                      lines that contain the word &#34;Windows 95&#34; and
                      then to print out each line in which a match is found or
                      substitute another text sequence (for example, just
                      &#34;Windows&#34;) where any match occurs.</para>

                      <para>Regular expression matching is very powerful in
                      that a single regular expression will match more than
                      just one word. For example, you may want to match
                      &#34;Windows 98&#34;, &#34;Windows 95&#34;, and
                      &#34;Windows 9X&#34; as a single autolink with the same
                      URL. Another reason for using a regex is to split the
                      matched string into sub-strings. For example, you may
                      wish to match the text &#60;article:aid&#62; (e.g.,
                      &#34;&#60;article:123&#62;&#34;) and replace it with a
                      link. The template would need to know just the
                      &#34;123&#34; portion. The regex can split the matched
                      string into the required parts, allowing the seperate
                      components to be passed to the template.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Replacing</para>

                  <para>Everything in this section depends on the template.
                  This section describes the &#39;standard&#39; template;
                  other templates may do something completely different with
                  these fields. The sample templates included with Autolinks
                  will adhere to the standards described below.</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Title: Enter the title of the Autolink in this
                      field. The title is displayed to site visitors as a
                      tool-tip.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>URL: Enter the complete URL for the Autolink in
                      this field. For external sites, always include
                      &#34;http://&#34; at the beginning of the link. For
                      local links, just the path to the page is sufficient
                      (remember that you can use Short URLs if they are
                      enabled).</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Comment: An optional comment on the Autolink. The
                      Comment field is not currently used in any of the
                      default Autolink templates, however, it is passed to the
                      template in case someone wants to use it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Other</para>

                  <para>Sample text to test link: In this field, enter sample
                  text to test the link. The sample text (and resulting links)
                  are displayed on the <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;View
                  Links</command> panel. In <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;Modify
                  config</command>, you can specify how the sample text will
                  be displayed (sample, result, both, or none).</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Sample: (displayed in <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;View
                      Links</command>)</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>Result: (displayed in <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;View
                      Links</command>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Modify Autolink</guibutton>&#34; to
              save changes.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Move:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Move to Autolink Type:</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Move</guibutton>&#34; to save
                  changes.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Delete: To delete an Autolink, click on the &#34;<guibutton>Delete</guibutton>&#34;
              link for that Autolink. A panel will be displayed asking you to
              confirm your request to delete the Autolink. If you wish to
              delete the Autolink, click &#34;<guibutton>Confirm</guibutton>&#34;;
              otherwise click &#34;<guibutton>Cancel deletion of Autolink</guibutton>&#34;
              and the link will not be removed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Add Link</command></para>

      <para>To add a new Autolink, click this link. On the next panel, the
      following options are displayed.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Autolink Type: From this drop-down list, select the Autolink
          Type from the previously-defined Autolink Types.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Name: Enter the title of the site in the Name field (for
          example, &#34;The Beatles Site&#34;). If the name is left blank on
          the first panel, the value is taken from the matching key field.
          This is the name that will be displayed as a tool-tip and in the
          listing of all Autolinks.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matching key: Enter the keyword or regex in the Matching key
          field. This is the text that will be matched in an article (for
          example, &#34;beatles&#34;).</para>

          <note>
            <para>Capitalization is not important in the Key (link) Word
            field.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>URL: Enter the complete URL for the site in the URL field (for
          example, &#34;<ulink url="http://www.beatles.com">http://www.beatles.com</ulink>&#34;).
          For external sites, always include &#34;<userinput>http://</userinput>&#34;
          at the beginning of the link. For local links, just the path to the
          page is sufficient (remember that you can use Short URLs if they are
          enabled).</para>

          <para>If the URL is located on your web site, enter the path to the
          file or the complete URL. For example, if the file is on your site,
          enter &#34;<filename>music.html</filename>&#34; and Autolinks will
          automatically prepend the &#34;<filename>http://www.yoursite.com</filename>&#34;,
          resulting in an Autolink of &#34;<filename>http://www.yoursite.com/music.html</filename>&#34;.
          To be more specific, you could also enter &#34;<filename>http://www.yoursite.com/music.html</filename>&#34;
          instead of just &#34;<filename>music.html</filename>&#34;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Comments: Use the Comments field to enter optional free-form
          alphanumeric comments about the link. The Comment field is not
          currently used in any of the default Autolink templates, however, it
          is passed to the template in case someone wants to use it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.
          You are displayed a second panel where there may be additional
          fields to be populated, including any dynamic data fields defined
          for the Autolink Type. Creation of a new Autolink must be two-stage
          because dynamic data fields presented will depend on the chosen
          Autolink Type.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>View Types</command></para>

      <para>To view, modify, or delete existing Autolink Types, click this
      link. On the next panel, the following options are displayed.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: The name of the Autolink Type as it is displayed in the
          <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks</command> panel. Must be unique.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Template: Enter the name of the template file for this
          Autolink Type (link-{name}.xd). If you enter &#34;<userinput>underlined</userinput>&#34;
          in this field, Xaraya looks for a file called &#34;<filename>link-underlined.xd</filename>&#34;.
          The file must exist with appropriate permissions and ownership in
          one of two locations on the site:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/autolinks/xartemplates/</filename>
              for a site-wide template</para>

              <para>or</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/autolinks/</filename>
              for a theme-specific template</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Method: Either &#34;Static&#34; or &#34;Dynamic&#34;, based
          upon the Execute Template Dynamically setting. It is useful to
          understand the difference between these two methods.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Static: A Method of Static will execute the template the
              moment that &#34;Modify&#34; or &#34;Save&#34; is clicked. The
              results are then stored away and used to replace linked text.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Dynamic: A Method of Dynamic does not execute the template
              when &#34;Modify&#34; or &#34;Save&#34; is clicked. Instead,
              Dynamic will execute the template when matching text is found.
              If the same matching text appears ten times in a page, a Dynamic
              type is executed ten times. There are two main reasons why you
              might use the Dynamic Method:</para>

              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The template performs some kind of lookup to get
                  additional details related to what has just been matched, so
                  that details can be displayed that are not known at the time
                  the autolink is created (an article title, for example).</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>You may have different autolink templates in different
                  themes and want to use the appropriate template for the
                  theme. This will execute the theme template based on the
                  theme being viewed by the site visitor. By contrast, a
                  Static Method will &#39;freeze&#39; the template based on
                  the theme the site administrator is using at that time.</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Description: Description of the Autolink Type. This is
          displayed within <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks</command> as a bit of
          information for the site administrator.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Options: To edit or delete an existing Autolink Type, click
          the appropriate link next to the Autolink Type to edit or delete. If
          you choose to delete an Autolink Type, you are asked to confirm your
          choice on the next panel. If the Autolink Type contains autolinks,
          you are asked to confirm the intention to delete these Autolinks as
          well. Autolinks that are not assigned to an Autolink Type are not
          permitted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Add Type</command></para>

      <para>Autolink Types are a group of similar-style or
      similar-functionality links based on a shared template for formatting,
      and sharing the same dynamic data properties if dynamic data is enabled.
      To add a new Autolink Type, click this link. This panel is also
      displayed when Modifying an Autolink Type. On the next panel, the
      following options are displayed.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name: Type the name of the Autolink Type in this field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Template name: Enter the name of the template file for this
          Autolink Type (link-{name}.xd). If you enter &#34;underlined&#34; in
          this field, Xaraya looks for a file called
          &#34;link-underlined.xd&#34;. The file must exist with appropriate
          permissions and ownership in one of two locations on the site:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/modules/autolinks/xartemplates/</filename>
              for a site-wide template</para>

              <para>or</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><filename>&#60;xarroot&#62;/&#60;themes_dir&#62;/&#60;theme_name&#62;/modules/autolinks/</filename>
              for a theme-specific template</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Execute Template Dynamically: For default Autolinks operation
          (non-regular expression), leave this box UNCHECKED. To execute the
          template dynamically, CHECK this box.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Description: Description of the Autolink Type. This is
          displayed within <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks</command>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create</guibutton>&#34; to save changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><command>Modify config</command></para>

      <para>This section allows configuration of how Autolinks appear on your
      site.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Matching Rule Options</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Punctuation characters: This list defines characters that
              are allowed to border a linked word. For example, if you want to
              match the word &#34;<userinput>site</userinput>&#34; but not in
              the word &#34;<userinput>my-site</userinput>&#34;, do
              <emphasis>not</emphasis> define &#34;<userinput>-</userinput>&#34;
              as an allowed punctuation character.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Match non-breaking space entity as white space: &#34;<userinput>&#38;nbsp;</userinput>&#34;
              is an entity that represents &#39; &#39;, while &#39; &#39; is
              just a space. To match &#34;<userinput>$nbsp;</userinput>&#34;
              to a space, CHECK this box. It is generally recommended that
              this option be CHECKED unless you have a specific reason to
              uncheck it. For example, if this box is CHECKED, a link that
              matches &#34;<userinput>my site</userinput>&#34; will also match
              &#34;<userinput>my&#38;nbsp;site</userinput>&#34; as well as
              &#34;<userinput>my site</userinput>&#34; and &#34;<userinput>my
              &#38;nbsp; site</userinput>&#34;. All of these links will
              display the same if the field is CHECKED, but you may not wish
              to match non-breaking spaces. White space in non-matching
              regular expressions is treated as white space, regardless of
              what type or how long it is.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Action Options</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Limit on number of times each link is used in a piece of
              text: Enter the number of times in a particular article that
              matching text will be converted to an Autolink. For example, if
              you would like a matching piece of text to be converted to an
              Autolink twice in a single article and subsequent matches would
              not be converted, enter &#34;<userinput>2</userinput>&#34; in
              this field. To convert ALL matching text within a particular
              article to Autolinks, leave this field blank.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Autolink decoration (style will override class): From the
              drop-down list, select the type of decoration displayed for
              autolinks. This field may be depreciated at some point, but it
              is currently implemented for legacy reasons. The definitions
              below are used on the default templates. It is possible to
              over-ride these settings in a link by using a dynamic data
              property field called &#34;style&#34;.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Default: The default decoration style as defined in
                  the site&#39;s theme will be used.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>None: The autolink is displayed without any
                  decoration.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Underline: The autolink text is underlined.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Overline: The autolink text is overlined (the opposite
                  of underlining).</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Both: Both Underline &#38; Overline decorations are
                  used to display the autolink.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Open links in new window: CHECK this box if you would like
              Autolinks to open in a new window. UNCHECK it to open Autolinks
              in the current browser window. It is possible to over-ride this
              setting in a link by using a dynamic data property field called
              &#34;target&#34;, where your own targets may be defined.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show template errors inline (errors shown in content): Use
              this while debugging. If a link does not execute the template
              properly, then it will generate an error message. CHECKING this
              field will show the error message as a tool-tip over the matched
              text (the text showing as an error class). UNCHECKING this field
              will leave words that link to an erroneous template intact -
              unmatched. The error message does not look good on a site, so it
              should be UNCHECKED once debugging is complete.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Template base name (affects all templates used): Don&#39;t
              touch this unless you want to see what template errors look
              like. Seemed like a good option so an admin can switch between
              different sets of links without changing theme.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Admin Options</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Items per page: How many Autolinks would you like to
              display per page? Enter that value into this field, for example,
              &#34;<userinput>25</userinput>&#34;.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Show sample links in list:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>None:</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Results only:</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sample only:</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Sample and Results:</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Click &#34;<guibutton>Create Autolink</guibutton>&#34; to add the
      Autolink to the database.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect3>
    <title>EXAMPLE: Adding AutoLinks to a Publication Type</title>

    <para>Adding AutoLinks to a Publication Type is very easy. There are two
    different methods for accomplishing this task, and we will cover them both
    in this example. Be sure you have some Autolinks defined (go to
    <command>Admin-&#62;Autolinks-&#62;Add</command> and add a few) and an
    article that contains Autolink text so you can see the results of your
    work.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Method 1</emphasis>. Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;View
        All</command>. Next to the Articles line in the panel, click &#34;<guibutton>On/Off</guibutton>&#34;
        under the Hooks heading. On the next panel that appears, CHECK to
        enable Autolinks in specific Publication Type(s), or CHECK the ALL box
        to enable Autolinks in all Publication Types. Click &#34;<guibutton>Save
        Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save changes. You have just enabled
        Autolinks to Publication Type(s)!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Method 2</emphasis>. Go to <command>Admin-&#62;Modules-&#62;Configure
        Hooks</command>. In the next panel, click Autolinks. CHECK the
        specific Publication Types in which you wish to enable Autolinks, or
        CHECK the ALL ARTICLES box to enable Autolinks in all Publication
        Types. Click &#34;<guibutton>Save Changes</guibutton>&#34; to save
        changes. You have just enabled Autolinks to Publication Type(s)!</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>