<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Before you begin your module</title>

  <!--Maintained by: -->

  <!--Status:-->

  <section>
    <title>What will your module do?</title>

    <para>It is known to everybody, but often forgotten: a good planning will
    help you create things better. The first stage in creating your module is
    the decision and description what your module will do. What is the reason
    you will create this module? It is clear by now you cannot do it with
    other tools, so what are the exact needs for this module?</para>

    <para>The example module has a clear architecture and reason: it is a
    demonstration module for developers. It's purpose is clear, and because it
    is an example, its structure is clear as well. </para>

    <para>You module should have the same clear setup.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Research your module needs</title>

    <para>The module needs are those parts of the system you will need in your
    module, and the parts that you don't have yet, so will need to create.
    </para>

    <para>The example module needs to show how things work. Therefore, we need
    the complete directory structure to display, we need an example of data
    storage, we need example functions to show how data is stored and
    retreived, we need display functions.. gosh, we need a lot.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Choose a name</title>

    <para>Choosing a name for your module is important, as this is the main
    way that your module will be known throughout the Xaraya community. The
    name should relate to the functionality that the module provides, but also
    be specific enough to be able to discern it from separate modules that
    might offer similar functionality. All modules names are lower-case
    only.</para>

    <para>The example module has the straight forward name 'example'. This is
    a great name, it describes its purpose, it is short enough, easy to
    remember and easy to write. Compare to a module called
    "mygreatmodulethatonlyisforme"... and imagine the URL this will
    generate.</para>

    <para>Try to stay within 10 characters for the name. There are two
    versions of the name for your module: the technical one, all lowercase and
    used by the Xaraya core to know where to find its API, and a nice one you
    can use for Display. The display name can have capitals and is mainly used
    when distributing your module.</para>

    <para>You can offer site admins the possibility to use an alias for your
    module. The alias will be used then instead of the module name.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Decide on the type of module</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Implications of your choice</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Register your module</title>

    <para>Registering your module is not compulsory, but it is a very good
    idea. By registering your module, you can ensure that no other official
    Xaraya module will take the name that you have chosen for your module. Two
    modules with the same name will not operate correctly on a single Xaraya
    site, so it is beneficial to both yourself and the Xaraya community in
    general to have a unique name. You may register your module via the
    release module on <ulink url="???">http://www.xaraya.com/</ulink></para>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Releasing your module</title>

      <para>If you have registered you module/extension, and if you want to
      release a version, then you can use the Xaraya Release module. This way,
      your release will be announced to all Xaraya installs. The Release
      module will place an announcement on the xaraya.com frontpage and make
      an accouncement in the RSS feed.</para>

      <para>You will have to think of some things before releasing:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will the module be free?</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Where can users download the module?</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Where can they see documentation?</para>

          <para>Documentating your module is very important. We give some
          guidelines on documentation<indexterm></indexterm> in the
          section</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Do you want your module to become an official Xaraya
          extension?</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>