<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Getting Help</title>

  <!--Maintained by:-->

  <!--Status:-->

  <section>
    <title>Developer Documentation and References</title>

    <para>Xaraya has information on its architecture, the functions provided
    by the core and the general best practises in a few places</para>

    <para></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>RFC index</para>

        <para>The RFCs of Xaraya are a very important source of information.
        They provide the planning and implementation of several parts in
        Xaraya. When reading an RFC, you should note the date of release and
        last update.</para>

        <para>The Xaraya RFC can be found via the documentation section at
        <ulink url="???">http://www.xaraya.com.</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>PHPDoc and XRef index</para>

        <para>The core files of Xaraya have header information. This
        information is used to generate phpdocumentation and an xref index.
        You can find this information via the documentation section at <ulink
        url="???">http://www.xaraya.com</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Forum</para>

        <para>The XarBB module is used as a forum on the community area of the
        Xaraya website. The developers forum is a good source of FAQ type of
        information. You should visit it </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Support forums, newsgroups, lists &amp; IRC</title>

    <para>The forum at xaraya.com has already been introduced. The IRC server
    at irc.xaraya.com serves several rooms. You should definitively visit
    #xaraya.support with questions you might have regarding development.
    </para>

    <para>Most developers prefer the ease of a mailinglist. The developers
    mailinglist is a great source of information. You can search it via your
    favourite newsreader or via the Xaraya website.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>...</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>