<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>What's in Xaraya?</title>

  <!--Maintained by:-->

  <!--Status: Brainstorm-->

  <section>
    <title>Your Xaraya installation</title>

    <para>You have probably already downloaded a version of Xaraya and played
    around. If you haven't, well: let's give it a try!</para>

    <para>Download the base distribution and do an install for a public site.
    Install all shipped modules and stick to the basic theme (Xaraya_Classic).
    This will give a nice overview of the possibilities of Xaraya.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Files and their locations</title>

      <para>You can browse around in the Xaraya directory structure. You will
      first find some basic directories, but when you look further you can
      encounter several paths that you wouldn't normally see in a for instance
      static website.</para>

      <para>The Xaraya core is placed in /includes, /var, /xaradodb, /themes
      and ...</para>

      <para>The directory /modules hold all the extensions (modules). Make
      sure you have articles, categories, dynamicdata and example in there.
      There are more, but we will only mention these in this guide. The module
      example is the important example module that will serve as a template
      for our module later on.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Xaraya key components</title>

    <abstract>
      <para>What er the basic parts you should have some knowledge about.
      Extended glossary type.</para>
    </abstract>

    <para><synopsis></synopsis></para>

    <section>
      <title>Core API</title>

      <para>Xaraya cannot live without the core. The core is there to do all
      basic operations in your installation. It provides services we need like
      the interaction with the database, generating the actual pages we see in
      a webbrowser, deal with security and many other basic tasks.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Modules</title>

      <para>Modules are extensions that you can plug into the core. They act
      like little programs themselves. Modules can communicate with the core
      and with eachother via hooks.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Blocklayout</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Themes</title>

      <para>Themes are the skins in Xaraya. A theme is a collection of
      templates and css files that uses blocklayout to generate the final
      pages users will see. You can add multiple themes to Xaraya, eg have
      your own theme and the print theme. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Hooks</title>

      <para>Hooks are one of the nice key features of Xaraya. You will need
      some time to dive into the subject, but once mastered (and it's not that
      hard), you will see the enormous power.</para>

      <para>Xaraya uses hooks to let parts of the installation talk to other
      parts. The Site Admin can decide which hooks to allow in which case. The
      hooks are called at the main actions in a module. Eg, when a new item is
      created, the new item hook is called. The module that calls the hooks
      doesn't need to know in advance what hooks it will call, but just does
      the call. The responding modules get information about the new item and
      can take their actions.</para>

      <para>An example: When you have a module that will let the admin create
      new items (see the example module: admin-new), it is a good thing to
      call the new item hooks. This way, a module like dynamic data can show
      fields in the new item form that you don't need to program in there in
      advance. When the form is submitted to create the item, the function
      will call the create hook, which will send the data to the hooked
      modules. In the case of dynamic data, the create hook will store the
      data from the added fields together with information to which item the
      data is hooked.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Datastorage</title>

      <para></para>

      <section>
        <title>Itemtypes</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom tags</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>