<glossary>
  <glossdiv>
    <title>Glossary</title>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>API</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>application program interface (API): A formalized set of
        software calls and routines that can be referenced by an application
        program in order to access supporting network services</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>BitKeeper</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>BitKeeper: is a scalable configuration management system,
        supporting globally distributed development, disconnected operation,
        compressed repositories, change sets, and repositories as
        branches.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>Blocklayout</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>Blocklayout: is the theme-rendering engine intended to give
        theme developers a maximum of control over the appearance and
        functionality of their Xaraya website. The RFC for Blocklayout is
        located at http://docs.xaraya.com/docs/rfcs/rfc0010.html.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>GUI</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>gui: Acronym for graphical user interface. A computer
        environment or program that displays, or facilitates the display of,
        on-screen options, usually in the form of icons (pictorial symbols)
        or menus (lists of alphanumeric characters) by means of which users
        may enter commands. Note 1: Options are selected by using the
        appropriate hardware (e.g., mouse, designated keyboard keys, or
        touchpad) to move a display cursor to, or on top of, the icon or
        menu item of interest. The application or function so represented
        may then be selected (e.g., by clicking a mouse button, pressing the
        "enter" key, or by touching the touchpad). Note 2: Pronounced
        "gooey."</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>LDAP</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>LDAP: Abbreviation for lightweight directory access protocol.
        A simplified version of the X.500 standard, which version consists
        of a set of protocols developed for accessing information
        directories. [After Bahorsky]</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>METADATA</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>Metadata: is machine understandable information for the web.
        The W3C Metadata Activity addressed the combined needs of several
        groups for a common framework to express assertions about
        information on the Web, and was super ceded by the W3C Semantic Web
        Activity.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>MOVABLE TYPE</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>Movable Type: is Six Apart's powerful, customizable publishing
        system, which installs on web servers to enable individuals or
        organizations to manage and update weblogs, journals, and frequently
        updated website content.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>PHP</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>PHP: is a widely used general-purpose scripting language that
        is especially suited for Web development and can be embedded into
        HTML.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>POSTNUKE</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>PostNuke: is a community, content, collaborative management
        system, a C3MS. More information is located at
        http://www.postnuke.com</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>RSS</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>RDF Site Summary (RSS): - also referred to as Rich Site
        Summary - is a method of describing news or other Web content that
        is available for "feeding" (distribution or syndication) from an
        online publisher to Web users. RSS is an application of the
        Extensible Markup Language (XML) that adheres to the World Wide Web
        Consortium's Resource Description Framework (RDF). Originally
        developed by Netscape for its browser's Netcenter channels, the RSS
        specification is now available for anyone to use.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    
    <glossentry>
      <glossterm>XMLRPC</glossterm>
      
      <glossdef>
        <para>XMLRPC: is a spec and a set of implementations that allow
        software running on disparate operating systems, running in
        different environments to make procedure calls over the
        Internet.</para>
      </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
  </glossdiv>
</glossary>