<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction to Xaraya</title>

  <para><!--Maintained by:--><!--Status: Brainstorm--></para>

  <abstract>
    <para>What is Xaraya, what does it have to offer, what is the aim?</para>
  </abstract>

  <section>
    <title>A little history</title>

    <para>Xaraya has its deep roots in PHPNuke, which was forked to Postnuke.
    From Postnuke, a strong development team was formed that created Xaraya.
    Xaraya was born in 2002, when the website www.xaraya.org was
    registered.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Framework</title>

    <para>Xaraya is a framework. It is aimed at those, that want to create a
    webapplication, much more than just a content management system or a
    single use website. Xaraya offers a core system which manages the
    interaction with the database, presents data in a viewable way and can
    serve data to other applications.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The development</title>

    <para>Developing for Xaraya can be done in various areas.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>

      <para>Everyone that starts with Xaraya will see that you will be
      directed to the templates in the theme that you use. The templates are
      used by the blocklayout system of Xaraya. Templates use a xhtml type of
      language. You can use html, php or Xaraya tags in templates.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Modules</title>

      <para>If you find that you need a service or application that is not
      available yet in Xaraya, you can decide to create a module. This guide
      will show the details of how to create a module in the first section of
      the document. Developing for the Core of Xaraya is also possible, and is
      explained in section XX.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Core</title>

      <para>The core serves all the services you will need in extensions. Core
      development is done by the core developers. Currently core development
      focusses on two main lines: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maintaining a stable branch, which is at present is released
          as Xaraya Core 1.x</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Creating new development, based on PHP5 and Creole in the
          Xaraya Core 2 branch.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The main guidelines for development are given in a collection of
      RFC documents. These can be found in the documentation section of the
      Xaraya website.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Revision system: monotone</title>

        <para>Xaraya uses the revision software monotone (<ulink
        url="???">http://www.venge.net/monotone)</ulink>. The development is
        done in branches. Xaraya offers an online view of the monotone
        repositories via <ulink url="???">http://mt.xaraya.com/</ulink>.
        Whenever a change is commited, an email is generated in the monotone
        mailinglist (mt-notices). </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>