<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction to Xaraya</title>

  <!--Maintained by:-->

  <!--Status:-->

  <section>
    <title>What can you expect from Xaraya and this Guide?</title>

    <para>Xaraya is a flexible package that provides the requisite framework
    to create content management solutions and web applications for small,
    medium and large scale installations alike. Xaraya is currently used to
    develop blogs, community portals, content management solution (CMS) for
    SMEs, corporate intranet and multisite web solutions, and specialist
    industry solutions such as applications in e-commerce, finance, education,
    scientific, or medical areas.</para>

    <para>One of the inherent problems that often accompanies the flexibility
    demonstrated by Xaraya, is a perception of complexity. This Developer
    Guide aims to reduce that perception of complexity. The Guide does this by
    illustrating how easily it can be to understand the components that make
    up Xaraya, and how they can be programatically combined to deliver the
    functionality you need to create your web application.</para>

    <para>This Developer Guide provides the reader with: </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>information to help understand how Xaraya components work
        together to deliver web functionality</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>step by step instructions on how to develop Xaraya extensions
        such as Modules, Blocks and Hooks</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>the official and up to date guide ensuring your applications
        retain compatibility with future Xaraya versions, and can be easily
        maintained and upgraded</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>What do you need to know?</title>

    <para>To best use this Xaraya Developer Guide some assumptions in
    background knowledge are made. In particular this Guide is not a training
    manual on PHP, XHTML or popular databases such as MySQL , postgreSQL and
    SQLite and assumes some familiarity with them at least.</para>

    <para>In order to develop with Xaraya, you will need to have an
    appreciation of the following general Xaraya concepts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Overview of how Xaraya core functionality works and delivers
        pages to your web site</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Identify key Xaraya components such as modules, blocks, and
        hooks; their structure; and how they work together to provide
        functionality in your web application</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>How you can use Xaraya's templating system, Blocklayout, to
        manipulate data from Xaraya function output and use it to deliver
        content to users</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following chapter in this Guide begins this exploratory
    journey.</para>

    <para>The second part of this Guide, Extending Xaraya using modules,
    provides a detailed and practical look at how you can start working with
    Xaraya.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
