<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction to Xaraya</title>

  <para><!--Maintained by:--><!--Status: Brainstorm--></para>

  <abstract>
    <para>What is Xaraya, what does it have to offer, what is the aim?</para>
  </abstract>

  <section>
    <title>A little history</title>

    <para>Xaraya has its deep roots in PHPNuke, which was forked to Postnuke.
    From Postnuke, a strong development team was formed that created Xaraya.
    Xaraya was born in 2002, when the website www.xaraya.org was
    registered.</para>

    <para>Xaraya has evolved into an application framework. It is not just a
    content management system, but provides the tools to create a web-based
    application. This can be an intranet solution, but also a complete content
    management system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Framework</title>

    <para>Xaraya is a framework. It is aimed at those, that want to create a
    webapplication, much more than just a content management system or a
    single use website. Xaraya offers a core system which manages the
    interaction with the database, presents data in a viewable way and can
    serve data to other applications. </para>

    <para>Xaraya is a framework and therefore is inviting users to develop
    their own tailor made applications. The framework provides the tools, the
    developer only needs to have the idea what he/she wants.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The development</title>

    <para>Developing for Xaraya can be done in various areas. Some areas are
    standard as that all webmasters will use the tools, other areas are for
    teh more specialized users.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>

      <para>Everyone that starts with Xaraya will see that you will be
      directed to the templates in the theme that you use. Templates are used
      to display data. They dictate the way the data is shown.</para>

      <para>Xaraya uses the blocklayout system. This system has its won
      synthax, strongly related to PHP. Standard shippped templates can be
      reckognised by the .xd extension. When you modify templates, you are
      building a theme. This guide will not focus on the templates, but on the
      modules and core that generate the data used in the blocklayout
      templates.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Modules</title>

      <para>If you find that you need a service or application that is not
      available yet in Xaraya, you can decide to create a module. This guide
      will show the details of how to create a module in the first section of
      the document. Developing for the Core of Xaraya is also possible, and is
      explained in section XX.</para>

      <para>Modules are extensions to the core of Xaraya. They are built to
      provide one specific service. This can be some type of data storage,
      data handling or some other type of service. </para>

      <para>Xaraya ships with several core and base modules. Core modules are
      the ones that the core needs to communicate with the outside world. Base
      modules are those used by the majority of website builders. Core and
      base modules should be certified to work with the current core. The
      coding is Xaraya compliant and they are compliant to the Security Xaraya
      imposes.</para>

      <para>There are a lot of modules besides the base ones. You can find
      many of them in the monotone repository at mt.xaraya.com.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Core</title>

      <para>The core serves all the services you will need in extensions. Core
      development is done by the core developers. Currently core development
      focusses on two main lines:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maintaining a stable branch, which is at present is released
          as Xaraya Core 1.x</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Creating new development, based on PHP5 and Creole in the
          Xaraya Core 2 branch.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The main guidelines for development are given in a collection of
      RFC documents. These can be found in the documentation section of the
      Xaraya website.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Revision system: monotone</title>

        <para>Xaraya uses the revision software monotone (<ulink
        url="???">http://www.venge.net/monotone)</ulink>. The core development
        is done in branches in the core repository. Module extensions are
        stored in the modules repository. The Xaraya website offers an
        overview of the status of the various modules in the repository. Only
        the ones that are certified to work will be shipped by the Xaraya team
        in a Xarya distribution.</para>

        <para>Currenty there are four repositories in total: the core,
        modules, themes and languages repository. Each have a set of branches
        in them. Xaraya offers an online view of the monotone repositories via
        <ulink url="???">http://mt.xaraya.com/</ulink>. You can easily follow
        the progress of development by subscribing to the monotone
        notification mailinglist. Whenever a change is commited, an email is
        generated in the monotone mailinglist (mt-notices).</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>