<chapter>
  <title>Xaraya Module Operations</title>
  
  <para>This chapter covers how modules interact with Xaraya. The
  information in this section is correct for the 1.0 release of Xaraya, for
  other releases please get the most recent copy of the Xaraya Module
  Developers Guide.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Locating Modules</title>
    
    <para>All Xaraya modules must be placed within their own subdirectory of
    the 'modules' directory to be recognized. Modules placed anywhere else
    within the file-system will not be located correctly.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Working out Module Functionality</title>
    
    <para>A module might have administration or user functionality, or both.
    Xaraya works out which functionality each module has by looking for the
    files in 'xaradmin' or 'xaradminapi’ directories to confirm
    administration functionality, and in 'xaruser' or 'xaruserapi'
    directories to confirm user functionality. Lack of these directories
    results in Xaraya assuming that this specific module functionality does
    not exist.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Initializing Modules</title>
    
    <para>Initialization of modules is accomplished through the
    modname_init() in the 'xarinit.php' file within the module's directory
    function. No other functions are called when the module is initialized.
    All initialisation routines should go into the init function.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Activating/Deactivating Modules</title>
    
    <para>Activation and deactivation of modules is accomplished through
    field settings within the appropriate database table. Unlike earlier
    versions of Xaraya, no physical changes to the module directories are
    made to infer the activation status of the module.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Upgrading your module</title>
    
    <para>Upgrading your module is important. The upgrade function is
    located in the xarinit.php and named yourmodule_upgrade(). This function
    takes the current versionnumber as 'oldversion' and uses a switch to
    look for the correct upgrade routines. Make sure you provide all
    necessary steps for each version to upgrade to the next version. Provide
    an empty upgrade step when there is nothing todo. This way, the upgrade
    function will stay consistent. The versionid is set in the
    xarversion.php file.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Calling Module Functions</title>
    
    <para>Module functions are called through the xarModFunc() and
    xarModAPIFunc() functions. No direct calling of module functions is
    allowed, even from within the same module. Creating Module URLs Direct
    URLs to functions URLs for modules go through the 'index.php' entry
    point, and are defined by a number of parameters. The parameters that
    currently decide which particular module function to call are as
    follows: module The name of the module. This corresponds to the
    well-known name of the module, which can be found through the modules
    administration interface type The type of the module function. This is
    currently either 'user' for user functions or 'admin' for administrative
    functions. func The name of the function itself. This is
    module-dependent. If any of these parameters are undefined within a URL
    Xaraya will apply defaults to them. Note that both the names of the
    parameters and their default values might change, and as such it is not
    recommended to create direct URLs for anything but to either go through
    the Xaraya main page or to use the xarModURL() function to generate URLs
    that will always be internally consistent for any given version of
    Xaraya. You can also extend the xarModUrl call by adding a parameter
    call to the function in the form of an array. <programlisting><function>xarModURL('<parameter>module</parameter>', 'type', 'function', array('foo' =&gt; $bar))</function></programlisting>
    will create the input parameter of 'foo' having the value of
    $bar.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Function calls</title>
      
      <para>Another way of accessing the functionality of other modules is
      by calling their functions directly with the xarModFunc() function.
      Doing this allows a number of advantages over hooks, but also a number
      of disadvantages. In general, calling functions directly is more
      flexible as the module developer understands exactly which functions
      they are calling and can pass additional arguments to the function to
      customize its abilities. The disadvantages are that the module named
      in the function call needs to be installed and active on the system
      for the calls to work, and if this is replace by a different module
      providing similar functionality it will not work correctly.</para>
      
      <para>Using direct function calls to other modules is fine within a
      module, but the developer should consider the implications of this on
      systems that might not have the modules that they are using installed.
      Also, even if direct function calls are used then the module developer
      should still call hooks at the appropriate places in the code to allow
      for other extended functionality to be added to the module.</para>
      
      <para>An example of where direct function calls might be used within
      the Example module would be if the module developer wanted users to be
      able to rate various aspects of the picture displayed such as 'use of
      color' and 'originality'. In this case, a simple hook would not be
      able to accommodate this requirement, so the developer would instead
      make explicit calls to the 'Ratings' utility module to display a
      number of separate ratings, each with its own identifier. The hook
      call would still be made, which might also add a rating to the
      picture, but in this case, the value could be considered as the
      overall rating for the picture rather than that just for a specific
      part.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>