<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Xaraya Module Architecture</title>

  <!--Maintained by:-->

  <!--Status:-->

  <para>The Xaraya module system design allows for the maximum flexibility to
  developers whilst ensuring that the module can be accessed in a generic
  fashion by the Xaraya core, other modules, and remote systems given access
  through other interfaces such as XML-RPC. The main design characteristics of
  the module system are listed below.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Separation of User and Administrator Functions</title>

    <para>Separation of user and administrator functions allows for a much
    cleaner module. It speeds up the responsiveness of the module in the
    most-often used cases (i.e. user actions) as the module only needs to load
    the code that is required of it. It allows for work one area of the code
    (e.g. an admin GUI redesign) to take place without affecting the other
    areas. In addition, it gives an extra layer of security to help ensure
    that privileged functions cannot be executed inadvertently from user
    areas.</para>

    <para>It is sometimes not very clear what you can denote an admin or a
    user function. In general, admin functions are those function that deal
    with setting up the module and it's functioning, sometimes including the
    data in there. In Example module, that is a display module for users, it
    is an admin task to add data. Articles uses the same logic. User functions
    are the ones used by the the average user of the module, the normal site
    user. </para>

    <para>The seperation of user and admin functions should be clear, but
    supported with the correct use of privileges. Defining privileges will
    give you better control of who will enter what area of your
    extension.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Separation of Display and Operational Functions</title>

    <para>Separation of display and operational functions allows for areas
    within and without Xaraya to use the functionality supplied by a module.
    This is most obvious in the case of modules with blocks. Where the block
    might display its own information but use the module functions to gather
    that information. Other modules where this is hugely important are the
    utility modules; things like comments and rating systems, that have no
    real use on their own but can be coupled with other modules to provide
    generic and site-wide functionality at very little cost to the module
    developer.</para>

    <para>Operational functions go into the xar...api directory. These
    functions will not call a template at return, but are expected to return
    the result of their operation in one form or the other. Functions that
    will display data will always go in xaradmin or xaruser directories. The
    display functions normally return an array that is used by BlockLayout, in
    cooperation with the template the module provides. The exception here is
    blocks, that are placed in xarblocks/.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Single Directory Installation - Structure</title>

    <para></para>

    <para>Having a single install directory allows for much easier maintenance
    of large Xaraya systems, and far easier install and removal of modules
    both for the module developer and for the site administrator. Dependencies
    of the layout on the file system are no longer required, and as such, the
    module designer does not need to worry about on which systems his module
    might be deployed, and how it needs to interact with the underlying
    operating system to function correctly.</para>

    <para>This design option means that all your functions and data will go in
    the directory modules/yourmodule and the according child
    directories.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Module Directory Structure</title>

    <para>Xaraya modules have a very specific directory structure. This allows
    the Xaraya system to use a generic system to access all modules without
    needing to know specific information about each separate module that is
    built. Following the directory structure as laid out below is an absolute
    requirement of any Xaraya-compliant module. Extra files and directories in
    addition to those shown below are allowed. In addition, if any of the
    files below are not required (e.g. the module does not have database
    tables of its own so it does not require the xartables.php file) then they
    do not need to exist. However, files that perform the functions outlined
    below must comply with the file naming convention to allow the Xaraya
    system to load the suitable files at the appropriate times to ensure
    correct operation of the module.</para>

    <para>The layout shown is the full directory structure of the example
    module. The example module has all standard directories, and example files
    in all of them. Your module might not need all, but will at least need the
    xarinit.php and the xarversion.php files.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link linkend="dir1">modules/ (1)</link></para>

        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para><link linkend="dir2">example/ (2)</link></para>

            <orderedlist continuation="continues">
              <listitem>
                <para><link linkend="dir3">xaradmin/ (3)</link></para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>create.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>delete.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>main.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>modify.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>modifyconfig.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>new.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>update.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>updateconfig.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>view.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xaradminapi/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>create.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>delete.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>getmenulinks.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>menu.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>update.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xarblocks/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>first.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>modify-first.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>modify-others.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>others.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xarimages/</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xarproperties/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Dynamic_Example_Property.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xarstyles/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>style.css</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xartemplates/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>blocks/</para>

                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem>
                        <para>first.xd</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>index.html</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>modify-first.xd</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>modify-others.xd</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>others.xd</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>includes/</para>

                    <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                      <listitem>
                        <para>index.html</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>user-menu.xd</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>properties/</para>

                    <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                      <listitem>
                        <para>index.html</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>showinput-example.xd</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>showoutput.xd</para>
                      </listitem>

                      <listitem>
                        <para>validation-example.xd</para>
                      </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-delete.xd<indexterm>
                        <primary>templates</primary>
                      </indexterm></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-main.xd<indexterm>
                        <primary>templates</primary>
                      </indexterm></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-modify.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-modifyconfig.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-new.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>admin-view.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-display.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-main.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-menu.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-search.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-usermenu_form.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-usermenu_icon.xd</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>user-view.xd</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xartests/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>testexample.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xaruser/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>display.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>main.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>search.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>usermenu.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>view.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>xaruserapi/</para>

                <orderedlist continuation="continues">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>countitems.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>decode_shorturl.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>encode_shorturl.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>get.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>getall.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>getitemlinks.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>getitemtypes.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>getmenulinks.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>index.html</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>menu.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>search.php</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>validateitem.php</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <orderedlist continuation="continues" inheritnum="inherit">
          <listitem>
            <para>example.wsdl</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>index.html</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>xareventapi.php</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>xarinit.php</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>xartables.php</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>xarversion.php</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>(1<anchor id="dir1" />) The top-level directory in Xaraya for
    modules</para>

    <para>(2<anchor id="dir2" />) The directory that contains all of the
    module code (in this case the module is named 'example')</para>

    <para>(3<anchor id="dir3" />) The directory that contains all
    administrative GUI functions for the module</para>

    <para>(4) create.php This a standard function that is called with the
    results of the form supplied by xarModFunc(‘example’,’admin’,’new’) to
    create a new item. Syntax: @param string $’name’ – The name of the item to
    be created @param int $’number’ – The number of the item to be
    created</para>

    <para>(5) delete.php This standard function is called whenever an
    administrator wishes to delete a current module item. Note that this
    function is the equivalent of both the modify() and update() functions as
    it operates a form and processes its output. This is fine for simpler
    functions, but for complex operations such as creation and modification it
    is generally easier to separate them into separate functions. There is no
    requirement in the Xaraya MDG to use one or the other, so either or both
    can be used as seen appropriate by the module developer. Syntax: @param
    int $’exid’ - The id of the item to be deleted @param string $’confirm’ –
    Confirm that this item can be deleted</para>

    <para>(6) main.php This function is the default function, and is called
    whenever the module is initiated without defining arguments. As such, it
    can be used for a number of things, but most commonly, it either shows the
    module menu and returns or calls whatever the module designer feels should
    be the default function. (This is often the view function)</para>

    <para>(7) modify.php This is a standard admin function that is called
    whenever an administrator whishes to modify a current module item. Syntax:
    @param int $’exid’ the id of the item to be modified</para>

    <para>(8) modifyconfig.php This is the standard function to modify the
    configuration parameters for the module. (9) new.php This standard
    function is called whenever the administrator wishes to create a new
    module item.</para>

    <para>(10) update.php This is the standard function that is called with
    the results of the form supplied by xarModFunc(‘example’,
    ‘admin’,’modify’) to update a current item. Syntax: @param int $ ‘exid’ –
    The id of the item to be updated @param string $ ‘name’ – The name of the
    item to be updated @param int $ ‘number’ – The number of the item to be
    updated</para>

    <para>(11) updateconfig.php This standard function updates the
    configuration parameters of the module given the information passed back
    by the modification form.</para>

    <para>(12) view.php This standard function is called whenever the
    administrator wishes to view a module item.</para>

    <para>(13) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(14) xaradminapi The directory that contains all administrative
    database functions for the module.</para>

    <para>(15) create.php This standard function creates an item when the
    administrator wants to create an item in the database. Parameters are
    passed from the xaradmin/create.php. This function returns the example
    item upon success, or raises an exception error upon failing. Syntax:
    @param $args ['exid'] the ID of the item @param $args [‘name’] name of the
    item @param $args[‘number’] number of the item Returns the example item ID
    as integer on success, returns false on failure and raises BAD_PARAM,
    NO_PERMISSION, DATABASE_ERROR</para>

    <para>(16) delete.php This standard function deletes an item in the
    database. Parameters are passed from the xaradmin/delete.php. This
    function returns true upon success, or raises an exception error upon
    failing. Syntax: @param $args [‘exid’] name of the item Returns the
    example item ID as integer on success, returns false on failure and raises
    BAD_PARAM, NO_PERMISSION, DATABASE_ERROR</para>

    <para>(17) getmenulinks.php This is a utility function that passes
    individual menu items to the main menu. Returns array containing the
    menulinks for the admin menu items. (18) menu.php This function generates
    the common admin menu configuration</para>

    <para>(19) update.php This standard function updates an item when the
    administrator wants to change an item in the database. Parameters are
    passed from the xaradmin/update.php. This function returns the example
    item upon success, or raises an exception error upon failing. Syntax:
    @param $args ['exid'] the ID of the item @param $args [‘name’] name of the
    item @param $args[‘number’] number of the item Returns the example item ID
    as integer on success, returns false on failure and raises BAD_PARAM,
    NO_PERMISSION, DATABASE_ERROR</para>

    <para>(20) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a url.
    (21) xarblocks/ This directory contains the files for generating blocks
    for the module.</para>

    <para>(22) first.php This is the code for the example block for the
    example module.</para>

    <para>(23) others.php This is the code for the example block for the
    example module.</para>

    <para>(24) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(25) xarimages/ This directory contains image files that are
    associated with the example module.</para>

    <para>(26) admin.gif This is the image that is displayed in the example
    module administration overview.</para>

    <para>(27) admin_generic.gif This is an optional image that can be
    displayed in the example module administration overview.</para>

    <para>(28) preferences.gif This preferences image is used in the example
    module.</para>

    <para>(29) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(30) xartemplates/ This directory contains the template files used
    by blocklayout for displaying pages within the example module.</para>

    <para>(31) blocks/ This directory contains the template files used by
    blocklayout to display the blocks for the example module.</para>

    <para>(32) first.xd Templates file for the first block in the example
    module.</para>

    <para>(33) firstAdmin.xd Templates file for the first block administration
    page for the example module. (34) othersAdmin.xd Templates file for the
    others block administration page for the example module.</para>

    <para>(35) example-firstblock-modify.xd Templates file for the first block
    administration modify settings page. (36) admin-delete.xd Templates file
    for administration delete function. (37) admin-main.xd Templates file for
    administration main function.</para>

    <para>(38) admin-menu.xd Templates file for the administration menu for
    Example module.</para>

    <para>(39) admin-modify.xd Templates file for administration modify item
    page.</para>

    <para>(40) admin-modifyconfig.xd Templates file for administration modify
    configuration page.</para>

    <para>(41) admin-new.xd Templates file for administration new item
    page.</para>

    <para>(42) admin-view.xd Templates file for administration view item
    page.</para>

    <para>(43) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(44) user-display.xd Templates file for the user display
    page.</para>

    <para>(45) user-main.xd Templates file for the users main page.</para>

    <para>(46) user-menu.xd Templates file for the users menu. (47)
    user-usermenu_icon.xd Template file for example user menu hook.</para>

    <para>(48) user-view.xd Templates file for the user display items
    page.</para>

    <para>(49) user-usermenu_form.xd Templates file for example hook for user
    menu.</para>

    <para>(50) xaruser/ The directory that contains all users GUI functions
    for the module.</para>

    <para>(51) display.php This standard function provides detailed
    information on a single item available from the module. Syntax: @param
    $args an array of arguments (if called by other modules) @param $args
    [‘objectid’] – A generic objected (if called by other modules) @param
    $args [‘exid’] – The item id used for this module</para>

    <para>(52) main.php This standard function is the default function, and is
    called whenever the module is initiated without defining arguments. As
    such, it can be used for a number of things, most commonly, it either
    shoes the module menu and returns or calls whatever the module designer
    feels should be the default function. (This is often the view()
    function)</para>

    <para>(53) user-menu.php This standard function is used to display the
    user menu hook.</para>

    <para>(54) view.php This standard function is used to provide an overview
    of all the items available from the module.</para>

    <para>(55) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(56) xaruserapi/ The directory that contains all user database
    functions for the module.</para>

    <para>(57) encode_shorturl.php The standard functions that encode module
    parameters into some virtual path that will be added to index.php, and
    decode a virtual path back to the original module parameters.</para>

    <para>(58) countitems.php This utility function counts the number of items
    held by the module. Returns the number of items as an integer type with
    the number of items held by this module.</para>

    <para>(59) decode_shorturl.php This function extracts arguments from short
    urls and passes them back to the xarGetRequestInfo() api function.</para>

    <para>(60) get.php This standard function retrieves a specific example
    item from the database. Syntax: @param $args [‘exid’ – Id of example item
    to get Returns item array, or false on failure Raises exceptions
    BAD_PARAM, NO_PERMISSION, DATABASE_ERROR</para>

    <para>(61) getall.php This standard function retrieves all example items
    from the database. Syntax: @param $ numitems – The number of items to
    retrieve (default -1 = all) @param $ startnum – Start with this item
    number (default 1) Returns an array of items, or false on failure Raises
    exceptions BAD_PARAM, NO_PERMISSION, DATABASE_ERROR</para>

    <para>(62) getmenulinks.php This utility function will pass individual
    menu items to the main menu. Returns an array containing the menu links
    for the main menu. (63) menu.php This standard function will generate the
    common menu configuration.</para>

    <para>(64) validateitem.php This standard function validates argument
    arrays that are passed for writing to the database.</para>

    <para>(65) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(66) getitemlinks.php This utility function passes individual item
    links to other calling functions Syntax: @param $args [‘itemtype’] – Item
    type (optional) @param $args [‘itemids’] – array of item ids to get
    Returns an array containing the itemlink(s) for the item(s)</para>

    <para>(67) xareventapi.php This standard function is the event handler for
    the system event ServerRequest Returns bool</para>

    <para>(68) xarinit.php This file contains the initialization, upgrade, and
    delete functions for the example module. Functions include example_init()
    – example_upgrade() – example_delete()</para>

    <para>(69) xartables.php This file contains the table definitions for the
    example module/</para>

    <para>(70) example.wsdl This file contains an example soap xml schema that
    connects and returns the number of items in the example database.</para>

    <para>(71) index.html This is a blank index.html file to prevent someone
    from viewing the directory contents when access this directory via a
    url.</para>

    <para>(72) xaradmin.php A depreciated file; all admin functions should be
    separated into individual files and placed into the xaradmin/
    directory.</para>

    <para>(73) xaradminapi.php A depreciated file; all adminapi functions
    should be separated into individual files and placed into the xaradminapi/
    directory.</para>

    <para>(74) xaruser.php A depreciated file; all user functions should be
    separated into individual files and placed into the xaruser/
    directory.</para>

    <para>(75) xaruserapi.php A depreciated file; all userapi functions should
    be separated into individual files and placed into the xaruserapi/
    directory.</para>

    <para>(76) xarversion.php This file contains the module ID number, author,
    and version information for the example module.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Standard Module Functions</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Variable handling</title>

    <para>Variables are loaded through xarVarFetch calls in order to be
    processed, checked for validity, as well as proper handling on unset vars,
    etc. Instead of relying on $_POST or $_GET calls throughout your module
    and then cleaning the input, Xaraya has a very robust way of handling the
    variable. You can process parameters in your function via the function
    itself as well. This is normally done by API functions, as parameters
    present in the environment can be different from the ones passed to these
    variables.</para>

    <para>An example call would be: <code> if (!xarVarFetch('itemsperpage',
    'int', $itemsperpage, 10, XARVAR_NOT_REQUIRED)) return; </code></para>

    <para>This fetches the <varname>$itemsperpage</varname> variable from the
    input variable 'itemsperpage' and validates it by applying the $validation
    rules, in this case it being an integer.</para>

    <para>The functions works in this order:</para>

    <para>First try to use the variable provided (itemsperpage), if this is
    not set (or the XARVAR_DONT_REUSE flag is used) then it tries to get the
    variable from the input (POST/GET methods for now). It then tries to
    validate the variable through xarVarValidate with the validation of 'int'
    (integer).</para>

    <para>After the call the <varname>$value</varname> parameter is passed by
    reference is set to the variable value converted to the proper type
    according to the validation applied.</para>

    <para>The $defaultValue provides a default value that is returned when the
    variable is not present or doesn't validate correctly.</para>

    <para>The <varname>$flag</varname> parameter is a bitmask between the
    following constants: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_GET_OR_POST</constant></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_GET_ONLY</constant></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_POST_ONLY</constant></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_NOT_REQUIRED</constant></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_VAL_RESULT</constant></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> You can force to get the variable only from GET
    parameters or POST parameters by setting the <varname>$flag</varname>
    parameter to one of <constant>XARVAR_GET_ONLY</constant> or
    <constant>XARVAR_POST_ONLY</constant>.</para>

    <para>You can force xarVarFetch not to reuse the variable by setting the
    <varname>$flag</varname> parameter to
    <constant>XARVAR_DONT_REUSE</constant>.</para>

    <para>Forcing xarVarFetch to return the validation result without throwing 
    an exception needs the <varname>$flag</varname> parameter to be set to
    <constant>XARVAR_NOT_REQUIRED</constant> + <constant>XARVAR_VAL_RESULT</constant>. 
    This combination is predefinied as <constant>XAVAR_VAL_REQ</constant>.</para>

    <para>By default $flag is XARVAR_GET_OR_POST which means that xarVarFetch
    will lookup both GET and POST parameters and that if the variable is not
    present or doesn't validate correctly an exception will be raised.</para>

    <para>The <varname>$prep</varname> flag will prepare
    <varname>$value</varname> by passing it to one of the following:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_PREP_FOR_NOTHING</constant>: no prep
          (default)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_PREP_FOR_DISPLAY</constant>:
          <function>xarVarPrepForDisplay(<varname>$value</varname>)</function></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_PREP_FOR_HTML</constant>:
          <function>xarVarPrepHTMLDisplay(<varname>$value</varname>)</function></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>XARVAR_PREP_TRIM</constant>:
          <function>trim(<varname>$value</varname>)</function></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <section>
      <title>Pitfalls with xarVarFetch()</title>

      <para>Loops with 1 $variable name</para>

      <para>If you have built a loop with this function in it, you will notice
      that the value of the first found instance is returned every single
      call, even though you may be calling for different named $_POST or $_GET
      elements. To solve this either use a variable variablename, or use the
      flag XARVAR_DONT_REUSE.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Fetching input variables</title>

        <programlisting>
        // If this is in your template/xhtml
        &lt;input name="item1" value=1&gt;
        &lt;input name="item2" value=2&gt;

        xarVarFetch('item1', 'str::', $value, NULL ) //  $value= 1

        xarVarFetch('item2', 'str::', $value, NULL ) //  $value= 1 !!!
      </programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>It is currently not possible to discern between 'Not Found' and
      'Validation Failed', if you need to know use the validate function and
      $_POST/$_GET directly in the error handling part.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Module variables</title>

      <para>Module variables can be set using
      xarModSetVar('module','modulevariable','initial value')</para>

      <para>Example: <programlisting>xarModSetVar('julian','startDayOfWeek','1');</programlisting></para>

      <para>These variables can be called later by
      <function>xarModGetVar(module, variablename):</function><programlisting>$cal_sdow = xarModGetVar('julian','startDayOfWeek'); </programlisting>Now,
      we can even make this a variable that the admin can set. Then add to the
      modifyconfig.xd template the following code snippet: <programlisting>&lt;input type="text" name="startDayOfWeek" value="#xarModGetVar('julian','startDayOfWeek')#" size="2" /&gt;</programlisting>
      and in the updateconfig function:<programlisting>//check the input with
xarVarFetch if (!xarVarFetch('bold', 'checkbox', $bold, false, XARVAR_NOT_REQUIRED)) return;
// Set the Module Variable:
xarModSetVar('example', 'bold', $bold); </programlisting>This lets the site
      admin -who has access to <function>modifyconfig()</function> set the
      variable by typing in a number for the variable 'startDayOfWeek', or
      'bold' as in the example.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>User Variables</title>

    <para>A user variable is an entity identified by a name that stores a
    value owned by exactly one user. Xaraya offers two API functions to
    manipulate user variables, they are xarUserGetVar() and xarUserSetVar().
    The purpose of xarUserGetVar() is to allow read access to one user
    variable. In contrast to that, xarUserSetVar() allows write access to one
    user variable. The $name parameter is checked against metadata to make
    sure the variable is registered. Xaraya keeps some metadata about every
    user variable, so you cannot access the $name user variable if its
    metadata is not registered.</para>

    <para>A module can register a new user variable by providing its metadata
    only if it has the right permissions (permissions are checked by the
    registration function). Usually the registration process should take place
    at initialization time for a module that wants to use the $name user
    variable during its life cycle. Xaraya does not impose any restriction on
    the value of $name except for duplicate and reserved names.</para>

    <para>As of this writing, the list of reserved names consists of:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><constant>uid</constant> The user id.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>name</constant> The user display name on the system.
          “Name” should be used in any case that you are displaying the user
          name, IE author fields, etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>uname</constant> The user name is the system
          variable used to differentiate one user from another in string vice
          integer format. This variable should not be used to display
          information about the user for consistency and security
          reasons.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>email</constant> The email address of the
          user.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>status</constant> The status of the user (active,
          inactive, deleted etc).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><constant>auth_module</constant> The authentication module
          last used for this user.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>You are advised (even for performance reasons) to use the following
    naming convention: <programlisting>$name := $module_name . '_' .
  $real_name</programlisting></para>

    <para>To register the $name user variable you have to use the module API
    function register_user_var() exported by the Modules module.</para>

    <para>Here is an example: <programlisting>
    $module_name = 'MyModule';

    $variable_name = 'MaxLinesPerPage';

    $metadata['label'] = $module_name . '_' . $variable_name;

    $metadata['dtype'] = _UDCONST_INTEGER; //one of the values  defined for dynamic user data variable types

    $metadata['default'] = 20; $metadata['validation'] = 'num:&gt;=:10&amp;num:&lt;=:100';

    xarModAPILoad('Modules', 'admin');

    $result = xarModAPIFunc('Modules', 'admin','register_user_var', $metadata);

    if (!isset($result)) {
        // xarModAPIFunc() failed
    } elseif ($result == false) {
        // registration failed
    } else {
        // registration succeeded
    }
    </programlisting></para>

    <para>As you can see in this example, a descriptive array for the new user
    variable is created first, and later register_user_var is called with that
    array as parameter. Meaningful keys for the array are label, dtype,
    default and validation. The label field is mandatory; it specifies the
    user variable name as you'll refer later in xarUserGetVar() and
    xarUserSetVar() $name parameter. The dtype field is mandatory; it can take
    one of the following values: _UDCONST_STRING, _UDCONST_TEXT,
    _UDCONST_FLOAT, _UDCONST_INTEGER. You should obviously choose the right
    value for the data type that the new user variable would contain. The
    default field is optional; Used when the user has not yet set a value for
    the new user variable. The validation field is optional; refer to the next
    section to get an overview of variable validation. To unregister a user
    variable you have to call the unregister_user_var(), which is located in
    the users module admin API. You should call that API only at
    uninstallation time for your modules. Keep in mind that by calling
    unregister_user_var() all the existing values for that user variable will
    be deleted from user data. As described in this document, Xaraya offers
    support for module variables too. If you get confused from that, and
    cannot see the distinction between these different things, here is a
    little explanation. Module variables are system-wide variables, shared
    between each module user, like configuration variables. No particular user
    owns them, and even if they do they are protected by permissions for write
    access, they are typically administrative-side variables. You are
    encouraged to use them when you have a need to give administrators the
    possibility to choose some behaviors of your module. However, when those
    behaviors are related to user preferences you should avoid using module
    variables and register a new user variable to be used in your code.</para>

    <para>As an example, you can consider the above code listing, where a new
    user variable is registered to allow every single module user to choose
    his own MaxLinePerPage setting. Now it is reasonable to have selected this
    choice, but here we could have chosen a unique shared module var as well.
    On the other hand, you do not have this kind of freedom, for example
    consider the authldap module in some cases. It needs to access a LDAP
    server, so it needs a variable that contains the LDAP server hostname.
    Obviously this variable should be a module variable, and access to it
    should be granted only to administrators with the right permissions. We
    invite you to ponder this issue for a while before you settle on module
    vars or user vars.</para>

    <para>Setting xarUserVars</para>

    <para>All user vars should be set from adding Dynamic Data on the roles
    module. This will give you the greatest benefit and will present the
    variables to all modules on the system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Templates</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing, activating and upgrading</title>

    <para>The installation, activation, upgrading and deinstallation of the
    module is directed by funcions in <filename>xarinit.php</filename>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Special Functions for Content Modules</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Special components for Utility Modules</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interacting with other Xaraya components</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>