<back>
  <section title="Future features">
    <t>
      Widgets: This feature will abstract common User Interface components
      into templatable tags.  The goal of such a feature is to give common
      components a consistent look and feel and cut down on code duplication
      while also making these features easy to use.
    </t>
    <t>
      Because widgets are meant for common usage, it is good practice for
      their output to take on a consistent appearance.  This makes for an
      easier and more pleasant user experience, and assures some level of
      consistency within a theme.
    </t>
    <t>
      Widgets will have certain constraints on their design, such as:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>must generate a common piece of markup</t>
        <t>must be theoretically useable across modules</t>
        <t>must implement only a single template</t>
        <t>must present a point of interaction between the user and Xaraya, and/or</t>
        <t>must present markup that allows standard data to be returned to xaraya</t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>
      Dynamic Style Sheets: This feature would use server-side browser
      sniffing to identify what CSS classes &amp; attributes a given module can
      render (reasonably) correctly. Based on the result, either a &lt;style&gt;
      or &lt;link&gt; tag to the css would be output. The tag would reference a
      php script (css.php) which would actually generate the style sheet
      from database records.
    </t>
    <t>
      Theme Management: Blocklayout will necessitate the creation of
      administration tools to manage themes. These would include a template
      manager, theme variable manager, and possibly a theme
      installer/uninstaller (similar to what modules have).
    </t>
    <t>
      Multi-module layouts: This feature would allow Xaraya to display
      output from more than one module during a page request. Major core
      changes are required; hooks may provide some insight into how to
      implement this feature. At the moment, simple multi-module layouts
      are possible via the xar:module tag.
    </t>
    <t>
      The help system will add a new widget:
      <artwork>
        &lt;xar:help /&gt; (scheduled beyond 1.0)
      </artwork>
    </t>
  </section>
</back>
