<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section anchor="blockgroup" title="&lt;xar:blockgroup /&gt;">
  <t>
    The Blockgroup tag is responsible for rendering a group of
    blocks. If empty, it renders the named group from the
    database.  Otherwise, it can specify the box template to use
    on all &lt;xar:block/&gt; tags within it.
  </t>
  <section title="Forms">
    <t>Empty form
    <t>The group of blocks is determined at runtime based on the
    value of the name attribute. The name references a value entered
    in the blocks administration indicating which block group to render.
    </t>
    <t>Block form
    <t>When specified as a block tag all the block tags specified within the
    blockgroup are rendered.
    </t>
    </t>
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Attributes">
    <t>
      <list>
        <t><spanx>[id]</spanx>
        <t>an identifier for the tag.</t>
        </t>
        <t><spanx>name</spanx>
        <t>The name of the block group to render. When the tag is
        used in its empty form this attribute is required. The attribute is
        ignored when the tag is used in its block form.
        </t>
        </t>
        <t><spanx>template</spanx>
        <t>Name of the box template to use by default on all blocks within
        the blockgroup tag. In its empty form, the template will be used
        to wrap all blocks within it. In its non-empty form, each block
        may individually override the box template, but otherwise will
        share the template defined by this attribute. This attribute is
        optional.
        </t>
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Syntax examples">
    <t>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
Renders the blockgroup 'left'. The template attribute is ignored or,
when in strict rendering creates an exception:

<xar:blockgroup name="left" template="SeaBreeze_left"/>

Renders the block 'login' in a blockgroup using the template
'SeaBreeze_center' for the blockgroup. The login block uses the block
(inner) template 'simple_login' and is wrapped in the box (outer)
template 'SeaBreeze_center':

<xar:blockgroup template="SeaBreeze_center">
<xar:block type="login" module="users" template=";simple_login"/>
</xar:blockgroup>]]>
      </artwork>
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Context">
    <t>Parent tag: none.</t>
    <t>Child tags: in block form at least one <xref target="block">&lt;xar:block&gt;</xref> tag.</t>
  </section>
</section>
