<section anchor="ddproperties" title="Dynamic Data Property Templates">
  <t>
    Dynamic Data Properties can also provide templated output. It is a simple process 
    to make the required changes to the data property itself, and supply appropriately 
    named templates.
  </t>
  <t>
    The <spanx>showInput()</spanx> and <spanx>showOutput()</spanx> functions of each
    dynamic property return data to a corresponding template in the respective
    modules/[modulename]/xartemplate/properties directory.
    Previously the <spanx>showInput()</spanx> and <spanx>showOutput()</spanx> functions
    of each dynamic property returned data to a corresponding template in the
    modules/dynamicdata/xartemplate directory. These are slowly being moved to
    the new location in the properties' respective modules.
  </t>
  <t>
    The directory structure and changes required for dynamic data
    property templates are illustrated below.
    The <spanx>propertyname</spanx> used for the specific template name
    is taken from the corresponding property array in the
    getBasePropertyInfo() function in the dynamic property itself
    at
    modules/[modulename]/xarproperties/Dynamic_[propertydescription]_property.php.
    <artwork><![CDATA[
html/
    |-- modules/
    |   |-- <module name>/
    |       |-- xarproperties/
    |       |       Dynamic_<propertydescription>_property.php
    |       |-- xartemplates/
    |           |-- properties/
    |                   <showinput|showoutput>[-<propertyname>].xd
    |-- themes/
        |-- <theme name>/
            |-- modules/
                |-- <module name>/
                    |-- properties/
                            <showinput|showoutput>[-<propertyname>].xt

]]>
    </artwork>
  </t>
  <t>
    The dynamic data properties are in the process of being moved
    from an old structure illustrated below, to the new directory
    structure illustrated above. The following diagram is left for
    the purpose of reference where dynamic data properties are
    still to be moved to the new structure. It should be used only
    in those specific cases until those properties are relocated
    to their respective module under the new structure. Note in
    particular the [admin|user] part of the template names are
    only used in the older structure illustrated below.
    <artwork><![CDATA[
html/
    |-- modules/
    |   |-- dynamicdata/
    |       |-- xartemplates/
    |               <admin-showinput|user-showoutput>[-<propertyname>].xd
    |
    |-- includes/
    |   |-- properties/
    |           Dynamic_<propertydescription>_property.php
    |
    |-- themes/
        |-- <theme name>/
            |-- modules/
                |-- dynamicdata/
                        <admin-showinput|user-showoutput>[-<propertyname>].xt

    ]]></artwork>
  </t>

  <t>
    Details of specific tags used to retrieve and display dynamic
    property data within module templates is documented in RFC0007
    Modularized Data. Further details on retrieval and display of
    dynamic property data can be found in the overview and
    templates (as comments) of the Dyn_Example module.
  </t>
</section>
