<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<rfc number="0001" category="info">
	<front>
		<title>Install System</title>
		<author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
			<organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
			<address>
				<email/>
				<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date month="June" year="2002"/>
		<!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
		<abstract>
			<t>The contents of this RFC contain the literal content of the old plain
	text version of RFC-0001</t>
			<t>When time is a less scarcer good, someone might convert the plain text
	into structured XML so we can benefit from it.
      </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
	<middle>
		<!-- One content section is mandatory -->
		<section title="Introduction ">
			<t>
			   The following RFC is a first summary and contains some solution
   proposals either compiled from the basic documents or from general
   definitions concerning Install Sytems in other CMSs
</t>
<t>
 Our install system is currently the best install system of all the free CMSs that already exist, and prolly better than
 the commercial ones. But, let's face facts, it needs some serious work to make it change with the times. Many things
 are changing within Xaraya. Our install system needs to be updated to keep up with these, and expandible for
 later use.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="List of requirements for the Install System">
			<t>
			<list>
				<t>SECURITY...many users do not delete the install directory...let's make sure it can't be used again if possible</t>
				<t>MORE MODULAR...let's make it pluginable or even scriptable to do the things we want it to do.</t>
				<t>SMALLER...let's follow through and use our new userapi, and adminapi functions to do the real work </t>
				<t>EASIER TO MODIFY...a must..it shall be coded using pnHTML as much as possible.</t>
				<t>More userfriendly: Add much more helpful texts to the installer</t>
				<t>Signed modules: Sign modules with a MD5 or equivalent to prevent hacks</t>
				<t>Database abstraction: Support different databases in the install </t>
				<t>Upgrades: Add more CMS systems to the upgrade scripts</t>
				<t>Themes install: Use the installer to also add themes</t>
				<t>Provide optional signup for support forums</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Solution proposals - database tables ADD">
			<t/>
		</section>
		<section title="Solution proposals - functions ADD">
			<t>
			 Installer Use Case (John Cox)
 I go to Modules Admin in my site. With the listing of modules that I already have installed, there is also a
 list of Modules that are "Official" and validated to run off this system. If I wanted to install the
 module then it would be just the matter of pushing an "Install Module" form button and I allow the script to
 do the rest of the work.
</t>
<t>
 The script would then initiate the server to server transfer (we might have to force a chmod here, or have
 a chmod check). This grabs the files and installs the module. Once the files are installed, we would
 probably have to push another button to continue the install. With that the Modules Admin grabs the
 version file and does two things. It will first propegate the modules vars table, and it will check to
 see if the install variable is active. If active, it also installs the SQL necessary for the module.
</t>
<t>
 What this will do is neccessitate the need for a modules repository, which is what we wanted way back
 in the planning stage of Xaraya. It will need to be maintained. I also believe that we will need to have
 a file that each site will load to check to see the official modules that are available. I believe that
 we could just load this on request and not on each page load of modules admin.
 </t>
<t>
Anyway some thoughts on a way to go. I'd really invite anyone to comment. I might not be grounded
 completely with the install process, but I really think that it would be a pretty cool thing to do, and
 would be unique.
</t>
<t>
 Installer Flow of Events
</t>
<t>
<list>
	<t>1.Select Language</t>
	<t>2.Do Environment checks</t>
	<t>3.Enter Database information</t>
	<t>4.Create / Modify database (core only) </t>
	<t>5.Switch to module installer</t>
	<t>6.Select modules to download </t>
	<t>7.Download modules</t>
	<t>8.Install / Upgrade modules</t>
	<t>9.Configure modules</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Installer Design Tenets 
</t>
<t>
<list>
	<t>Use xarAPI as early as possible</t>
	<t>Seperate throw-away parts from reusable parts: Bootstrapping vs Module Install</t>
	<t>Integrate Module Installer into Modules module</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Implementation Considerations 
</t>
<t>
 (Francisco Sam Castillo)
</t>
<t>
 An addendum to my prior post would be that the normal php limitations
 that are imposed Under php safe mode and other possible constrains that are available and
 needed by Sysadmins that aim to lock down domains and secure the virtual users
 data are not in Effect under perl with the same scope, thus you really benefit from
 having the best Of this 2 wounderfull languages one for all database, web processes and
 another for Backend services and maintenance, of course this can also be
 accomplished by using The cgi or stand alone php but that is a questionable solution since you
 are not always Granted this option in all servers and even when you could in fact
 compile your own Php cgi binary not all hosts allow this now, and all of them no matter
 which architecture Of *nix use perl, and if talking about win32 systems well ?ActivePerl is
 available to them And in that case uid/gid  issues are no relevant because NT / w2k or XP
 do not have Such security layouts in them in such a greater detail as a unix system
 has.
</t>
<t>
 Thus maybe if the win32 user base is big enough or has problems in
 getting perl support But has php, then a second engine for this in php would work under this
 types of servers.
</t>
<t>
 This would cover all possibilities IMHO.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Relationship of the System to other areas">
			<t>
			<list>
				<t>Modules module: Is invoked for module installs / upgrades</t>
				<t>Module registry: Check for new versions, download modules</t>
				<t>xarDDL: Table creation support for different database types</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Code that will need to be rewritten">
			<t/>
		</section>
		<section title="Basic documents for this RFC">
			<t>
			[1] Module Dependencies: http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/10572 
</t>
<t>
[2] Modules Remote Install: http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/8725 
</t>
<t>
[3] Securiy Issues with Remote Install: http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/8739
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Tools that need to be created from scratch">
			<t/>
		</section>
		<section title="Retractions ">
			<t>
			We list features that were considered but rejected for this Install System below.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Open Issues">
			<t>
			Write access to modules directory. Autoinstalling modules is fraught with many security issues. 
</t>
<t>
 Jim McDonald writes:
</t>
<t>
 My two biggest worries are that unauthorised uses could get to this through
 some sort of security hole and really trash the Xaraya install, and
 that it will require the modules directory to be set to an insecure
 setting to accomplish this. Bad directory permissions is one of the
 current outstanding areas where Xaraya doesn't look good, and this
 will just make it worse.
</t>
<t>
 If we are going to do this I'd prefer to see it as an option at
 install-time rather than something that is automatically ready to go.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgements ">
			<t>
			<list>
				<t> Jim McDonald</t>
				<t>John Cox</t>
				<t>Andy Varganov</t>
				<t>Jim Barchuk</t>
				<t>Lawrence Akka</t>
				<t>Greg Allan</t>
				<t>Aidan Humphreys</t>
				<t>Scott Kindley</t>
				<t>Francisco Sam Castillo</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Changelog ">
			<t>
			    0.1 (Febuary 3, 2002) John Robeson
</t>
<t>
       Initial Version
</t>
<t>
    0.2 (June 23, 2002) gregorrothfuss
</t>
<t>
        Resources added
</t>
<t>
        Use Cases
			</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
</rfc>
