<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc number="0028" category="bcp">
  <!-- Front matter is used for identification of author and organisation -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="devprocess">Xaraya Development process: repository model and tool usage</title>
    <author initials="M.R." surname="van der Boom" fullname="Marcel van der Boom">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
        <email>marcel@xaraya.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J" surname="Schrage" fullname="Jan Schrage">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jan@xaraya.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2002"/>
    
    <!-- Initiating team for this RFC -->
    <workgroup>Repository managers</workgroup>
    
    <!-- List keywords for the RFC here -->
    <keyword>rfc</keyword>
    <keyword>repository</keyword>
    
    <!-- The abstract summarises in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This RFC describes the development process used by the Xaraya development Group, 
        both in general process terms as in explicit tool usage terms.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    
    <note title="Implementation of policy">
      <t>
        With hindsight, since the first revision of this document, the described policy has 
        not been completely implemented so far. My personal opinion is that this is due to
        the following factors:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>learning curve for bitkeeper</t>
          <t>code is still in flux</t>
          <t>eagerness for producing code</t>
        </list>
        The policy described in (part a) of this document is still the desired policy and
        I will be working on that process to asymptotically reach the process as described
        in this document.
      </t>
      <t>
        However, the most important parts of the process are in place such as the scenario
        analogy. With the bitkeeper suite of tools, most of this process is not visible but
        automatically arranged for.
      </t>
    </note>
    
  </front>
  
  <!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
    <section title="Repository model">      
      <t>Repository supported scenario based development</t>
      
      <t>
        The first part of this document describes the policy for the Xaraya source
        repository. It is written with no particular repository tool in
        mind. (At the time of writing we use CVS) We will refer to the tool
        used as SCM (Software Configuration Manager for lack of a better
        term) to keep this part of the document valid when we decide to switch to
        another tool. We are evaluating subversion
        (<eref target="http://subversion.tigris.org">http://subversion.tigris.org</eref>)
        , bitkeeper
        (<eref target="http://www.bitkeeper.com">http://www.bitkeeper.com</eref>)
        as replacements for CVS to give us more efficient process
        support.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        To keep the policy readable, the terms used are the ones which
        are common to CVS. Other SCM tools might use other words to
        describe the same principles. The actual implementation of
        this policy with the tool of our choice in in <xref target="scmusage">part B</xref> of this document.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The document assumes you know how to use a SCM. The text
        focuses on the rules to guarantee a pristine repository
        supporting our development team instead of obstructing it. If
        the SCM cannot support our process, we&#39;ll have to come up
        with some kind of self-discipline guidelines to implement our
        process. If possible and reasonable we will let the SCM do
        some sanity checks to keep developers on the right
        track. Please read these guidelines and stick to them. Each
        section is accompanied by a section &quot;Possible
        support/enforcement&quot; which lists a possibility to be able
        to support the guideline. It does not mean that these measure
        are in fact in place, but they might be some day!
      </t>
      
      <section anchor="Formats" title="Formats">
        <t>
          The file format used in the Xaraya repository tree is Unix,
          i.e. lines end with LF. If you are not using a *nix system
          please turn off any auto-conversion-to-proprietary-format in
          your editor, as this will mess up things for other
          developers and will lead to php execution errors.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Take special care in naming files. Although a *nix
          file-system is generally case-sensitive and won&#39;t
          complain if you commit a FILE and a file and a FiLe. Windows
          and Mac systems will not be able to distinguish these files
          and will not be able to use the repository.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Xaraya uses the PEAR coding standard (<eref
          target="http://pear.php.net">http://pear.php.net</eref>).
          Please read these guidelines and follow them when you
          code. This includes using phpdoc tags for documenting your
          code (<eref
          target="http://www.phpdoc.de">http://www.phpdoc.de</eref>)
        </t>
        
        <t>Possible support by SCM:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>check for CR/LF Action: warn/cancel commit;</t>
            <t>signal on pre-commit that same name (case-insensitive)
              exists, Action: warn/cancel commit</t>
            <t>lint-like tool: Action: warn only</t>
            <t>basic check for documentation tags Action: warn only</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Development_process" title="Development process">
        <t>
          The development in Xaraya is a team effort. We all agree
          that the quality of our code needs to be as high as
          possible. To support this goal we have defined a development
          process which will be supported by the SCM tool.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Before we describe the process let&#39;s define the terms we
          use to describe it.
        </t>
        
        <section title="Trees, trunks, scenarios, branches, tags and others">
          <t>
            <list>
              <t><em>Tree:</em></t>
              <t>
                The tree is the total of all elements, typically
                files, containing the sources of the project, which we
                want to manage. The files are not limited to source
                code; it is even recommended that all information
                which is more or less part of the project will be
                placed under control of the SCM. Think of documents,
                static web-pages, test-scripts, sql-scripts etcetera.
              </t>
              <t><em>Trunk:</em></t>
              <t>
                The trunk represents the main line of development and always
                contains the latest approved changes in development.
              </t>
              <t><em>Branch:</em></t>
              <t>
                A branch is a (temporary) (partial) copy of the tree which is
                created with a specific purpose. Changes made
                in a branch do not appear on the trunk unless they are merged back
                in.
              </t>
              <t><em>Scenario:</em></t>
              <t>
                A scenario is a specific development task. A scenario always
                lives on a branch and is created by the repository managers in the
                repository.
              </t>
              <t><em>Tags:</em></t>
              <t>
                Tags are created in the tree to represent a specific state of
                the tree which might be needed in the future. For example, you
                might tag the tree before you commit a very complex change.
              </t>
              <t><em>Releases:</em></t>
              <t>
                Releases are basically the same as tags, with the exception
                that they are permanent,
                read-only and occur always on a release
                branch. They represent the known state of the tree and contains the
                exact contents for a certain release of the software.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="Development_process_description" title="Development process description">
          
          <t>
            We use a development process we call &quot;scenario
            based development&quot;. In short this means that all
            development takes place in scenarios (which always live on a
            branch, remember?). No development takes place on the trunk. I
            repeat, no development takes place on the trunk ;-)
          </t>
          
          <t>The process consists of two main activities:	  
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Normal scenario based development cycle</t>
              <t>Release scenario</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          
          <section title="Normal scenario based development cycle">
            <t>During normal development the following process is  used:    
              <figure>
                <artwork src="images/rfc0028_2.png"/>
              </figure>
              <eref target="images/rfc0028_1.png">Large picture</eref>
            </t>
            <t>
              To describe the process we&#39;ll use an example of a
              (group of) developer(s) developing a GUI for the
              permission administration in Xaraya.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Let&#39;s start with the normal development cycle. Each
              development task is described in a scenario and assigned
              a name (([perm_gui]). When the developer(s) are ready to
              start developing this scenario a tag is created in the
              trunk ([perm_gui-start]) and a branch for the
              development effort is created ([perm_gui-branch]).
              Developers check out a working copy of this branch and
              start developing.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              After a while the developers feel that the scenario is
              finished and want to have it integrated into the
              project. For this to happen they start with so called
              &quot;catch-up&quot; with the trunk, to merge in other
              approved scenarios. The scenario developers resolve all
              interoperability problems with their scenario and the
              others. The &quot;catch-up&quot; with the trunk might be
              necessary more than once, depending on approval of other
              scenarios.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Let&#39;s assume they have resolved the conflicts and
              want to finish the scenario. They tag their branch with
              the ([perm_gui-end]). At this point, the formal work of
              the developers for this scenario is temporary
              completed. At the tag-point a working installation of
              Xaraya is left for others to review and test for
              approval.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              When tests are finished, the scenario branch can be
              merged back into the trunk and the integrators make sure
              the trunk is updated to a stable state. Just before
              merging a tag ([merge_of-perm_gui]) is created in the
              trunk.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              If tests fail and it is necessary to continue
              development on the scenario the ([perm_gui-end]) tag is
              removed and scenario developers continue their
              work. This cycle is repeated as necessary to ensure that
              the trunk always receives a working system state. It is
              the responsibility of the integrator to leave the trunk
              in a working state after integrating a finished
              scenario.  You see that the process always ends up with
              a working software package, whether it be in a scenario
              branch, the trunk or a release branch. After closing up,
              a working system is left behind at all times. This helps
              the team isolating problems and steering the project on
              feature inclusion instead of time. The project is at all
              times in such a state that a release branch can be
              started.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              During the normal development cycle multiple scenarios
              may be active at any given moment. Obviously the
              &quot;scenario scheme&quot; will be chosen intelligently
              as to minimise the number of conflicts expected. Crucial
              in this respect is communication between different
              scenario developers. Scenario developers are free to
              merge in code from other active scenarios if they see
              good reason to do so. In practice try to avoid this
              situation. It is better to finish one of the scenarios
              first, get it approved, do a catch-up with the trunk and
              then finish the second scenario.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The scenario branch is closed for development after a
              successful merge and may even be removed if
              appropriate.
            </t>
          </section>
          
          <section anchor="Release_scenario" title="Release scenario">
            <t>
              When it is time to construct a release of the software
              the following process is used.
              <figure>
                <artwork src="images/rfc0028_4.png"/>
              </figure>
              <eref target="images/rfc0028_3.png">Large picture</eref>
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The release scenario isn&#39;t that much different from a
              normal development cycle. When we think a release is warranted a
              tag is created in the trunk
              ([release_2_1_2-start]) and a release branch is
              created ([rel-2_1_2]). Note that this is the same
              procedure as any normal development scenario, so far.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The first difference is that in a release branch, the
              development of new features is forbidden. It is a preparation for
              release and not a new development effort.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              Second, no &quot;catch-ups&quot; occurs
              in a release branch. In the ([rel-2_1_2]) branch
              the release people start preparing the code for release, in this
              case release 2.1.2. No merging of the trunk will happen in the
              branch. The test team can check out a copy of the release branch to
              do formal testing. When all is ready, the release manager approves
              the creation of a tag in the branch named
              ([release-2_1_2]). The state of the tree as it
              appears when the tag is created is the
              release. Any change after the tag is there is considered a bug fix
              after release.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The distribution activities operate on the tree tagged with
              the ([rel-2_1_2]) tag. Actual distribution
              activities take place outside the tree, unless they can be done
              partially before the tag is created. In that case they are
              considered as release preparation and need to be tested as
              rigorously as all other features of a release.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              The release branch continues to exist after release, but only
              bug-fixing is done on the branch. At no point in time on a release
              branch is a merge done from any other branch including the
              trunk.
            </t>
            
            <t>Possible support by SCM:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>access privileges to prevent commits in wrong branches.</t>
                <t>
                  automatic regression testing on scenario-branches and
                  trunk Action: warn/cancel commit (depending on how this will be
                  implemented)
                </t>
                <t>
                  implement multiple stage commit (like review/integrate/commit
                  cycle) Action: depending on SCM
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            
            <t>
              From developers it is expected they can dream the above
              process.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Handling_commits" title="Handling commits">
        <t>
          The basic action for changing the repository is a commit of
          one or more changes made to files in the repository. While the
          development process assures that commits are isolated to a
          scenario, some guidelines how to manage your commits are in
          order.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          A commit is forever! Period. That&#39;s why commits must not
          be done without any thinking up front. Even if you decide something
          is wrong and a commit must be rolled back, history shows that it
          has been done. A rollback doesn&#39;t exist; it consists of (at
          least) two commits.
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="Where_to_commit" title="Where to commit">
          <t>
            The development process creates at least three tags for each
            scenario and at least 2 for each release cycle. Make absolutely
            sure you are committing your work to the right branch/tag
            combination. Triple check it! If things are unclear, ask one of the
            repository managers for help. Backup your own stuff. Quadruple
            check your commits if you are working on multiple scenarios at
            once. The SCM tool will support this by setting the appropriate
            permissions on the scenarios you are working on.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="When_to_commit" title="When to commit">
          <t>
            All work is done on a scenario branch and the work you commit
            is limited to that branch. The scenario developers can work out a
            commit policy. A review will take place at the end of the scenario
            before the scenario is merged back into the trunk.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="What_to_commit" title="What to commit">
          <t>
            Honour the scenario scheme! Don&#39;t start working on the
            great new feature in a release branch! If you want to work on that
            feature, that is ok, describe the scenario, get it approved and a
            new scenario will be created from the trunk to work on that great
            new feature.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="How_to_commit" title="How to commit">
          <t>
            Each commit requires a log message. Use this log feature
            intelligently. The SCM tool might enforce you to enter certain
            information: (for example a reference to a test procedure). This
            will be determined as needed. At the time of writing the log
            message is free for you to fill with useful information. Why you
            made a change is a good question to answer in a log message for a
            commit.
          </t>
          
          <t>Possible support by SCM:
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>use templates for the log messages Action: none</t>
              <t>check content of log messages for minimal content. Action: defer commit</t>
              <t>Integration with tracker facility Action: scan log message /
                enter tickets directly in repository (investigate this!)</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      
    </section>
    <!-- Start of part B -->
    
    <section anchor="scmusage" title="Repository tool usage">
      <t>
        The second part of this document describes how we implement the repository
        policy described in the first part with our tool of choice:
        <eref target="http://www.bitkeeper.com">Bitkeeper</eref> [BK].
        Everything in this part is BK specific.
      </t>
      
      <section anchor="Bitkeeper_philosophy" title="BitKeeper philosophy">
        <t>
          If you are used to working with CVS, forget what you know
          about it. BK works different in most respects although the actual
          commands used to work with repositories are very much like their
          CVS counterparts. This part will be easier to understand if you
          don&#39;t translate what is said here to a CVS world.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Probably the biggest thing to get used to is that with BK
          developers are always working with multiple repositories
          which have parent-child relationships with
          each other. Typically you clone a parent repository to a
          child repository, start working for a while and submit a
          changeset to the parent repos. At any given moment you may
          pull changes from a parent to a child or push changes from a
          child to a parent. If you&#39;ve read part A of this RFC you
          will notice that a changeset corresponds in a very intuitive
          way to a scenario and a pull can be seen equivalent to a
          catch-up.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Bitkeeper will keep track of all changesets for you. When you
          try to push a changeset into a parent repository while other
          changeset have been pushed while you were developing it will tell
          you to do a pull first to get synchronised with the parent
          repository. Again, a inherent quality assurance check will be done
          automatically for you, to prevent pushing changes in the wrong
          order.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="The_overall_process" title="The overall process">
        <t>
          In a BK world you typically clone a repository once and it
          will live a very long time from that time onwards. BK provides very
          powerful commands to modify your local repository to synchronise
          it with parent repositories or peer repositories.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Once you have cloned the parent repository you are in total
          control how to proceed. You may work directly in the child
          repository or clone this local repository again and start working
          in the grandchild, thus using the child as your own
          stable repository. It&#39;s up to each
          developer how to organise his/her work.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Bitkeeper is very good at merging changes. In nearly all
          cases it will automatically merge all changes right, even when your
          repository hasn&#39;t been pushed for a long time. (We will dig
          into this some more later on).
        </t>
        
        <t>
          For describing how to use BK in practice we have two
          situations:	
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Developing as a single developer</t>
            <t>Developing with a group of developers</t>
          </list>
          
          Note that even if you work in a group you always work in or
          with your own repository and that if you work alone the description given
          for the group can equally well be applied when you are working alone. The 
          alone and group descriptions are used to clarify the process rather than describe
          your ability to make friends with people.
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="rollingyourown" title="Developing on your own (direct child of Xaraya)">
          <t>The following steps describe in short how you would work when rolling your own repository:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>Clone the Xaraya repository:
                <artwork>
                  bk clone user@xaraya.com:/usr/local/repositories/xaraya/core/stable [local-name]
                </artwork>
                This creates a local repository with its parent set to the xaraya repository 
                at the host xaraya.com identified  with the specified user.
              </t>
              <t>
                Make changes to the code in whatever way you are used to. You
                are automatically working in a scenario now. No further work on
                your part is necessary for this. Note that this is best though of as an
                implicit scenario. It's not named, nor are the tags explicitly created, the 
                process is preserved however, your changes are local to you and not directly
                merged into a central repository.
              </t>
              <t>
                When you are finished with the changes to the scenario you
                can check in your changes. Note that your are checking in your
                changes to your own repository and not to the parent repository you
                originally cloned from.
                <artwork>
                  bk ci 
                  bk commit
                  or 
                  bk citool (GUI)
                </artwork>
                
                BK will ask you for comments on the changes you made. We
                recommend using the citool command first as this will guide you
                through the construction of the changeset. The construction of a
                changeset is finishing up your scenario and making sensible
                comments about it. Within the citool you can commit the changeset.
                Note that this step can be repeated for every scenario you want to
                make. It allows for intuitive division of work into logical steps,
                please make sure that you do. Note also that this can all be done
                off-line on the beach in Florida. No contact is needed with the
                parent repository.
              </t>
              <t>
                After a number of changesets you can decide to
                push your changes to the parent repository, after which they can be
                made visible to other developers.
                <artwork>
                  bk push
                </artwork>
              </t>
              <t>
                If during your development other changesets (new scenarios,
                bug fixes etc.) have been pushed to the xaraya repository BK will
                notify you of that and will force you to do a bk pull first.
                <artwork>
                  bk pull
                </artwork>
                
                Bitkeeper will notify you if there are conflicts and aid you
                in resolving them with a graphical merge tool. After all conflicts
                have been resolved, push your change set to the parent repository
                again. BK will resolve far more conflicts automatically for you
                than CVS does. For example, when files have been moved, CVS will be
                stymified, but bitkeeper will still merge your changes to the right
                place, even if your repository is way behind in directory and file
                reorganisation (can you say NS-module?)
              </t>
              <t>
                For how to add, delete and move files and directories have a
                look at <xref target="commands">the survival guide</xref>.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="working_in_groups" title="Working in groups (grandchildren of xaraya)">
          <t>
            Essentially the same things apply as for working as an
            individual. The main difference is: If you are working within a
            group the parent repository may or may not live on xaraya.com. Say
            developers A,B and C are working on &#39;blocklayout&#39;,
            coordinated by A.
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                A super-scenario (i.e. a new repository)
                &#39;blocklayout&#39; is created on xaraya.com by the
                repository managers (by cloning the xaraya repository in a special
                way)
              </t>
              <t>
                All developers who work on that scenario clone (an extra)
                local repository from xaraya.com:
                <artwork>
                  bk clone user@xaraya.com:/usr/local/repositories/xaraya/core/scenarios/blocklayout
                </artwork>
                Note the different name of the repository
              </t>
              <t>
                The same steps as in
                <xref target="rollingyourown">Developing on your own</xref> apply.
                Of course you should take care to coordinate development somehow.
                Even the best tool cannot replace that. During the group
                development of the super-scenario your parent is the blocklayout
                repository and not the normal xaraya repository.
              </t>
              <t>
                When work on the blocklayout super-scenario is finished, the
                changesets in the special blocklayout repository can be pushed by
                the repository managers at once to the xaraya repository. (which is
                the parent of blocklayout) The same rules apply here for pulling
                and pushing. In the case of a super-scenario, it is sometimes
                (depending on the scenario topic) advisable to let the repository
                managers regularly do a pull from the xaraya repository which the
                developers can pull to their local repository.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>  
          <t>Alternatively:	  
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                Developer A clones the xaraya repository from xaraya.com
                for work on the scenario.\
              </t>
              <t>
                A&#39;s clone becomes the parent repository. B and C clone
                their repository from A&#39;s machine:
                <artwork>
                  bk clone user@A.somewhere:/path/to/repository
                </artwork>
                It is A&#39;s responsibility to ensure a secure setup: A
                has to create ssh accounts for B and C on his machine.
              </t>
              <t>
                The same steps as in <xref target="rollingyourown">Working
                  with your own repository</xref> apply.
              </t>
              <t>
                When work on the scenario is finished, A pushes the
                changesets from his/her repository to the parent: bk
                push.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Please note: BitKeeper supports a star topology. It is
            possible to change parents for your repository. We strongly
            discourage that except for very special occasions, as it tends to
            make development and conflict resolution much harder. It is easy to
            get confused, too. To give an example where re-parenting makes
            sense:
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                A wishes to leave the scenario and work on something else. B
                takes over.
              </t>
              <t>
                All change sets are pushed to A&#39;s repository so that the
                repositories of A,B and C are in sync. (This is technically not
                necessary but it does make life easier.)
              </t>
              <t>
                B sets the parent of his repository to the development
                repository on xaraya.com:
                <artwork>
                  bk parent user@xaraya.com:/usr/local/repositories/xaraya
                </artwork>
              </t>
              <t>C sets the parent of her repository to B:
                <artwork>
                  bk parent user@B.somewhere:/path/to/repository
                </artwork>
              </t>
              <t>B has to create an ssh account for C on that machine.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>Graphically the above works out as follows:</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork src="images/rfc0028_5.png"/>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="BK_survival_guide" title="BK survival guide">
        <t>
          We advise you to print out the BitKeeper reference card. It
          is located in your local installation directory and called
          bk_refcard.ps or bk_refcard.pdf.
        </t>
        <t>
          BitKeeper has an integrated graphical, hyperlinked help tool
          which can be called with the command:
          <artwork>
            bk helptool
          </artwork>
        </t>
        <t>
          A quick help for each command is available with:
          <artwork>
            bk help [command]
          </artwork>
        </t>
        <t>
          What is below as a quick-quick-reference for survival
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="commands" title="Commonly used commands">
          <t>
            <list>
              <t>bk pull: Get updates from the parent repository.</t>
              <t>bk push: Push change sets to the parent repository.</t>
              <t>bk mv [source] [destination]: Move file/dir, recording the move</t>
              <t>bk new [files]: Add file(s) to the repository</t>
              <t>bk rm [files]: Remove file(s) (recoverable)</t>
              <t>bk rmdir [dir]: Remove directory (recoverable)</t>
              <t>bk status: Show status information</t>
              <t>bk grep [pattern] [files]: Search some/all revisions of file(s) for a pattern</t>
              <t>
                bk delta [file]: check in a change to a file to the local repository, 
                to be added to change sets later on. This can (but need not) be used prior to bk citool: it
                allows you to enter descriptions for the changes made to single
                files, in addition to the description the whole change set gets
                anyway.
              </t>
              <t>bk ci: check in the all changes in current dir into the repository</t>
              <t>bk commit: create a changeset from the pending deltas</t>
              <t>bk revtool [filename]: GUI for browsing changesets</t>
              <t>bk difftool [left] [right]: Graphical diff tool</t>
              <t>bk csettool: Graphical change set browser</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            In summary, bk delta and bk ci register changes to files, bk commit groups them into a 
            changeset, bk push publishes those changesets to the parent repository.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Use_cases" title="Use cases">
        <t>
          This section will describe some use cases, sometimes made up,
          sometimes shamelessly copied from other documents on the internet,
          sometimes real author experience. The examples are meant both as
          well, err examples and to show that bitkeeper can solve real
          problems
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="Bug_hunting" title="Bug hunting">
          <t>
            Bug fixing can vary from making a quick fix from totally
            overhauling a set of files to overcome a design flaw.
          </t>
          <t>
            Suppose you found a bug in the session management code.
            Apparently it has been introduced a long time ago (it used to work)
            and you are not sure when it was introduced. You try some versions
            released earlier but you cannot figure out how or what.
          </t>
          <t>
            Using bk revtool session.php you quickly glance over all
            changes made to the file in the past. You find a couple of
            suspicious changesets based on their comments. Playing with the
            revtool narrows it down to a changeset which put a brace in the
            wrong place. You fix the bug in a new changeset, refer in your
            comment to the old changeset and commit your changes.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the bug were introduced in a changeset and was isolated,
            you could have reverted that changeset without touching anything
            else in the repository, only revoking that particular change
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="Creating_a_patch" title="Creating a patch">
          <t>
            While working on the 300% speed increase scenario, you need
            the exception handler code from another developer group. The code
            is in the tree with several other unrelated changes that they
            don&#39;t want to send to anyone.
          </t>
          <t>
            Run bk revtool to find the changeset which introduced the
            exception handler code. Then run 
            <artwork>
              bk export -tpatch -r1.234  &gt; exceptionhandler.diff
            </artwork> 
            If the changeset properly
            grouped the relevant changes this patch can be applied to another
            tree which needs those changes.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="Sharing_changes" title="Sharing changes">
          <t>
            If another group is working on some changes, but they are not
            ready yet to be pushed to the xaraya repository, how do you prevent
            redundant work, so your development can continue?
          </t>
          <t>
            If the other developer (group) has made their repository
            publicly available you don&#39;t even need the help of the other
            group. You create the patch yourself by cloning their repository.
            In most cases different developers are working with the same parent
            (the default xaraya repository) and don&#39;t even need to make a
            patch. They can do a sideways pull from their
            repository to incorporate the changes.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Returning from the beach from florida ;-)">
          <t>
            You have tanned in Florida for three months without internet
            access, because your psychiatrist has told you to do so. He
            didn&#39;t know you were using bitkeeper, so you happily developed
            a great new thing. Returning from Florida you notice that 50
            changesets have been pushed while you were away. First, you think
            about returning to Florida immediately with the 
            <artwork>
              find . -name *.rej
            </artwork> 
            in the back of your head, but you give it a  try anyway.
          </t>
          <t>
            bk pull downloads and applies all changes which you missed,
            regardless how long you have been away. Your repository will never
            get corrupted by bitkeepers data-integrity checking at every step.
            You notices that most of the changes are auto-merged with yours,
            even the complete directory organization you did on the module
            system. The conflicts which come up are easily resolved using the
            3-way merge tool.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="New_functionality" title="New functionality">
          
          <t>
            Developing new functionality is probably the most common
            activity. For this, a child of the normal xaraya repository must be
            cloned in which the changesets can be developed. If the new
            scenario is big enough a central child may be created which may
            function as a parent for the specific scenario itself. (See
            <xref target="working_in_groups">Working in groups</xref>)
          </t>
          
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="Releasing_version_1.2" title="Releasing version 1.2">
          
          <t>
            The PMC decides it&#39;s time to release. From the xaraya
            repository a special clone is made (xaraya-1.2) to which only
            reviewed changesets can be pushed, typically last minute fixes.
            When the release is ready the repository is cloned another time
            (xaraya-1.2-bugfixes) to have a bug-fix repository for the release.
            The xaraya-1.2 repository is closed for all changes, but can be
            pulled for changesets from other repositories. Bugfixing for the
            release occurs in the bug-fixing child xaraya-1.2-bugfixes.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            When it is necessary to release a version 1.21 for example
            the whole process is repeated only with different names. After time
            some repositories will eventually disappear.
          </t>
          
          <t>If you think bitkeeper is disk hungry that way, you are
            right. By using hard-links this can be reduced significantly. If
            you&#39;re in a windows world this is not possible, but that is
            hardly a surprise.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Conclusion" title="Conclusion">
        <t>
          The described process is the backbone of our development
          progress. Before this process was accepted it has been reviewed
          extensively and voted upon by all relevant people. This process
          will not change lightly (although improvements will always be
          looked for).
        </t>	
        
        <t>
          As you may have noticed, bitkeeper is far more advanced than
          CVS. This is meant to make our life easier. The repository managers
          have tried to configure bitkeeper in such a way that it is most
          easy to use, not necessarily the most efficient way. In time we
          will probably change some configuration items of our repository
          management. This RFC (both part A and B will be maintained by the
          repository managers, to always reflect the latest state of
          things.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <!-- Revision history is mandatory -->
    <section title="Revision history">
      <t>2003-07-26: updated paths to reflect new repository organisation, some minor fixes</t>
      <t>2002-11-27: converted private documents to RFC, small corrections and review, no major changes from original</t>
      <t>before 2002-11-27: Private documents</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>
</rfc>
