<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<rfc number="0019" category="info">
	<front>
		<title>Help System</title>
		<author initials="G." surname="Rothfuss" fullname="Gregor J. Rothfuss">
			<organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
			<address>
				<email>rothfuss@abstrakt.ch</email>
				<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date month="May" year="2002"/>
		<!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
		<abstract>
			<t>The contents of this RFC contain the literal content of the old plain
	             text version of RFC-0019
	             </t>
			<t>
		      When time is a less scarcer good, someone might convert the plain text
	            into structured XML so we can benefit from it.
                  </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
	<middle>
		<!-- One content section is mandatory -->
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
			All ?xxx numbers refer to the basic documents in section 7.    
	             </t>
			<t>
			We read through the articles on http://www.postnuke.com, its           
			forum threads, feature requests on sourceforge and the developers mailing list.
	             </t>
			<t>
                    The following RFC is a first summary and contains some solution proposals either compiled from the basic  
                    documents or from general definitions concerning comments systems / forums.
                    </t>
		</section>
		<section title=" List of requirements for the Help System">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
			Use ?DocBook for the help text sources [1] 
			</t>
					<t>
                    Have documenation in multiple formats: HTML, PDF 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    Allow context-sensitive help 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    seamless integration of support websites / irc / phplive 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    full text search 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    user feedback ala MSDN (see rate this page stuff) 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    ml support 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    newbie -> intermediate -> pro docs integrated (cross link to MDG from the installer docs, etc) 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    links to developer.xaraya.com or xCommunity as appropriate 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    integrate feature requests / bug report links 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    have a support script that collects environmental data 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    fetch phpdoc comments for programming manuals 
	             </t>
					<t>
                    synchronize documenation with master copy over xmlrpc
                    </t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Solution proposals - database tables">
			<t>
			It remains to be determined if the contents of the help system are better stored in the file system  
			according to the module directory structure standard, or in a table. There are pros and cons for storing  
			the data in the database. 
			</t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
				Pro
				</t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
				Easier to update the manual
				</t>
							<t>
				Easier to perform full-text searches
				</t>
							<t>
				Easier to translate
				</t>
							<t>
				Easier to reference manual sections (for rating, comments etc)
				</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
				Contra
				</t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
				Harder to provide content in standalone formats: PDF, HTML
				</t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
				Module vars:
				</t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
				Enable online help: Display help links throughout xaraya
				</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Solution proposals - functions">
			<t>
			xarModHelpURL(string module,string type, string topic) [2] provide a way to call into the help system (syntax very rudimentary, not final) 
	             </t>
			<t>
A proposal for a help module 
with articles, categories, ratings and comments almost in place, its time to leverage them for a kick ass online help system. 
	             </t>
			<t>
http://www.drupal.org/node.php?id=284 has some nice ideas. 
	             </t>
			<t>
i suggest we create a help utility module that does the following: 
	             </t>
			<t>
- maintain global / module specific manuals - allow for notes on the manual - provide feedback links to bug trackers - allows for rating of content 
	             </t>
			<t>
this could be achieved by storing manuals as articles in the article module, with a category indicating that it is documentation. each module would add articles on module install. 
	             </t>
			<t>
the categories would look like this: 
	             </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
            			documentation
            			</t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
            			surveys
            			</t>
							<t>
            			downloads
            			</t>
							<t>
            			nascar
            			</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
                    these categories would be set with permissions indicating they can only be seen by administrators. 
	             </t>
			<t>
                    the help utility module would leverage the articles module by calling its API to display articles, call the     
                    comments modules to add coments, same for ratings. additionally, the help module could add a hook for 
                    feedback, sending feedback to the module author (data collected from xarversion.php) 
	             </t>
			<t>
                   A propsal for the help structure 
	            </t>
			<t>
                  Good documentation is essential not only for Xaraya "core" but also for modules. While installing, upgrading,  
                  removing a module should be intuitive, configurig right permissions to get the best from the script or 
                  understandig some tricky points or... require a good documentation. On the other side often good 
                  developers aren't good manuals writers ;-) 
	           </t>
			<t>
                 In my experience the most difficult part in writing manuals is organizing informations and guidelines: when 
                 you have done such a difficult work is only metter of filling in infos... more or less ;-) 
	          </t>
			<t>
                So my idea: what about adding a "modules manual schema" in xardocs so that mods developers have only to 
                fill in the section (and/or of course deleting/adding sects) ? 
	         </t>
			<t>
                  It could be just like a checklist or a summary with only chapter names. We could also add a reference to it 
                  in MDG chapter 7.12 and consider the implication with RFC 19 - Help System. 
	            </t>
			<t>
                    The first schema that comes to my mind is something like this: 
	             </t>
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
                      1. OVERVIEW 
	               </t>
							<t>
                      1.1 Purpose of this module
	               </t>
							<t>
                     1.2 Requirements
	               </t>
							<t>
                     1.3 Authors and credits
	              </t>
							<t>
                    1.4 Obtaining latest version
	             </t>
							<t>
                   1.5 Collaborate and bug catching and fixing
	             </t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
                   2. INSTALLATION 
	             </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
		             2.1 Fresh install
		             </t>
							<t>
		             2.2 Upgrading
		             </t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
                    3. CONFIGURATION 
	             </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
                    3.1 Module configuration
	             </t>
							<t>
                    3.2 Permissions
	             </t>
							<t>
                    3.3 Block configuration
	             </t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
                    4. ADMIN GUIDE 
	             </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
                   4.1 Adding new items
	             </t>
							<t>
                    4.1.1 How to
	             </t>
							<t>
                    4.1.2 Input Labels explained
	             </t>
							<t>
                    4.2 Editing items
	             </t>
							<t>
                   4.3 Delete an item
	             </t>
							<t>
                    4.4 Other options
	             </t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
                   5. USER GUIDE 
	             </t>
					<t>
						<list>
							<t>
                    5.1 View items
	             </t>
							<t>
                    5.2 Display details
	             </t>
							<t>
                    5.3 ....
	             </t>
							<t>
                    5.4 ....
	             </t>
						</list>
					</t>
					<t>
                    6. FAQ 7. TO DO
                    </t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Relationship of the Help System to other areas">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
				Comments System: Used for user comments on the manual
				</t>
					<t>
				Ratings Module: Used for rating of manuals
				</t>
					<t>
				XML-RPC Module: Sync documentation with master copy
				</t>
					<t>
				Tracking Module: Collect usability data (which module is used most etc)
				</t>
					<t>
				Admin module: provide help display functionality
				</t>
					<t>
				phpdoc parser: get API commentary for programmers reference
				</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Code that will need to be rewritten">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
			Help system in admin module
			</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Basic documents for this RFC">
			<t>
			[1] RE: ?xardev DOCUMENTATION: Preview PDF now available. xardev post 04/26/02 gregorrothfuss
     	             </t>
			<t>
                    [2] RE: ?xardev READ: New Block Stuff &amp; Revamp xardev post 05/13/02 Veres Ferenc
                   </t>
		</section>
		<section title="Tools that need to be created from scratch">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>
			Docbook parser: We need to figure out a way to keep the docbook sources synced with the help system. 
			</t>
					<t>
                    phpdoc parser: Is there a php-based phpdoc parser available? Check with PEAR.
                    </t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Retractions">
			<t>
			We list features that were considered but rejected for this API below.
                    </t>
		</section>
		<section title="Changelog">
			<t>
			0.1 (May 13, 2002) gregorrothfuss
	             </t>
			<t>
                     Initial Version
	             </t>
			<t>
                    0.2 (July 9, 2002) gregorrothfuss
	             </t>
			<t>
                    Module Schema from Stefano Garubi added
	             </t>
			<t>
                    Help System implementation notes added
                    </t>
		</section>
	</middle>
</rfc>
