<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc number="0001" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="xarCommunity">Xaraya Community Enhancements (aka xarCommunity)</title>
    <author initials="DAD" surname="Daulton" fullname="Douglas">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
				<email>apakuni@xaraya.com</email>
				<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2002"/>
    
    <!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>The contents of this RFC contain the literal content of the old plain
				text version of RFC-0001</t>
      <t>When time is a less scarcer good, someone might convert the plain text
				into structured XML so we can benefit from it.
      </t>
    </abstract>
		<note title="Note">
			<t>This RFC will be replaced by RFC0031 (xDeveloper Community Tools)</t>
		</note>
  </front>
  
  <!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
    <!-- One content section is mandatory -->
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
				The main objective of this project is to rethink, redesign and
				redeploy support.xaraya.com.  This RFC will outline a variety
				of proposed changes to the functionality, use and therefore
				underlying architecture of support.xaraya.com.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Known Issues ">
			<t>General Usability</t>
			<t>
				<list style="numbers">
					<t>Confused links down the sidebars</t>
					<t>Too many sites to go to without explanations of what they are
						(All the Xaraya sites plus all the Sourceforge areas)</t>
					<t>Scattered support services from Sourceforge to support.xaraya.com
						to ice-interactive.com to xaraya.com as well as docs, themes,
						modules, and blocks.</t>
					<t>Inconsistent theme = inconsistent "mind share"</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Xaraya Theme</t>
			<t>
				<list style="numbers">
					<t>The links at the top of each site do not always go anywhere.</t>
					<t>The switching graphic takes you to a different place depending
						upon what site you are at.</t>
					<t>The sites all look the same (not true)</t>
					<t>The sites have different navigation</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Proposed Solution">
			<t>Proposed Platform</t>
			<list style="numbers">
				<t>Xaraya:      Rogue .703+</t>
				<t>Forum:       PostBoard 3.0  (see 3C4. Forums - Architechture)</t>
				<t>Live Support:  ?PhpLive (www.livepeople.info/support/web/Xaraya)</t>
				<t>IM/IRC:        Trillian (client - www.trillian.cc) / Jabber (server - www.jabber.com)</t>
			</list>
<artwork>
stratagem
I think the relaunch should be via .71

stratagem
The forum used should be able to evolve to a point where
all views are available to the users. Be it the dreaded threaded views
or the current postboard views.

stratagem
I'm still not sold on PHPLive - but will see where this goes.

stratagem
I think a site specific IM tool would be better than third
party IM proggies/networks.

:Wolf-
Can't cover the existing 3 areas of support effectively. And
now we want to add IM and live support?

:jotajota
Different ways to cover support lead to different people
giving support. I can't be in IRC while in working hours but I can
surely be on IM

:Karateka
Different needs need to be covered by different
methods. PHP Live should not be used to replace the current IRC, but
it could be well used as a distributor of people seeking help to
streamline them into whatever suits them best. One example: even
sending someone who would have ended up on irc with a question that
could be easily answered in the docs could be considered an act of
live support.

:Karateka
PHP Live should be used as the primary layer that works on
top of the real support structure and it should be available to
everyone, since it needs (just like the boards) no additional software
like Java or an IRC client.

:Karateka
The usage of PHP Live is an incredible useful method to
enhance the usability of the website itself. Thus, in the long run,
PHP Live! usage might actually decrease, as the website becomes more
self-explanatory (if we listen to the feedback we get).

:Isaac
The issue of irc not being addressed while at work is near
being solved though the use of a special proxy system that will run
acorss port 80 just like http. Once myself and Harry work the final
details out we should be installing and testing just such a system
out.

:Isaac
The use of one on one tools while great ofr nich industries
such as online support while buying products, does not lend itself tyo
an open community structure such as the one that has allready been
established here with Xaraya. one on one relies very heavily on the
support of highly trained and skilled people who can answer everything
trwon at them while with Xaraya those people are not willing to lend
themselfs to helping users while wrting code for those same users next
edition of the software. Furhter more as this system was tested once
before it failed before making it out of the gate because none of the
staff wanted to sit alone in a html window just waiting for users to
show up. If this application was focused just on supporting say the
Documentation site and the ability to help users find documents It
might prove to be usefull. If you can find staff to man it in the long
run.

:Karateka
This system was never tested on xaraya.com before. You are
talking about quite a different system and that particular system
wasn't really tested. Further on, with this system, you don't need to
just sit and wait.

:Isaac
As I have stated numerous times in the past, After 7 years of
lending myself to tech support in many different areas for many
different systems a community type system that relies on not only
staff supporting users but Users supporting users in an open support
envirnment as compared to that of a closed one to one environment such
as a "live support program" Is the generally best method. with
thousands of small to medium sized IRC networks and around 200 large
irc network alive and well in the world wide web and several Million
people using these system the system is tested. If you want some
examples of support systems take a look at irc.openprojects.net or go
a step further and goto efnet.net irc.galaxy.net or irc.dal.net and
load up their 10,000 plus channels and find some support rooms that
are active. Take phplive or some other "live support program" and
apply it speciicly to http://docs.xaraya.com and use it specificly for
documentation support as it is good for very focused support of single
topics such as documentation. In the proccess make very very sure you
dont confuse the general public with several different "live support
systems" Most importantly make sure that the system used is GPL or GNU
and not commercial in nature.

:Karateka
1-1 systems such a Human Click got about 1 Million websites
to use it in one year. Anyway, PHP Live! is an extra layer for
support. It's the easiest and fastest method for users to seek
support, they don't need java in their browser or start up their irc
client. It works with the click of a mouse. By default, I am inviting
users to join the irc-chat at the end of each chat session. I am not
trying to take anyone away his favourite toy. I *do* know that some
people more or less disapprove it without even looking at it. That's
ok for me. I am still hanging out on irc and answer questions there
and talk with them and help them solve problems. As I said, it could
replace some irc-stuff, but at the same time I say a directly and fast
established 1-1 chat does not suit all support needs and there are
many situations where irc-channel-based support just fits better. I
have no understanding for closed-mindedness though. PHP Live! is a
tool, it's not a general problem solver, just as irc isn't. It is a
new tool. So, for some areas it's a matter of experimenting with it,
however, for others, it has proven already that it does the job in an
excellent way. Those people I helped so far were saying that this tool
is incredibly cool. Some people said they'd need to tell their friends
about Xaraya first before they'd join the irc. If it's not in our goal
to have such excited minds, then I am sorry. And yes, sorry again, but
I couldn't help myself, but I added myself not only to the support
department, but also to the documentation department and the marketing
department to answers calls there and got nice results.
B. Xaraya Theme
1. Theme issues described above need to be resolved ASAP.
2. Core Xaraya theme must be made extensibile in a manner that allows
Site Managers to customize aspects of thier site/subdomain so it is
clearly part of the Xaraya family yet has retain its own personality.
3. To be an "official" Xaraya site, it must run the current approved
Xaraya Family theme.

:Wolf-
And, since the release of the 'Xaraya
family theme' has been regulated to one server, it would follow that
ALL 'official' sites need to be hosted on said server.

:Grape
Docs will keep it's own theme and will be introducing a more documentation
oriented theme in the future. The 'Xaraya Family Theme' will not be
used.

:stratagem
I think each site should have a unique look. I
believe that some users get confused without knowing which site they
are on exactly.

			</artwork>
		</section>

		<section title="Forums">
			<t>
				<list style="numbers">
						<t>Forums - Overview All forums to sit on a
						common table set with specific forum views displayed at each subdomain
						or sister site.  This allows </t>
					<t>Forums - Subdomains &amp;Topics
				www.xaraya.com (Home) Feature Requests 
				- Core Functionality (for non	devs) 
				Info Requests 
				- Materials used to explain/market Xaraya
				Developer Market 
				- Promote folks who can implement and modify Xaraya
			</t>
<t>
<artwork>
:gregorrothfuss
while i like the idea to have a directory of Xaraya
implementors, i think a forum is a very bad fit for that. a directory
with a few required fields would be far better suited 
-support.xaraya.com 
- Installation(win) Installation for Wintel	environments 
- Installation(lin) Installation of Linux/Unix environments 
- General Support 
- Core Functionality (for non devs) Bug
- Reports 
- Core Functionality (for non devs)  

:gregorrothfuss   
this needs to be pondered further. as long as we have no better alternative
than the SourceForge Trackers, we should stick with them. As it
stands, nobody bothers to resubmit bugs that are marooned on the
forums.   

:Rabbitt
there's a good idea gregor -- a module that acts
as a forum of sorts and takes bug requests and submits them to
sourceforge automatically... hmmm...  Core Modules - Subforums
addressing issues and hacks for any module distributed as part of the
core developer.xaraya.com (new ???)  Developer (Core) - Core
Functionality (for devs only) Developer (Markets) - Develop
"Marketing/Sales" materials Core Modules - Subforums addressing issues
and hacks for any module distributed as part of the core
 
:gregorrothfuss
this may be a good home for the new mailing lists
that are being set up on the Xaraya server. provide web-based search
facilities etc. It would be an advantage if interested parties could
follow the lists from there, but would need an account to post. 

:Grape   
would be an excelent home for the mailing lists. 
themes.xaraya.com Requests (Core) - Core Theme System Features Request 
(Themes) - Specific theme mods or new themes 
Public Support 
- Theme Installation &amp; Mod (for non-devs) 
Developer Support 
- Theme Installation &amp; Mod (for devs only) 
Core Modules 
- Subforums for individual themes &amp; developers mods.xaraya.com 
Requests (Core) - Core Module System Features Request (Mods)
 - Specific module hacks
mods or new mods Public Support 
- Mod Installation &amp; Mod (for
non-devs) Developer Support 
- Mod Installation &amp; Mod (for devs
only) Core Modules
 - Subforums for individual modules &amp; module
development crews blocks.xaraya.com Requests (Core) 
- Core Block
System Features Request (Blocks)
 - Specific theme mods or new themes
Public Support
 - Block Installation &amp; Mod (for non-devs) Developer
Support 
- Block Installation &amp; Mod (for devs only) Core Modules -
Subforums for individual blocks &amp; developers 

3. Forums -
Architecture a. Port PostBoard to use Comments API as its core.
Leverages core functionality and PB built from ground up as Xaraya
Mod.   

:Wolf-   
POSTBOARD?? If we are going to the trouble of porting
and rewriting, there why not just emulate some of the better forums
out there?   Grape   similarly, one might appreciate the aesthetics of
postboard prior to a full-on installation of it   mrherald   Perhaps
we should discuss what is so great about each forum in detail at, I
don't know, how about here: WhatForum  
b. Common tableset and
architecture will allow for ease of management of threads among
appropriate forum by Moderators 
c. Thread movement/deletion should
fire e-mail to author with new location (URL) or reason for deletion
d. Forum architecture should allow for moving thread into docs dev
queue for conversion to FAQ or other doc.   

:Wolf-   
This item is
ambiguous. Clarification is needed.   

:jotajota   

e. Forum threads
should be subscribible by email and (ideally) answerable by email too 

D. Live Support  
:Grape   
what are you talking about?  
a. Enables
solutions to be pushed from forums, docs and other sources  
:Grape   
i can push a broom and it might be a solution, but what solutions do you
intend to push?  
b. Enables pushing support chat logs to docs dev
queue, forums and/or bug tracker 

E. FAQs &amp; Documentation
a. Document Development Forum is fed by Forums, Bug Tracker, an Live
Support 

:Wolf-  
This is the first mention of the 'Document Development Forum'
It has not been defined anywhere else.   Grape   what is this? i think
a document development forum would be pointless and would rather have
people simply email requests.   mrherald   A good reason for a docs
forum would be to get everyone communicating someplace other than the
wiki and e-mail. This can be used to openly discuss issues such as
what pages need work and who knows about what. It is much better than
just assuming that everyone knows what is going on in the wiki and is
more open than plain e-mails. It should increase efficiency and
effectiveness  F. IM &amp; IRC a. becomes general chat channel for the
community  gregorrothfuss   IM may be a useful way to escalate
issues. I dont want to idle in the support rooms all the time when i
am working on something, but I would not mind if a select group of
people could IM me with urgent questions. \
						</artwork>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
	
		</section>

		<section title="Requirements ">
			<t>
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Database Tables: TBD </t>
					<t>Code Base
						<list style="numbers">
							<t>Rewrites</t>
							<t>New Code </t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Issue Resolution">
			<section title="Active issues">
				<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>Multilingual Support - 
							The current support architecture is focussing on english
							support. The Xaraya support infrastructure needs to scale out to third
							party sites to provide multilangual support. The formation of a
							Multilingual Support Council is proposed.
							<artwork>
:jotajota   
Why use third
party sites instead of people speaking different languages giving
support in the same place? Not only is that less confusing but it also
allows for more supporters online on the site giving sinergy (what
supporter A doesn't know can be asked to B by the supporter himself)
and more opportunities to get help (I preffer to get help on my mother
tgongue but I could get it in French if I had to...)   
								
:gregorrothfuss 
People want to have local communities, and centralizising everything
on one site is not going to happen. we may as well take this into
account, and try to come to an understanding with 3rd party sites. 
						
:mrherald   How about both? If an outside site wishes to provide
support (we cannot stop them from doing it and we cannot force them to
use what we have here) let them offer support, but be sure to link to
it and have them link back to our support area. Support forums on the
Xaraya family of sites should not be the only ones available to the
user, but in the absence of other support it should be provided here.
							</artwork>
						</t>
						<t>Parking Lot 1. Home for issues which will not be addressed in this
							revision/release</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section title="Document Changelog">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>1.0 (February 2, 2002) Douglas A. Daulton (aka Apakuni)</t>
					<t>Initial Version 1.1 (February 6 2002) Gregor J. Rothfuss Multilingual Support Council added</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Credits &amp; Supporting Documents">
			<t>
				<list>
					<t>Bob Brown (MrHerald / apt419)</t>
					<t>E-mail: Issues and Concerns Sascha Endlicher (karateka)</t>
					<t>E-mail: Live Support Gregor J. Rothfuss (gregor): </t>
					<t>IRC Log: Support Discussion Carl P. Corliss (rabbitt): </t>
					<t>IRC Log: Support Discussion</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
</rfc>

