<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc='yes'?>

<rfc number="0027" category="bcp">
  <!-- number: Fill in the number for the RFC -->
  <!-- obsoletes: Comma separated list of RFC numbers which this one obsoletes -->
  <!-- category: std=standard, bcp=best common practice, info=info, exp=experimental, historic=historic -->

  <!-- Front matter is used for identification of author and organization -->
  <front>
    <title>EU Data Protection Compliant Users Module</title>
    <author initials="ML" surname="Luetolf" fullname="Marc Luetolf">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
	<email>mfl@netspan.ch</email>
	<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2002"/>
    
    <!-- Initiating team for this RFC -->
    <workgroup>Project Management Committee</workgroup>

    <!-- List keywords for the RFC here -->
    <keyword>rfc</keyword>
    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This RFC is the template for writing RFCs in XML or plain text for the 
	Xaraya project.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
    <!-- Introduction is mandatory -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Every RFC contains at least the following sections:
	<list style="bullet">
	  <t>Introduction</t>
	  <t>at least one content section</t>
	  <t>Revision History</t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- One content section is mandatory -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
This document proposes certain changes to the Xaraya source code to make the
users module compliant with the EU directive on data protection. This does
not imply that Xaraya sites without these changes cannot comply with the
directive. The changes proposed simply make it easier to do so, primarily by
giving the users enhanced functionality to manage personal data they submit.
This makes life easier for the site administrator, who otherwise has the
onus to comply with user requests concerning personal data.

The directive is quite complex and, depending on the type and purpose of the
data collected, can be quite onerous. The changes proposed in this document
purport to take into account common situations encountered by most
organizations that will run Xaraya. With this in mind, what follows is a
simplified summary of the major points of the directive that will be used to
define the requirements of a compliant users module.

For special situations the directive in its entirety may need to be taken
into account. The directive can be found here:
http://www.privacy.org/pi/intl_orgs/ec/final_EU_Data_Protection.html
</t>
</section>

    <section title="Implications of the Directive">
      <t>
For the purpose at hand the directive distinguishes between the following
subjects (we take subject to mean a natural or legal person):

§         Data Subject: the natural person whose personal data is the object
of the directive.

§         Controller: the subject that determines the purposes and means of
the processing of personal data.

§         Processor: the subject that processes personal data on behalf of
the controller.

§         Recipient: the subject to whom data are disclosed.

The directive applies to any and all processing of personal data, with some
exceptions. Exempted are a number of national or EU institutions themselves
(!), and strictly personal or household uses of personal data.

While we can make a module EU compliant, this does not necessarily mean that
any use of the module is necessarily legal in all cases. National
legislation may supercede the directive. What may be allowed by the
directive, e.g. processing of personal data "revealing racial or ethnic
origin, political opinions, religious or philosophical beliefs, trade-union
membership" with the user's consent, may be prohibited by national law. Such
considerations are excluded from this document.

Also excluded from this discussion is the obligation that a site may or may
not have to notify a supervisory authority as described by the directive.
[section IX]

The directive distinguishes between data collected from the user and data
about the user collected from other sources. For our purpose only the former
is relevant, i.e. data submitted by users registering on a site.
</t>
</section>


    <section title="Main Points">
      <t>
1.        The user must give his/her unambiguous consent to the processing
of his/her personal data.

2.       The user must be told to what end the data will be used.

3.       The user must be told whether submitting the data is mandatory or
not, and the consequences of submitting or not submitting the data.

4.       The user must be told who the recipients of the data will be.

5.       The user must have the right to access and modify the data.

6.       The user has the right to object at any time to the processing of
the data. Accordingly "Where there is a justified objection, the processing
instigated by the controller may no longer involve those data".
</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Revision history is mandatory -->
    <section title="Revision history">
      <t>Put a summary of the major revisions to this document in here</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!-- Back matter is used for references and appendices which come after the references -->
  <back>
    <references title="Reference title">
      <!-- Fill in references as needed -->
      <reference>
	<front>
	  <title>Reference title</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>Organization</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="2002"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <!-- Repeat the aboven block if more references are needed -->
    </references>
    
    <!-- Any section after this will become an appendix -->
    <section title="Example appendix">
      <t>Any section which is present after the references will become an appendix</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
