<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc number="0002" category="info">
  <front>
    <title>Comments API</title>
    <author initials="C." surname="Corliss" fullname="Carl P. Corliss">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
	<email>besfred@gmx.net</email>
	<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2002"/>
    
    <!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This RFC contains a proposal for the implementation of a comments API.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	All ?xxx numbers refer to the basic documents in section 7.
	We read through the articles on http://www.postnuke.com, its forum
	threads, feature requests on sourceforge and the developers mailing
	list.
	The following RFC is a first summary and contains some solution
	proposals either compiled from the basic documents or from general
	definitions concerning comments systems / forums.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="List of requirements for the Comments API">
      <t>
	The main objective of this API is to provide a small, yet flexible
	codebase for adding comment functionality to modules. This API will
	not replace a full-blown forum, but will rather aim to implement
	core functionality. A forum could conceivably make use of this API
	to extend on it and provide advanced functionality. It might be
	feasible to make parts of this API pluggable to allow for the
	addition of more rendering types for instance.<xref target="refs.8"/>
	Following is a list of requirements broadly grouped into
	categories.
	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>Backend</t>
	  <t>Keep the codebase small to make maintenance easier</t>
	  <t>Separate display and core functionality code</t>
	  <t>The API should be completely transparent for the modules, and
	    vice versa. There should be no dependencies between a module
	    and the API.</t>
	  <t>Provide gateway functions to
	    <list>
	      <t>Email</t>
	      <t>NNTP</t>
	    </list>
	    Authors of posts can opt to receive replies to their posts via
	    email. Maybe allow others to subscribe to a thread.
	    Note that this is closely related to a generic Notification API.
	    See section 5 for more information
	  </t>
	  <t>Make comments url-addressable <xref target="refs.5"/>. This allows to refer to
	    individual comments with hyperlinks.</t>
	  <t>Provide several search &amp; summary functions, like the date of the
	    last comment for a given discussion <xref target="refs.11"/>.</t>
	  <t>Moderation</t>
	  <t>Rely on permissons system for moderation access <xref target="refs.2"/></t>
	  <t>Implement a bot posting prevention system <xref target="refs.4"/>, <xref target="refs.15"/></t>
	  <t>Allow the deletion of subcomments. <xref target="refs.6"/> This raises a lot
	    of questions what should happen to child comments if a
	    parent comment is deleted.</t>
	  <t>Rendering</t>
	  <t>Provide pluggable rendering modules, maybe from other forums <xref target="refs.3"/>
	    The comments API will ship with a few basic rendering modules such
	    as threaded and flat views.</t>
	  <t>Implement pagination so that long lists of comments do not
	    overwhelm the layout.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution proposals - database tables">
      <t>This is just one proposal for a table structure, the one chosen
	by the XOOPS project can be found in [21].</t>
      <section title="Table Comment">
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    // as the comment repository
	    commentid        unique long integer value
	    modname          holds a reference to the module (see section 5g)
	    hookid           references an item in the module, semantics are
	                     defined by the module.
	    author           foreign key to the users table
	    title            the title of the comment
	    comment          the comment, maximum size to be determined
	    comdate          the date of the comment as UTC timestamp
	    hostname         records the hostname of the poster
	    lineage          the family tree upto and including the current comment
	  </artwork>
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution proposals - functions">
      <t>This is just one proposal for an implementation, the one chosen
	by the XOOPS project can be found in [20].</t>
      
      <section title="Backend Code">
	<t>The Backend API gives the developer a means in which s/he can
	  seamlessly interact with the database. All database interaction
	  is completely handled by the following routines.
	  List of Functions:
	  <artwork>
	  xarComments_Get(modname, hookid, CommentId=0, depth=-1, sort='ASC')
	  xarComments_Add(modname, hookid, ParentId, author, title, comment, hostname)
	  xarComments_Delete(CommentId, delkids=true)
	  xarComments_Modify(CommentId, title, comment) {
	  xarComment_Search(searchstring [,module] [,hook]);
	  xarComment_Stats([module, [hook]]);
	  xarComments_MoveThread(AttachToId, CommentId, IncludeParent=true);
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>Details of Functions:</t>
	<t>
	  In these functions you will notice the parameter 'hook' -- this
	  parameter is the itemid of the module in question (ie., the
	  'hook' into the module).
	</t>
	<t>Common Function Parameters:</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    $module:  string (or integer), module name or possibly
	              the registered id of the module.
	    $hook:    integer, itemid of the module. (ie., for
                      News module it would be the storyid)
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>Common Return:</t>
	<t>
	  The initial proposal is to have a named array for the comments,
	  the structure of the array is shown below:</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	  commentarray(
	    "CommentId" =&gt; 423,
	    "author" =&gt; "Joey Butta",       // name of the author
	    "title" =&gt; "Booga Booga",       // title of the comment
	    "date" =&gt; "(timestamp)",        // date the comment was made
	    "comment" =&gt; "Nothing to say.", // the comment itself.
	    "depth" =&gt; "3",                 // level depth in the parent/child tree
	    "hostname" =&gt; "192.168.1.9",    // hostname or ip of the author
	    "lineage" =&gt; "23:64:234:322:328:423", // "family tree" for this comment
	    "haskids" =&gt; false
          );
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>Function Descriptions:</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentGet
	    RETURN: commentarray OR array of commentarrays
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module:     see above;
			$hook:       see above;
                        $sort:       string ("ASC" or "DESC")
			$commentid:  integer (0 or greater)
			$depth:	     integer (-1, 0 or &gt;0)
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Acquires comments based on the module/hook and the comment id. The depth
	  parameter allows us to only acquire comments to (n) levels deep. A value of 0
	  would acquire the sole comment specified by the comment id and -1 would
	  acquire all comments down to the deepest level. If both the commentid and the
	  level are ommitted from the function call (ie., xarCommentGet('News','1') ),
	  all comments for the given module/hook are retrieved.  To retrieve a single
	  comment the call would be:  xarCommentGet('News',1,5,0) 1 being the storyid,
	  5 being the commentid, and 0 telling the function to only return that one
	  comment. If sort is specified, the top most parents are sorted by date in the
	  direction specified, otherwise they are sorted in ascending order by date.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentGetKids
	    RETURN: commentarray OR array of commentarrays
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module:	 see above;
			$hook:	 see above;
			$parent:	 integer (1 or greater)
			$level:	 integer (0 or greater)
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Acquires a list of comments based on a particular thread. This is similiar to
	  the current ?DisplayKids(...) function. The level parameter keeps track of how
	  many levels deep in the the parent/child tree we are.  This function is
	  intended to be nested and will be utilized in the function xarCommentGet(...)
	  as a means of acquiring comments down to a particular depth.  If there are
	  no children for the particular comment, an empty array is returned.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentAdd
	    RETURN: bool (True or False)
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module: see above;
			$hook:	   see above;
			$commentarray: named array
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Adds a Comment to the database based on the module/hook and returns
	  a true or false on success. The commentarray contains the actual comment.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentDel
	    RETURN: bool (True or False)
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module: see above;
			$hook:	 see above;
			$commentid:	 integer (0 or greater)
	    </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Deletes comment(s) from the database. If the comment has children and
	  boolchildren is false, all first level children's parent ids are reset to the
	  grandparent's id or zero if the parent is a toplevel comment. Note: this does
	  not affect the relationship between the first level children and any children
	  they might have. Otherwise, if boolchildren is set to true, the comment and
	  =all= it's children are deleted from the database.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentModify
	    RETURN: bool (True or False)
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module: see above;
			$hook:	   see above;
			$commentid:	   integer (0 or greater)
			$commentarray: named array
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Modifies a comment in the database based on the module/hook/commentid. The
	  commentarray contains the actual comment.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentSearch
	    RETURN: commentarray OR array of commentarrays
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module: see above;
			$hook:	   see above;
			$searchstring: string
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Returns a comment or array of comments based on the search string.  If the
	  module/hook is given, it searches only the specific module/hook for the
	  searchstring. If the module is given and not the hook, it searchs for all
	  comments matching the searchstring for the given module only, likewise if
	  the hook is given without the module.  If both the module/hook are not
	  given, it returns ALL comments. Note The comment array structure
	  returned by this function is slightly different as it would include the
	  module/hook as key elements.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentNext
	    RETURN: commentarray
	    PARAMETERS:
	                $commentarray: named array
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Returns the next comment in the comments array - this function and it's
	  counterpart, xarCommentPrev(...) are helper functions similar in concept to
	  adodb's ?MoveNext() function. Each time this function is called, the array
	  pointer is moved ahead one comment traversing all branches (ie., children) of
	  the tree one at a time until the end is reached (ie., the last comment).
	</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>	  
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentNext
	    RETURN: commentarray
	    PARAMETERS:
			$commentarray: named array
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>returns the previous comment in the comments array.</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentStats
	    RETURN: statsarray
	    PARAMETERS:
			$module: see above;
			$hook:	 see above;
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Returns an array with last comment, date of last comment, # of comments etc
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Rendering Code">
	<t>Rendering will be done through the use of a class factory. This
	  allows for the implemenation of different renderers without changing
	  the API. Each renderer has the exact same methods.</t>
	<t>List of Functions</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	  xarCommentRenderFactory($type) &lt;-- Constructor
	  Class Renderer
	  Renderer() &lt;-- Constructor
	  xarCommentDraw($commentarray, $optionsarray)
	  xarCommentDrawInput()
	    xarCommentDrawEdit($commentid)
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>Details of Functions</t>
	<t>Common Function Parameters</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	  $commentarray   This array holds the comments to be drawn. See
                          above for its structure.
          $optionsarray   This array holds the renderer-specific options
                          in key-&gt;value form.
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>Common Return</t>
	<t>All functions in the rendering code return XHTML in a variable.</t>
	<t>Function Descriptions</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentRenderFactory
	    RETURN: renderer class
	    PARAMETERS:
			$type: the name of the renderer to use.
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>returns the chosen renderer class.</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentDraw
	    RETURN: XHTML
	    PARAMETERS:
			$commentarray: named array.
                        $optionsarray: named array.
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>returns the comments specfied rendered in XHTML.</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentDrawInput
	    RETURN: XHTML
	    PARAMETERS:
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>returns the comment input form rendered in XHTML.</t>
	<t>
	  <artwork>
	    FUNCTION: xarCommentDrawInput
	    RETURN: XHTML
	    PARAMETERS:
			$commentid: id of the comment to edit.
	  </artwork>
	</t>
	<t>returns the comment edit form for the specified
	  comment rendered in XHTML
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Relationship of the API to other areas">
      <t>Textsanitizer</t>
      <t>
	The comments should go through a foul language filter before
	being posted. That filter should not be part of the comments system
	though. Also, support for various text encoding systems (HTML, bbcode,
	wikicode) will be provided by the Textsanitizer.
      </t>
      <t>Permissions</t>
      <t>
	The Comments API will make extensive use of the Permissions system to
	implement access control and the display of elements <xref target="refs.7"/>. The option
	to turn comments on or off for a given module <xref target="refs.10"/> will also be
	handled by the Permissions system. It remains to be seen whether
	extensive use of the Permissions system will lead to an overload
	within that system.
      </t>
      <t>Categories</t>
      <t>
	It might be beneficial to attach metadata to comments via the
	Categories system.
      </t>
      <t>Users</t>
      <t>What should happen with orphaned content? <xref target="refs.12"/></t>
      <t>Hooks to external editors</t>
      <t>
	Spell checkers <xref target="refs.14"/> and WYSIWYG editors will be hooked in via the
	standard methods.
      </t>
      <t>Notification systems</t>
      <t>
	Several aspects of the Comments API would benefit from plugging into a
	Notification system. This would regularly update subscribed parties on
	the status of comments.
      </t>
      <t>Module system</t>
      <t>
	The Comments API needs a reliable way to refer to modules. Currently
	this issue remains unresolved. <xref target="refs.17"/>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Code that will need to be rewritten">
      <t>
	<artwork>
	  /modules/Downloads
	  /modules/News
	  /modules/NS-Comments
	  /modules/Polls
	  /modules/Reviews
	  /modules/Search
	  /modules/Sections
	  /modules/Top_List
	  /modules/Topics
	  /modules/Web_Links
	  and some blocks
	</artwork>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Tools that need to be written from scratch">
      <t>A helper function to determine the real IP address of a user.
	This function can make use of the Forwarded-for header. <xref target="refs.18"/></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Current Issues">
      <t>Current proposal for retrieving comments from the database is
	very expensive  Possible fix: encode the parent/child hierarchy
	in the key. <xref target="refs.19"/>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Retractions">
      <t>We list features that were considered but rejected for this API below.
	<list style="numbers">
	    <t>Let anonymous users specify a name <xref target="refs.13"/>
	    The reasoning was that we do not want to establish a secondary
	    way of registering with Postnuke, an account light of sorts.
	    Experience with live sites has shown that appending the name to
	    a post works well.</t>
	  <t>Implement core functionality for a moderation system.
	    There are lots of different ways to implement moderation
	    systems: Karma (ala slashdot.org), Network of Trust
	    (ala advogato.org) <xref target="refs.9"/>. Provide a simple field to
	    record the score of a comment regardless of the means
	    by which this score was calculated.
	    ?Not implemented due to upcoming Rating System RFC/API
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Changelog">
      <t>
	<artwork>
	  4.1 (January 7, 2002) modified by Carl P. Corliss (aka Rabbitt)
	  Added 'haskids' field to db table scheme
	  Added function xarCommentSearch to Section 4a (Function List and Description)
	  Modified function xarCommentGet -- added parameter 'sort'
	  4.0 (January 6, 2002) modified by Gregor J. Rothfuss
	  Section 4b extended.
	  Formatting cleanups.
	  3.5 (January 6, 2002) modified by Carl P. Corliss (aka Rabbitt)
	  Sections 4a, 4b &amp; 9 added.
	  #2 of Section 10:Retractions moved from Section 5:Moderation.
	  'rating' removed from comment table layout.
	  3.0 (January 4, 2002) modified by Gregor J. Rothfuss
	  Section 8 added.
	  2.0 (January 4, 2002) modified by Gregor J. Rothfuss
	  Database schema added.
	  Section 5g added.
	  1.0 (January 3, 2002)
	  Initial Version
	</artwork>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <reference anchor="refs.1">
	<front>
	  <title>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/8069</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>jstarkweather</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.2">
	<front>
	  <title> http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/5845</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>Jim McDonald</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.3">
	<front>
	  <title> http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/5791</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization> chv, hzink</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.4">
	<front>
	  <title>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/5465</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>electric monk</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.5">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=485710&amp;group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>goosepro</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.6">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=456931&amp;group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.7">
	<front>
	  <title> http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=477620&amp;group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.8">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=484304&amp;group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.9">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=440629</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.10">
	<front>
	  <title> http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=442294</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.11">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=442947</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.12">
	<front>
	  <title> http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=445490</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.13">
	<front>
	  <title>http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=455164</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.14">
	<front>
	  <title> http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=460677</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.15">
	<front>
	  <title> http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=27927&amp;atid=392231&amp;func=detail&amp;aid=477934</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.16">
	<front>
	  <title>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/5718</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.17">
	<front>
	  <title>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/pndev/message/8363</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.18">
	<front>
	  <title> http://www.cgsa.net/php/identifierShow.php</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="refs.19">
	<front>
	  <title>http://groups.yahoo.com/group/PN-Data/message/28</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>unknown</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="unknown"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
