<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc='yes'?>

<rfc number="0032" category="info">
	<front>
		<title>Xaraya Usability Recommendations</title>
		<author initials="D." surname="Daulton" fullname="Douglas Daulton">
			<organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
			<address>
				<email>apakuni@xaraya.com</email>
				<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="D." surname="Vogel" fullname="Drew Vogel">
			<organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
			<address>
				<email>drew@drewvogel.com</email>
				<uri>http://www.drewvogel.com</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		
		<date month="February" year="2003"/>	
		
		<!-- Initiating team for this RFC -->
		<workgroup>Documentation Team</workgroup>
		
		
		<!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
		<abstract>
			<t>
		        This document is intended to be the starting point of a specific series
		        of initiatives designed to improve overall usability of Xaraya from all
		        points-of-view (POV).  This is a living document and, as such, is subject 
		        to change.  
			</t>
			<t>
		        Specifically, we expect that some of the issues raised herein may have 
		        already been addressed and/or are in the process of being resolved.  As
		        these issues are resolved, they will be moved to the "Resolved Issues"
		        Appendix.  They will not be removed as this document is intended to be 
		        the document of record for all usability concerns.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	
	<!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
	<middle>
    <!-- One content section is mandatory -->		
		<section title="Preface">		      
			<section title="Underlying Assumptions">
				<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t><em>Markets and User Base Defined</em>
							<t> 
                Xaraya's target markets/user base are as follows:
								<t></t>
								<list style="numbers">
									<t><em>Web Designers/Developers: </em>
										Arguably the largest immediate audience of Xaraya,
										independent Web Designers/Developers are looking for 
										tool that will allow them to quickly deploy a 
										robust, yet simple-to-use content management system
										for their customers. This market will act as
										Administrators for client sites and their clients will
										act as Editors/Members.									
									</t>	
									<t><em>Individuals, Clubs &amp; Special Interest Groups (SIGs): </em>
										This market likely mirrors Web Designers/Devs closely.
										The differentiator is, in most cases, a small
										group or individual will be primarily responsible for
										application, content and user administrations
									</t>	
									<t><em>Small-Medium Sized Business Web Presence: </em>
										The end-customer of the Web Designers/Developers who
										have enough knowledge in house to install and administer
										Xaraya as a public web presence.  In addition to core
										CMS and User Management functionality, this market will
										be looking for 3PD eCommerce Plugins as well to allow 
										them to conduct business on the web.
									</t>	
									<t><em>Corporate Intranet: </em>
										Like the Small-Medium Business market, the Corporate
										Intranet market has the technical know-how on staff
										to install and administer Xaraya themselves.  This 
										market will look for specific Core and Plug-In 
										components to enable Interop with existing systems. 
										Examples include extending Core User components to
										use LDAP authentication and support for Oracle and 
										Microsoft SQL Server. 
									</t>	
								</list>  
							</t>	
						</t>
						<t><em>90% of end-users never touch code</em>
							<t> 
							As developers first, we all tend to think too technically
							and, as a result, assume too much know-how on the part of the
							end-users of the code.  While 3PDs are a valuable audience which
							needs active and agressive support, they will be best served
							if we make the underlying Xaraya platform as user-friendly as
							possible for the non-technical browser/member and content owner/editor.
							</t>					  	
						</t>
						
						<t><em>Clear, Common Nomenclature Required</em>
							<t>
								To create clear, effective documentation which enhances usability
								for all target audiences, clear and consistent nomenclature is  
								required.  Where appropriate, we have attempted to establish
								naming conventions and labels we think will be most effective.
								All of this terminology is open for discussion.  In the end,
								we need simple, concise definitions that work.
							</t>	
						</t>
						
					</list>
				</t>	
			</section>	
			
			<section title="Terminology">
				<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>
							<em>Xaraya Components</em>
							<t></t>
							Common terminology is a critical component to effectively communicating
							with one another and with the end-user.  In the past, we have used 
							the term <em>Module</em> relatively loosely.  As we more definitively
							isolate core components more clearly from add-on components, we suggest
							deprecating the term <em>Module</em> and adopting the term 
							<em>Component</em>.  With this change, we further define Xaraya 
							Components as follows:
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers">
								<t><em>Core: </em> 
								Core components include all files (module, SQL, docs, 
								themes, etc.) considered an essential part of the core 
								distribution of Xaraya.
								</t>
								<t><em>Plugins: </em>
								Commonly referred to as <em>Modules</em>, Plugins include
								any add-on which either extends a core Component or adds
								entirely new functionality to Xaraya.
								</t>
								<t><em>Themes: </em>
								Also referred to as <em>Skins</em>, Themes use BlockLayout
								to reconfigure the visual user interface (UI) of Xaraya. 
								Themes can be as subtle as a simple color change and as 
								radical as a complete redesign of the way th page functions
								and how information is arranged.						  		
								</t>
							</list>
							<t></t>
						</t>	            
						<t><em>General Terms Used in this Document</em>
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers">
								<t><em>Interop: </em>
									Short for <em>Inter-Operability</em>, Interop refers to 
									the increasing need for Web Services in general and 
									Websites in specific, to interact with one another
									in meaningful ways.  The primary goals of Interop 
									initiatives generally serve both the developer and the
									end-user by establishing standards which make it 
									simpler to share data and eliminate repetitive tasks.
								</t>
								<t><em>Third Party Developer (3PD): </em>
									Any individual or team that develops Plugins and/or 
									Themes yet is not member of the Xaraya Development Team.
								</t>
								<t><em>xApproved: </em>
									Working name for "blessed" Plugins and Themes.  xApproved
									components have be reviewed by the Xaraya Team and are
									certified as compliant with the standards outlined in
									the Xaraya Developer's Guide.
								</t>
							</list>
						</t>	
					</list>
				</t>	
			</section>	      
		</section>	
    
		<section title="Developer POV">
			<section title="Core Architecture">
			
				<section anchor="General_Issues" title="General Issues">	
          <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t><em>Platform Awareness:</em>
                <t></t>
                To enable ease of installation and a variety of administrative 
                utilities, Xaraya needs to auto-detect the following information
                about the installation environment. <em>Note:</em> This need 
                may already be addressed by calling PHPInfo in the installer.
                <t></t>
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t><em>Operating System: </em>Brand &amp; Version</t>
                  <t><em>Database Platform: </em>Brand &amp; Version</t> 
                  <t><em>Site Kit Dependencies: </em> Any packages which may 
                    be required for components of a specific site kit.</t>
                  <t><em>???: </em></t>
                </list> 	
                <t></t>					
              </t>	
              <t><em>Component Subcategories:</em>
                <t></t>
                In addition to the macro-level classification of Xaraya Components 
                (Core, Plug-In &amp; Theme), Core &amp; Plug-In Components can
                and should be further subcategorized to facilitate several
                initiatives.  Refer to <xref target="Appendix_B">Appendix B</xref>
                for proposed Component Subcategories.  Initiatives enabled by 
                Component Subcategories include:		 
                <t></t>
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t>xApproved Component Registration</t>	
                  <t>Auto-generated Component Information/Download/Install Directory</t>
                  <t>Automated Component Update</t>	
                  <t>Site Kit Development &amp; Distribution</t>	
                  <t>Default Component Permissions based on User Role</t>
                  <t>???</t>					
                </list> 	
                <t></t>	
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
				</section>	  
				
				<section anchor="Directory_Structure" title="Directory Structure">
					<t>					
					To enable quick, selective back ups, the application should be
					organized within a simple, yet specific directory structure. As
					new components (Core or Plug-In) are created, they should adhere
					to this directory structure.  One possible solution is listed below.
					Within <em>/var/www/html</em>, the top-level directories would be:
					<t></t>
					<list style="numbers">
					  <t><em>/backups: </em> 
					  		If a backup utility is included in the Core, this would be 
							the target directory for the local tar/zip files created.
					  </t>
					  <t><em>/core: </em> 
					  		Only Core components and their supporting files are held here.
							Subdirectories may include:
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers"> 							  
								<t>/core/components</t>
								<t>/core/language</t>
								<t>/core/sql</t>	
								<t>???</t>							
							</list> 
							<t></t>
					  </t>
					  <t><em>/configs: </em> 
					  		Xaraya's analog to /etc, this directory 
					  		includes all custom configuration files.
					  </t>
					  <t><em>/content: </em> Isolated primarily to give one central, 
					  		standard location for developers to put user-added content.
							By centralizing user added content in one standard directory,
							we enable simpler back-ups of content not contained within the DB.
							One simple example would be <em>/albums</em> created by <em>Gallery</em>.
							Additional detailed examples include ...
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers"> 							  
								<t>/content/articles</t> 
								<t>/content/albums</t>
								<t>/content/downloads</t>	
								<t>/content/home/*.username/ <em>(possibly used by Dynamic User Data)</em></t>
								<t>/content/images</t> 
								<t>/content/music</t>
								<t>/content/reviews</t>
								<t>/content/uploads</t>
								<t>???</t>							
							</list> 
							<t></t>
					  </t> 
					  <t><em>/docs: </em> 
					  		This directory holds all docs for Xaraya.	It would NOT 
							contain docs for individual Plugins or Themes.  Those
							docs would be held in a subdir of the directory created by 
							and containing the Plug-In or theme.  					  		
					  </t>
					  <t><em>/plugins: </em> All 3PD Plugins and their supporting 
					  		files (/docs, /lang, etc.) go here. This isolates them from 
							Core components and reduces the opportunity for corruption 
							of Core by accidental overwrites or installs gone awry.
							Unless installing a Site Kit containing non-Core Plugins,
							this directory would be empty with the base Xaraya installation.
					  </t>
					  <t><em>/themes: </em>
						 	This directory would initially contain the default Xaraya
							theme and would be the target directory for installation of 
							all 3PD Themes.
					  </t>
					</list>
					</t>
				</section> 			
		
				<section anchor="ui_overall" title="BlockLayout and Overall UI Issues">	
					<t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                <em>Typeface: </em>
                Theme templates should consistently apply typeface across the 
                application.  Basically, all fonts should be controlled by the
                theme CSS. This may already have been addressed in the BL
                implementation.  If so, we still need to keep an eye out for
                legacy font controls from PN which had very inconsistent font
                controls.
              </t> 
              <t>
                <em>Link Style: </em>
                If links are not underlined in theme CSS definition, rollover 
                must include underline.
              </t>
              <t>
                <em>Supported Browsers: </em>	
                The following list covers all browsers in which Xaraya has been
                developed and tested.  This does not mean Xaraya will not function
                in older browsers, only that it has been designed to leverage
                technologies available in more current offerings.  Browsers not
                on this list are not officially support by Xaraya.	  
                <t></t>
                <list style="numbers">
                  <t>Internet Explorer 5.5+</t>
                  <t>Mozilla 0.9.8+</t>
                  <t>Netscape 6.2+</t>	
                  <t>Opera 6.5+</t>									 
                </list>	
                <t></t>  
              </t>
              <t>
                <em>Proprietary CSS Attributes: </em>
                Xaraya does not endorse proprietary CSS attributes such as 
                <em>scrollbar-*s</em> in Internet Explorer, or <em>-moz-*</em> 
                in Mozilla.
              </t>	
              <t>
                <em>General Enhancements to "How To" Language: </em>
                There are some changes that should be made to the English 
                language file that will make X more clearly understandable. 
                <em>See Drew.</em>
              </t>  
              <t>
                <em>Use Non-technical Language: </em>
                Remove all techno-speak from site.  Example: Don't refer 
                to things as "date/timestamp" -- say "date field", "time field", etc. 
              </t>	
              <t>
                <em>Input Field Width: </em>
                Width of text input fields should be configurable by the 
                Administrator in Site Settings.
              </t>
              <t>
                <em>Breadcrumb Support: </em>
                Not sure if bread crumb support is planned as a BL Widget.  If not, it should
                be.
              </t>		
              <t>
                <em>Page Weight: </em>
                Page weight on an un-modified configuration should be 
                ~50K. Exceptions include articles, reviews, etc.</t>								
              <t>
                <em>Consistent Element Labels: </em>
                Consistent use and guidelines for naming of all UI elements,
                including, but not limited to buttons (SEARCH, GO, BACK, etc)
                and Field Names (ex. Username, Password, Address, etc.)
                Final approved list to be determined.
              </t>						
              <t>
                <em>Delete Confirmations: </em>
                Confirm <em>ALL</em> deletions from the site database.
              </t>							
              <t>
                <em>HTML Language: </em>
                All text in lang/xxx.php should be parsed as HTML, and 
                displayed in HTML if codes are present. There are a few 
                locations in which this is not the case. <em>See Drew</em>
              </t>
              <t>
                <em>Printer Friendliness: </em>
                All pages should offer a link to a printer friendly version.
              </t>
              <t>
                <em>Consistent Content Add/Delete Process: </em>
                With the exception of content-specific fields, the UI
                tools used to add content should have conistent look-and-feel,
                instructions and other UI elements and processes. In short,
                adding WebLinks should function the same as adding Reviews.
              </t>							
            </list>
          </t>			
				</section>
		</section>
  
		<section title="Third Party Developer (3PD) Standards">
			<section title="xApproved Plugins">
				<t>Plug-In standards still need to be defined in the Xaraya Developer's 
					Guide.  Once established, we need an infrastructure to review
					and approve new <em>xApproved</em> Plugins.	  
					<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t><em>xarAPI Compliance:</em> 
							All xApproved Plugins must comply with the xarAPI as outlined
							in the forthcoming Xaraya Developer's Guide.
						</t> 
						<t><em>phpDoc Style Comments:</em> 
							All xApproved Plugins must be suitably commented in the phpDoc
							style so comments can be extracted as needed for further 
							development by Xaraya and/or other 3PDs.
						</t>
					</list>
					</t>
				</t>
			</section>	
		
			<section title="xApproved Themes">
				<t>Theme standards still need to be defined in the Xaraya Developer's 
					Guide.  Once established, we need an infrastructure to review
					and approve new <em>xApproved</em> Themes. Some preliminary standards
					include:
					<t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t><em>Web Standards:</em> 
						  	XHTML 1.0 (Strict) and CSS 2.0 compliant
						</t>
					</list>
					</t>
				</t>
			</section>							
		</section>
      
		</section>			
		
		<section title="Administrator (GOD) POV">
			<section title="Installation and Upgrades">
				<t>
					The following describes the ideal Installation experience.  Some features
					may not be feasible by Release 1.0 and/or may not make sense when
					described technically. New steps/screens/functionality are 
					<em>emphasized</em> and, as a rule, are explained in greater detail 
					later in the document.
				</t>
				
				<section title="BASE INSTALLATION">					
          <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t><em>Pre-Install Questions/Checks</em>
                <t></t>
                <list style="numbers"> 
                  <t><em>Pre-Install Checklist</em></t>
                  <t>Language</t>							  
                  <t>Accept GPL?</t>
                  <t><xref target="Appendix_A">Permit Installation Logging?</xref></t>	
                  <t>Systems Setting Check</t>							  
                  <t>Database Settings</t>
                  <t><xref target="Appendix_C">Site Kit Selection</xref></t>				
                </list>
							  <t></t>		
              </t>
              
              <t><em>Base Configuration</em>
                <t></t>
								<list style="numbers"> 								  
									<t>
										<em>Pre-Install Checklist: </em> Collect any non-automated 
                    configurations processes into one printable <em>DO-THIS-FIRST</em>
                    file, and tell the user what they have to do (chmod, 
                    etc). Strongly recommend they print it out before proceeding
									</t>
									<t>
										<em>phpMyAdmin: </em> In either basic or xModular form, 
										phpMyAdmin should be distributed and installed with Xaraya 
										Core. It is a very mature and useful tool for Administrators. 
                    As such, we should embrace it.  As phpMyAdmin is a MySQL-specific
										tool, it would need adapted (presumably via ADODB) to work
										with other Xaraya-supported databases (PostGRESQL, Oracle).
										If this is not possible, the feature would only be made
										available for MySQL users or an alternative tool would
										be used							 							
									</t>		
									<t>
										<em>Default Theme: </em> Xaraya distribution should contain
										only <em>ONE</em> default theme.  Other themes may be readily
										available on Xaraya.com, but the single default theme is 
										required to create a consistent set of documentation and 
										help reduce the learning curve.
									</t>	
									<t>
										<em>Default Core Modules: </em>	
										<t></t>
										<list style="numbers">	 
											<t>Articles</t>
											<t>
												<em>Credits: </em> A simple way to put ALL 
												credits for EVERYTHING on the site in one place.	
											</t>		
											<t>Comments</t>
											<t>Help</t>
											<t>?</t>
											<t>?</t>
											<t>Search</t>
											<t>Site Map <em>(NEW)</em></t>
										</list>
										<t></t>
									</t> 
									<t>
										<em>Component Configuration: </em>	
										Remove the LIST option from the start of Component (Modules) 
										configuration in AdminPanels. Use "Regenerate" every time.
									</t>
									<t>
										<em>Lorem Ipsum (Default Content): </em>
										At installation, there should be default data in ALL areas of 
										the site -- Reviews, Topics, Articles, FAQs, Sections, etc. -- 
										if for no other reason than it provides the documentation team 
										material with which to work when teaching how to edit or delete 
										stuff.
									</t> 	
									<t>
										<em>??? </em>	
									</t>
								</list> 
							<t></t>		
						</t>		 					
						
						<t><em>Site Kits</em> 				
							<t></t>
							<t>
								Site Kits are explained in far greater detail in 
								<xref target="Appendix_C">Appendix C</xref>.  The following
								are high-level reccommended behaviors of Site Kits.
								<t></t>		
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t> Install ALL approved Modules, but only activate/configure
									 	those defined in the Site Kit.</t>
									<t> Tell the user what modules will be ACTIVATED (all are installed, 
										selection above determines which are activated by the installer)</t>
									<t> Display INACTIVE modules (with descriptions) and allow user to add them.</t>
									<t> Any modules that are activated which require additional configuration, 
										the configuration of that module is added to the installation process.</t>										
									<t>???</t>							  													
								</list>              
							</t>
						</t>
            </list>
          </t>
				</section>	
				
				<section title="Upgrades and Additions">
					<t>
						Again, Red Hat Network and MS Windows Update are the functionality
						benchmarks for ease of use. Specifically, Xaraya would ideally
						have a built in mechanism through which the Administrator can 
						click a button and have their installation compared to a database
						residing on Xaraya servers.  Once this comparison is complete,  a 
						report is generated describing available updates and giving the 
						Administrator the option of downloading and installing the updates 
						automatically.
					</t>
					<t>
					<list style="numbers"> 
						<t><em>Overall Considerations</em>
						<t></t>						
						<list style="numbers"> 						
							<t><em>Xaraya Registration DB: </em>
								Centralized database housed on the Xaraya web server 
								(Sasquatch).  This DB contains two primary types of 
								information:
								<t></t>
								<t>
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t><em>Component Registration:</em>
										All Xaraya components (Core, as well as Official/Approved
										Plugins and Themes) require registration with a
										unique identifier in the Xaraya Registration DB.
									</t>
									<t><em>Install Registration:</em>
										If we elect to go this route, the Registration DB
										would also contain unique registration keys for each 
										Xaraya installation.
									</t>
								</list>
								</t>
								<t></t>
							</t>	
							<t><em>Available Updates Profile (Xaraya Server): </em>
								Profile derived from Component Registration tables.  Used in
								Comparison Pass to determine which updates are available
								for installation.
							</t>						
							<t><em>Installation Profile (Local Install): </em>
								After install/update is completed, an Installation Profile
								is created/modified on the user's server. This file
								will be used in the Comparison Pass and, optionally, it
								could be pushed to the Install Registration tables as well.
							</t>
							
							<t><em>Comparison Script: </em>
								Admin Panels provides <em>Check for Updates</em>
								button.  When clicked, the following occurs:
								<t></t>
								<t>
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t><em>Pre-Upgrade Checklist: </em>
										Check list is displayed which includes, among 
										other things, a detailed description of what is 
										about to occur and what, if any, server configurations 
										(ex. Enable write permissions) are required to proceed.
										It also includes links to reccommended pre-upgrade
										utilities (ex. <xref target="backup">File/DB Backup</xref>).
										After reviewing this checklist and taking action 
										as needed, the user clicks the <em>Next</em> button.
										<em>Note: </em>All Upgrade screens have and
										<em>Cancel</em> button which exits out to AdminPanels.
									</t>	
									<t><em>Pass Installation Profile to Server</em>
										Passes the local Installation Profile to the Comparison 
										Script on Xaraya's server.  Script compares profiles 
										and reports on available updates.
									</t>
									<t><em>Select Desired Updates: </em>
										From the report, user uses checkboxes to select
										desired updates for installation.
									</t>
									<t><em>Package and Transfer Files: </em>
										Based on user selection, script builds a tar/zip file 
										containing the selected updates and writes it
										to the install directory on the target server.
									</t>
									<t><em>Install Updates: </em>
										Once the file has transferred, the script expands 
										the archive and writes files to the appropriate 
										location.  If needed, the script also updates the 
										*SQL server    
									</t>
								</list>
								</t>
								<t></t>
							</t>						
						</list> 
						</t>		
				
						<t><em>Core Specific</em>
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers"> 
								<t><em>TBD As Needed</em></t>
							</list>	
							<t></t>	
          			</t>
						
						<t><em>Plug-In Specific</em> 
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers"> 
								<t><em>TBD As Needed</em></t>
							</list>	
							<t></t>		
          			</t>
						
						<t><em>Theme Specific</em>
							<t></t>
							<list style="numbers"> 
								<t><em>TBD As Needed</em></t>
							</list>		
						</t>
					</list>
					<t></t>
					</t>
				</section>						
			</section>
      				
			<section anchor="backup" title="Administrative Utilities Toolset">
				<t> 
				To truly administer a Xaraya site well, the Administrator needs a strong toolset.  Some
				of the tools are be discussed elsewhere in this document. The following is a current best
				guess at the desired Administrative Utilities Toolset.
				
				<list style="numbers">
					<t><em>Backup Utilities: </em>
						Using platform awareness and available tools, the Administrator need the ability
						to quickly and efficiently back up his site prior to upgrading.  These tools
						include Database Backup (phpMyAdmin or similar tool) and File Back Up for the 
						following Xaraya directories (at a minimum). 
						<t></t>
						<list style="numbers">
							 <t>/configs</t>
							 <t>/content</t>
							 <t>/plugins</t>
							 <t>/themes</t>
						</list>	
						<t></t>
					</t> 
					<t><em>Custom Language Editor: </em>		
						  	One interface to edit ALL language files, even those in 
							component directories (Plugins &amp; Themes). As part of the component registration 
							process, it would announce the presence/location of the 
							component language files.
							<t></t>
							<em>Drew's Notes: </em>  
							<t></t>
							It would be great if there was a default file, say <em>eng_override.php</em> 
							(different prefix for other languages, of course) in the 
							<em>/configs</em> that would allow over-ride of what's in the language 
							files, to prevent having to edit the distribution files directly. 
							For example, in /plugins/<em>&lt;plugin_name&gt;</em>/lang/eng/global.php, 
							it has	<em>'define("_PRODUCTTITLE","Product title");'</em>, but I would 
							like to override that. 
							<t></t>
							So, in eng_override.php, I would be able to do 
							<em>'define("_PRODUCTTITLE","Product/Event title");'</em> and have 
							eng_override.php included at the appropriate times to override 
							what's in the distribution file if the eng_override.php file 
							exists. As I edit my distribution language files more and more, 
							the more I think this feature would be very helpful. If the 
							eng_override.php file doesn't exist, it would just use the 
							defaults in the distribution language file.
							<t></t>  
					</t>	 
					<t>
						<em>Groups &amp; Permissions GUI: </em>
						Groups &amp; Permissions GUI was badly in need of an overhaul.
						Marcinmilan is already hard at work on this.  We are just calling it
						out here to support his work in progress.
					</t> 
					<t>
						<em>Administration Menu Block: </em>		
						The default installation should display Administration menu 
						items in a menu block, not as a module list. Everyone uses 						
						the menu block method; it's the most powerful option. 
						<em>Note: </em> This method is already being employed in 
						AdminPanels.  Like Permissions GUI, we are calling it out 
						here as a show of support.
					</t>					
					<t><em>??? </em>		
						  
					</t>

				</list>
				</t>	
			</section>					

			<section title="Default User Roles">
				<t>
          		One of the core failings of the *Nuke platform is that it only provided
					two default user roles (Administrator and User).  This approach assumes
					that the Administrator was also the Content editor in all cases.  
					Regular usage of *Nukes and user feedback indicates the need for a 
					third default role (Editor).  Each proposed user role is defined below.
        		</t>
				<section title="Administrator (GOD User)">
					<t>	
						No real role change here.  This is the Xaraya equivalent of 
						<em>/root</em>.  Just as no Server Admin will give out <em>/root</em>
						to just anyone, so to should the Administrator role be tightly
						guarded.	By default, the Administrator can do <em>anything</em> 
						on the system.
					</t>
				</section>	
        
				<section title="Editor (Super User)">
					<t>
						 This is an entirely new default role.  Most Administrators end
						 up creating this sort of role anyway, so it makes sense to 
						 include it as a default.  By default, this role has 
						 <em>ONLY</em> content and user management (add/approve/modify/delete) 
						 rights.  They have no system configuration, install/upgrade,
						 database access or other global rights to impact the system.						 
					</t>
				</section>		
        
				<section title="Member (Base User)">
					<t>
						 In the past, this role has been generically referred to as
						 <em>User</em>.  This level of access gives permission to
						 additional content and/or services and local user configuration
						 options.  This role has no Administrator/Editor rights.	 This
						 role can submit content for publication, but it must be 
						 approved by an Administrator or Editor.
					</t>
				</section>	
				<section title="Anonymous (Guest User)">
					<t>
						 No real change here. This is a single account which is used by
						 generic browsers.  Beyond accessing publicly available content 
						 and services, this user has <em>NO</em> rights on the system.
					</t>
				</section>	
			</section>		
		</section>				
		
		<section title="End-User (Member/Editor) POV">		
      
			<section title="Role-Specific Behaviors">	  
			
				<section title="Editor Role">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers"> 
							<t>
								<em>Context Sensitive Editing Tools: </em>
								All Components should provide access to Administrator/Editor tools 
								from <em>WITHIN</em> the module if the user logged in is an
								Administrator or Editor with the appropriate permissions for that 
								Component.	
							</t> 
							<t>
								<em>Reorganize Content Management Links/Pages: </em>
								Organize Editor pages by long-term usability and 
								put the options that are most likely to be frequently used 
								at the top of the page. For example, WebLinks is currently 
								ordered as follows:
								<t></t>	
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t>Add a category</t> 
									<t>Modify a category</t>
									<t>Add a new link</t>
									<t>Modify a link</t>
									<t>Web Links Configuration</t>
								</list>
								<t></t>
								It is more logical, when long-term usage is considered, 
								to order it as follows:			
								<t></t>	
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t>Add a new link</t> 
									<t>Modify a link</t>
									<t>Add a category</t>
									<t>Modify a category</t>
									<t>Web Links Configuration</t>
								</list>
								<t></t>	
								Alternatively, it would be very useful (though probably 
								difficult to implement) to track usage of Editing Tools 
								based, perhaps, on page hits.  Armed with this usage data,
								the system could, upon logon, present the Editor with a 
								<em>Frequently Used Tools</em> Menu Block or AdminPanel.	
								<t></t>
							</t>									
							<t>
								<em>Article MetaCommands: </em>
								<t></t>	
								<list style="numbers"> 
									<t>
										<em>Story Links: </em>
										Provide an easy method within an article to link to another 
										article on the same site. Metacommands like "&lt;readprev=520&gt;" 
										and "&lt;readnext=525&gt;" would be VERY useful. Each metacommand 
										would be replaced as follows:
										<t></t>		
										<list style="numbers"> 
											<t>
												<em>"&lt;readfirst=519&gt;"</em> would display user-defined text (like 
												"&lt;i&gt;Click &lt;b&gt;here&lt;/b&gt; to read the first article&lt;/i&gt;") 
												in this series link to article #519. 
											</t>
											<t>
												<em>"&lt;readprev=520&gt;"</em> would display user-defined text (like 
												"&lt;i&gt;Click &lt;b&gt;here&lt;/b&gt; to read the previous article&lt;/i&gt;") 
												and link to article #520.
											</t>
											<t>
												<em>"&lt;readnext=525&gt;"</em> would display user-defined text (like 
												"&lt;i&gt;Click &lt;b&gt;here&lt;/b&gt; to read the next article&lt;/i&gt;") and 
												link to article #525. 
											</t>
											
										</list>
										<t></t>	
									</t>
									<t>
										<em>Read More: </em>
										Add a metacommand for NEWS STORIES like "&lt;readmore&gt;". When 
										this text is found in the body of an article, automatically 
										replace it with a user-defined string (like "&lt;i&gt;Click 
										&lt;b&gt;here&lt;/b&gt; to read more...&lt;/i&gt;") that links to the full 
										article view. In the full article view or in print view, 
										the &lt;readmore&gt; string is NOT displayed.
									</t>
									<t>
										<em>Page Break: </em>
										Where ever this appears, a single article is broken into 
										multiple pages with auto-generated navigation links (ex. PREV, NEXT, etc.) 
									</t>
									<t>
										<em>Configurable URL/HREF Targets: </em>
										Ideally, Xaraya would be aware if the contents of
										an HREF are local (onsite) or external (offsite)
										as determined by the presence or absence of 
										<em>http://</em>. The Administrator/Editor would be 
										then be able to set a configuration variable which 
										would determine if the HREF should pop a new window 
										to display the target URL (analagous to target="blank").  
										This seting would be global across the site, but 
										could be over-ridden on a case-by-case basis.										
									</t>
								</list>
								<t></t>	
								<t></t>						
							</t>	
						</list>
					</t>		
				</section>	
				
				<section title="Member Role">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers"> 
							<t>
								<em>my.&lt;domainname&gt;.com: </em> 
								On login, default page is <em>my.&lt;domainname&gt;.com</em>.
								This page would display things like:
								<t></t>
								<list style="numbers"> 	
									<t>Waiting private messages,</t>
									<t>Custom RSS feeds,</t>
									<t>User's admin tools (gallery upload, change password, etc),</t>
									<t><em>New Items</em> (See Below)</t>	  
									<t>Bookmarked Forums, Links etc (see vBulletin)</t>
									<t>
										<em>Alerts &amp; Notifications: </em> 
										Derived from choices made in Pub/Sub/Unsub component.
									</t>	 
									<t>Other Dynamic User Data (DUD) enabled content</t>
									<t>???</t>
								</list>
								<t></t>
							</t>	
							<t>
								<em>"NEW" Block: </em>
								A category called "NEW" that displays, based on item timestamp 
								and date/time of user's last login, new items. Period of time 
								for "new" status is configurable by admin.
							</t>
							<t>
								<em>Content Sorting: </em>
								Users can set PRIORITY of items on the site (display SPORTS topic 
								items first, display ARTS topic items second, etc.) and the page 
								will show only the items that the user has configured to see (turn 
								OFF SPORTS topics (they are not displayed)..
							</t>	
						</list>
						<t></t>
					</t>		
				</section>	
				
			</section>
			
			<section title="Module-Specific Behaviors">
				<section title="Articles">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers">
							<t>
								<em>PREVIOUS, NEXT, and TOP Links : </em>
								Display these at the bottom of the front page. 
								Get the count of the number of articles to display from the 
								value in Administration --&gt; Settings --&gt; Stories # on homepage.
							</t>
							<t>
								<em>???</em>
								
							</t>							
						</list>			
					</t>
				</section>	
			
				<section title="Content Management">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers">
							<t>
								<em>DMOZ/Yahoo Index: </em>	
								All modules which gather and classify information (links, 
								downloads, etc) should use a DMOZ/Yahoo style index. 								
							</t>	
							<t>
								<em>New Item Indicator: </em>
								New items in sub-categories need some "new" indicator (icon, font color, 
								etc.) which is configurable at the Administrator and/or Theme level.
							</t>	
							<t>
								<em>???</em>
								
							</t>							
						</list>			
					</t>
				</section> 
				
				<section title="Community Management">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers">
							<t>
								<em>User/Context Sensitive Help System: </em>
								Ideally, the help system will be aware of both the Component it is being
								called from (to determine Help Content) and the Role of the User logged in
								(Admin, Editor, Member) and display the appropriate level of Help detail
								based on user Role.
							</t>
							<t>
								<em>??? </em>
								
							</t>			
						</list>	             
					</t>
				</section>
	
				<section title="Dynamic User Data">
					<t>
						<list style="numbers">
							<t>
								<em>??? </em>
								
							</t>					
						</list>	             
					</t>
				</section>	
		</section>	
	</section>  		   
   
   <section title="Revision history">
      <t>2003-01-15: First Draft (Daulton/Vogel)</t>
		<t>2003-02-03: Second Draft (Daulton/Vogel)</t>
      <t>2003-02-11: Release 0.9 (Daulton/Vogel)</t>
   </section>    
</middle>

<back>
	<section anchor="Appendix_A" title="Installation Reporting and Automated Update Tools">
	<t>
         It has been suggested that, upon completion of a Xaraya install, the 
         application either automatically ping Xaraya's server and collect information 
         (perceived as spyware by many) or we ask users to register which does the 
         same thing.  For real world examples ... think Windows Update, Red Hat Network
         and the Eclipse Updater Tool.
	</t>
	<t>
         This Reporting Installer could collect all sorts of valuable information
         which, if positioned correctly and paired with a clean and simple opt-out
         process could achieve the following goals:
         <list style="numbers">	 
           	<t>Accurate Install/Usage statistics with which we can use in ...
					<t></t>
					<list style="numbers">
						<t>Forecasting future installs,</t>
						<t>Defining Market Share,</t>
						<t>Fund-raising,</t>
						<t>Marketing</t>
					</list>
					<t></t>
	           	</t>
	           	<t>
		             Establishes useful user database with as much (or as little) information
		             as we feel is appropriate to maintain about our install base.  This would
		             not be spyware because we would allow folks a simple way to opt-out at the
		             beginning (no optin by default) and if they optout, we would simply add a
		             install tick to the counter and collect no data.
	           	</t>
         </list>	
         <t>
           As users elect to opt-in, they share more information about their install
           and intended usage which allows us to do some really cool stuff like ...
         </t>
         <list style="numbers">
           <t>Automated core updates (again, think Eclipse Updater, RHN, WU)</t>
			    <t>Detailed market analysis (who is using the site for what ... blogs, music sites, pron, etc)</t>
			    <t>Detailed system stats for install base (windows, LAMP, etc)</t>
			    <t>Automated YANXS directory</t>
			    <t>Security Alerts and Patch Notices via email even SMS or pager</t>
         </list>	
         <t>
           We can work out the details, but you get the idea.  It is not spyware if we
           give them the option to opt-out and tell them if they do, no information
           beyond a "Install Counter tick" will be passed and we could even forgo that
           if we wanted.  IMO, the benefits to everyone (core, user and dev communities
           alike) and hurts no one.
         </t>
       </t>
	</section>		
     
	<section anchor="Appendix_B" title="Proposed Component Subcategories">
       <t>
         <list style="numbers">
           <t>
             <em>Core Components</em> 
             <t></t>
             <list style="numbers">							
               <t><em>Setup  (Base??): </em>
                 Single or infrequent-use tools for configuring the site
                 ex. Site Configuration, Theme Selection
               </t>
               <t><em>Utilities (AdminPanels): </em>
                 Backend Management (db adds, cleanup, archiving, etc)
                 ex. Translations, Autolinks, Web Services, Categories
               </t>
               <t><em>Content Admin: </em>
                 Any tools which setup how content is viewed/managed
                 ex. Articles, Links, Downloads, RSS, Pubsub, Polls Reviews, 
                 WSW Editor
               </t>
               <t><em>Membership (Users): </em>
                 Any and all tools for user management
                 ex. Groups, Permissions, DUD, Messages, Mail Blast
               </t>	
               <t><em>Site Promotion: </em>
                 ex. Recommend, Stats, HitCount, Keywords, Mail Blast
               </t>	
               <t><em>Online Help: </em>
                 ex. Search, FAQs, Help
                 <t></t>
               </t>						
             </list>					
           </t>
           
           <t>
             <em>Plug-In Components</em> 
             <t></t>				
             <list style="numbers">
               <t><em>eBusiness/eCommerce: </em>
                 ex. OpenRealty, OSCommerce, CafePress, Amazon bookstore, etc.
               </t>
               <t><em>Scheduling/PIM: </em>
                 ex. xCalendar, xProject, ToDo List, BKView, Seminar Scheduler
               </t>
               <t><em>Communication/Social Networking: </em>
                 ex. Forums, NNTP UI, Chat/ShoutBox, WebRing
               </t>
               <t><em>Content Expansions: </em>
                 ex. Pinup, Gallery, MeG, Comic, AvantGo, MP3 Managers/Streamers, Fan
                 Fiction, Collaborative Stories, MyHaiku, Bible/Torah/Quran Verse DB,
                 pnEncyclopedia, pnDictionary, CookBook/Recipe Modules
               </t>
               <t><em>Games: </em>
                 ex. Nascar, Fantasy Football, Flash Games, Half-Life/Counterstrike/Unreal Server Stats
               </t>
               <t><em>Data Collection: </em>
                 ex. Surveys, Quizzes, Extended Polls
               </t>
               <t><em>Dynamic User Data: </em>
                 ex. xResume, xPortfolio, My <em>&lt;sitename&gt;</em> HomePage, Blog, DUD DB 
                 Expansions for specific groups (Church, School, Club, Game Clan, etc)
               </t>
               <t><em>Core Extensions: </em>
                 These are really Core Components Hacks and/or Replacements.  May not be
                 prudent to list them, but would include stuff like ... Advanced Search, 
                 Mass Mailer, KnowledgeBase(expanded FAQs)
                 <t></t>
               </t>
             </list>	
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
	</section>			
		
	<section anchor="Appendix_C" title="Site Kits">
	<t>
         As the name implies, <em>Site Kits</em> are a series of pre-configured 
         Xaraya tarballs	(Core + Modules).  As frame of reference, think of the
         Red Hat GUI-based Installer. For example ...
			</t>
			<t> <em>Red Hat:</em> What sort of install is this?
				<list style="numbers">
					<t><em>Server</em></t>
					<t><em>Workstation</em></t>
					<t><em>Laptop</em></t>
					<t><em>Custom</em></t>
					<t><em>Everything</em></t>
				</list>						
			</t>
			
			<t>
				Like the Red Hat example, Xaraya Site Kits would install and configure
				pre-built packages based on user choice.  The Xaraya example may look like this ...
			</t>
			
			<t>	<em>Xaraya:</em> How will you use your Xaraya installation?						
				<list style="numbers">
					<t><em>Generic Community :</em> Includes Links, Calendar, Downloads, Forum, Articles, Users</t>
					<t><em>News Site:</em> Includes Articles, Users, Reviews, Calendar</t>
					<t><em>Personal Site:</em> Includes News, BLOG, Links, Gallery</t>
					<t><em>Family Site:</em> Includes Users, Gallery, Articles, Reviews, Links</t>
					<t><em>Online Store:</em> Includes Users, Forums, OSCommerce, Reviews</t>
					<t><em>Gaming Clan:</em> Includes Calendar, Articles, Reviews, Forums, Users, Half-Life Server Stats (or other game server stats)</t>
					<t><em>Corporate Intranet:</em> Includes LDAP, SQL2000 support, Forums, Articles, Gallery, FAQs, Calendar, etc.</t>
					<t><em>School Homeroom:</em> Includes Users /Students, GradeBook, Forums, Articles, Reviews, Gallery, etc.</t>
					<t><em>Non-Profit:</em> Includes Users, Forums, Paypal Donations, Reviews, Articles, etc.</t>
           			<t><em>INFINITE COMBINATIONS:</em> This list can (and will) grow.</t>
					<t><em>Custom</em> </t>
					<t><em>Everything</em> </t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
         As you can see, the possibilities are boundless.  The advantages of this sort of functionality are manifold ...
         <list style="numbers">
           <t>
             It engages 3PDs in much the same way the Red Hat installer and RHN does.
             It gives them a framework within which to simply distribute their work and a
             clear incentive to use that framework guidelines (xDeveloper Guide) to the
             letter.
           </t>
           <t>
             It provides a distinct competitive advantage over other OS CMS as it
             makes us the most configurable tool while making said configuration as
             simple for the end user as possible.
           </t>
           <t>
             It shows foresight and planning which will invite/attract other, bigger
             development partners (IBM, etc) and helps us cement Xaraya as something more
             than garage project like PN or PHP-Nuke.
           </t>
           <t>
             Along with things like LDAP authentication, SOAP support and other
             Interop tools, it provides a possible entree into larger corporate install
             base.
           </t>
           <t>
             Driven by BL, it makes Xaraya the platform of choice for independent
             small to medium sized web developers looking for a way to provide dynamic
             websites without knowing how to code.  They do the install, retheme and
             viola.
           </t>
           <t>
             It makes us a viable option for small to medium business owners looking
             for a way to establish a web presence at low cost.  If they have a bit of
             tech savvy they can do it themselves.
           </t>
           <t>
             Opens the doors for schools (K through University) and other Non-Profits
             to establish web presence is a simple, cost-efficient manner. They may pay
             their ad agency to develop their theme/look, or better yet call on the body
             of Xaraya developers/designers to do so, and save the development costs.  At
             the HS and University level, they may also grow a new generation of  Xaraya
             devs by engaging their students in module development.
           </t>
           <t>
             Instantly breaks the current OS CMS mold which will certainly lead to
             considerable positive exposure for this project in the OS media and in
           </t>
         </list>
         <t>
           Lots of food for thought here ... but the bottom line is this sort of
           feature/module will go a long way to further killing installer usability
           concerns, maintaining an active, engaged an loyal community and rebuilding a
           loyal install base for Xaraya.	
         </t>
       </t>
	</section>		
     
	<section anchor="Appendix_D" title="References and Resources">
       <t>
         <list style="numbers">
           <t><eref target="http://developer.apple.com/techpubs/macosx/Essentials/AquaHIGuidelines/index.html">AQUA: Apple's Human Interface Guidelines</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://www.nngroup.com/reports/">Nielsen Norman Group: Web Usability Guidelines</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://www.webmasterbase.com/article/744/16">SitePoint: Do-It-Yourself Accessibility</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://psychology.wichita.edu/optimalweb/default.htm">Software Usability Research Lab: Wichita State University</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://www.cs.waikato.ac.nz/~daven/docs/oss-wp.html">Usability and Open Source Software by David M. Nichols and Michael B. Twidale</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/UAAG10/">WC3: User Agent Accessibility Guidelines 1.0</eref></t>
           <t><eref target="http://www.useit.com">www.useit.com: Usability Guru Jakob Nielsen</eref></t>
         </list>
       </t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="Appendix_E" title="Package Installations (RPM/MSI Format)">
		<t>
			These ideas require a more mature, stable Xaraya release to begin feasibility
			review.  They are captured here because ultimately, they serve both the project 
			(wider distribution channels) and the end-users (ease of installation).
			<list style="numbers">
				<t><em>Linux Distributions: </em>
					Work with Red Hat &amp; other major Linux distros to integrate 
					Xaraya into their distribution as an on-install package that check 
					dependencies, etc.
				</t>
				<t><em>Windows Distributions: </em>
					Work with FoxServ project to integrate Xaraya into their installation.
				</t>
         	</list>
		</t>
	</section>
    
	<section anchor="Appendix_F" title="Resolved Issues">
		<t>
			This space reserved for future use.
		</t>
	</section>
		
    <section anchor="Appendix_G" title="Additional Credits">
      <t>Many thanks to the following folks who helped research or otherwise prepare these materials.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Chris Dudley (Miko)</t>	          
          <t>Marcel Van der Boom (MrB)</t>  
			 <t>Marty Vance (Dracos)</t> 
			 <t>Tomislav Grabic (Tomi)</t>
	      </list>
		  </t>
    </section>
</back>

</rfc>
