<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<rfc number="0026" category="std">
<!-- number: Fill in the number for the RFC -->
<!-- obsoletes: Comma separated list of RFC numbers which this one obsoletes -->
<!-- category: std=standard, bcp=best common practice, info=info, exp=experimental, historic=historic -->
<!-- Front matter is used for identification of author and organization -->
  <front>
    <title>BlockLayout for Content</title>

    <author initials="P" surname="Fletcher"
    fullname="Philip Fletcher">
      <organization>Stutchbury</organization>

      <address>
        <email>philip@stutchbury.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.stutchbury.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2002" />

<!-- Initiating team for this RFC -->
    <workgroup>Project Management Committee</workgroup>

<!-- List keywords for the RFC here -->
    <keyword>rfc</keyword>

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <keyword>BlockLayout</keyword>

<!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This rfc describes the concept of allowing content to be
      parsed as a BlockLayout template.</t>

      <t>It attempts to address the scope and implications of the
      changes required to implement this proposal.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
<!-- Introduction is mandatory -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This RFC is a first draft proposing the benefits and flexibility
      of parsing Xaraya content for BlockLayout tags. Please see 
      the Appendix for a definition of terms used in the context of this 
      document.  </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Current Implementation">
      <t>The rendering of current Xaraya content is currently
      defined by one or more template files. Although the content
      can vary, the format in which it is presented is determined
      by one or more template files which, by their very nature,
      are static. BlockLayout provides an enormous amount of
      flexibility for implementors to create a unique website for a
      client. Template files will usually be created by the
      implementor for a client site and will not normally be
      modified by admins or editors.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="BlockLayout Rendering for Content">
      <t>This RFC proposes that, in addition to providing the
      rendering for Master, Slave and Internal blocks, BlockLayout
      should also be able to provide rendering for Content. It is
      adding a lower level of granularity to BlockLayout. This
      means that specifed content would be parsed as if it were a
      Template file. All BlockLayout tags would be valid.</t>

      <t>For the purposes of this document, content is defined as
      any data stored in the database for the purpose of display,
      usually on a web site but could be published by any other
      means.</t>

      <t>By using the BlockLayout DTD (or XML schema), Xaraya will
      define a standard structure for all dynamic content. Module
      developers will not have to re-invent the wheel, but will
      have a clearly documented, flexible and proven framework to
      build their data around.</t>

      <t>Authorized admins, editors and even authors would be able
      to create content that is rendered in a truly unique fashion,
      within the defined boundaries of the static template
      files.</t>

      <t>Third party modules, such as WYSIWYG editors or
      FormExpress :) would use the BlockLayout DTD to structure the
      storage and presentation of their content.</t>

      <t>Changes required to the BlockLayout interfaces would
      greatly ease the creation of a database backed template
      editor in the future.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security">
      <t>In a CMS which accepts contributions from insecure (public) 
      sources, one would not want all contributors to be able
      to include BlockLevel tags in their text which might reveal
      sensitive information or destroy the formatting of a page.
      This would have to be addressed at the data entry stage,
      preferably by providing a core function/method that module
      developers would call before committing content to the
      database.</t>

      <t>The granularity of allowable BlockLayout tags could be
      developed over time, with a simple boolean value to begin
      with (i.e. all or nothing) and then extending the current
      'Allowable HTML tags' functionality to include BlockLayout
      tags.</t>

      <t>As an aside, it would be useful for implementors and
      admins to be able to specify custom 'Allowable Tags' and to
      be able to define wildcard matches to be permitted or
      denied.</t>

      <t>On the display side, only content flagged for parsing by 
      BlockLayout would be processed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Performance">
      <t>Assuming that BlockLayout has already been designed for
      performance, this proposal should not significantly impact
      page rendering speed.</t>

      <t>Not all content would need to be parsed. A flag or code
      placed against a content column would instruct a module to
      submit the content to BlockLayout before rendering.
      Alternativley, an xml declaration could be made at the head
      of the content.</t>

      <t>The same cacheing principals would apply - except that the
      md5 checksum would be applied to the content string rather
      than the template file. It would be beneficial (although
      initially not essential) for the module to request that
      BlockLayout does not cache the results. The implementation of
      cacheing rules for content could warrent further
      investigation, especially when combined with widget tags.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution Proposal">
      <t>This section discusses how the BlockLayout for Content
      proposal could be implemented.</t>

      <section title="BlockLayout Interface Changes">
        <t>The following public interfaces to BlockLayout are:</t>

        <section title="xarTplString()">
          <t>Due to it's similar naming convention to xarTplFile(),
          this function appears to do what this proposal requires,
          but the two functions do not behave the same.</t>

          <t>xarTplFile() will accept a BlockLayout Template file
          name; if that file has not already been compiled, then
          the blCompiler will be invoked and a cache file
          created.</t>

          <t>xarTplString(), however will only accept the equivalent
          of the contents of a BlockLayout cache file i.e. valid
          PHP code, not BlockLayout code.</t>

          <t>For consistency, the functionality offered by
          xarTplString() should be the same as that offered by
          xarTplFile i.e. the input should the an uncompiled
          BlockLayout Template. An appropriately named new function
          should be created to implement the current xarTplString()
          functionality e.g. xarTplEval()</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Code that will need to be written">
      <section title="New Functions">
        <section title="xarTpl__executeFromString()">
          <t>This new private function will implement cacheing for
          string based template parsing. It is loosely based around
          xarTpl__executeFromFile(). In fact, there is much 
          commonality that should be brought together into shared 
          functions.</t>
<t>
          <artwork>
          function xarTpl__executeFromString($sourceString, $tplData, $cache_flag=true)
{
    global $xarTpl_cacheTemplates;

    $needCompilation = true;

    if ($xarTpl_cacheTemplates &amp;&amp; $cache_flag) {
        $varDir = xarCoreGetVarDirPath();
        $cacheKey = md5($sourceString);
        $cachedFileName = $varDir . '/cache/templates/' . $cacheKey . '.php';
        //
        //Need to check if source string has changed - is md5 distinct enough to:
        //a) Change with minor amendments to sourceString? or
        //b) Not conflict with other cached files?
        //
        if (file_exists($cachedFileName) ) {
            $needCompilation = false;
        }
    }

    //xarLogVariable('needCompilation', $needCompilation, XARLOG_LEVEL_ERROR);
    if ($needCompilation) {
        $blCompiler = xarTpl__getCompilerInstance();
        $templateCode = $blCompiler->compile($sourceString);
        if (!isset($templateCode)) {
            return; // exception! throw back
        }
        if ($xarTpl_cacheTemplates &amp;&amp; $cache_flag) {
            $fd = fopen($cachedFileName, 'w');
            fwrite($fd, $templateCode);
            fclose($fd);
        } else {
            return xarTpl__execute($templateCode, $tplData);
        }
    }
        $tplData['_bl_data'] = $tplData;
    // $__tplData should be an array (-even-if- it only has one value in it),
    // if it's not throw an exception.
    if (is_array($tplData)) {
        extract($tplData, EXTR_OVERWRITE);
    } else {
        $msg = 'Incorrect format for tplData, it must be an associative array of arguments';
        xarExceptionSet(XAR_SYSTEM_EXCEPTION, 'BAD_PARAM',
                       new SystemException($msg));
        return;
    }

    // Start output buffering
    ob_start();

    // Load cached template file
    if (xarCoreIsDebuggerActive()) {
        $res = include $cachedFileName;
    } else {
        // Suppress error report when debugger is not active to prevent
        // that the var dir hash key could be stolen
        $res = @include $cachedFileName;
    }

    // Fetch output and clean buffer
    $output = ob_get_contents();
    ob_end_clean();

    // Return output
    return $output;
}

          </artwork>
					</t>   
     </section>

        <section title="xarTplEval()">
          <t>The public function xarTplEval() will simply replace
          the current functionality of xarTplString().</t>
<t>
          <artwork>function xarTplString($templateCode, $tplData) {
          return xarTpl__execute($templateCode, $tplData);
          }</artwork></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Modified Functions">
        <section title="xarTplString()">
          <t>This will become the public interface to BlockLayout for
          Content. The current version of this function does not appear to be called from anywhere (at the moment), so 
          changes should have no impact on existing code.</t>

<t>          <artwork>function xarTplString($templateCode, $tplData, $cache_flag) {
          return xarTpl__executeFromString($templateCode, $tplData, $cache_flag);
          }</artwork></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>This section lists some of the things I might not yet 
      have a handle on or that may need to be investigated by
      someone who has a better understanding of the core
      Xaraya code</t>
      <section title="md5">
        <t>md5 is used against the template source string to provide a
        file name for the cache. Is the result of md5 distinct enough
        to:</t>
				<t>
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>Change with minor amendments to sourceString? or</t>
        <t>Not conflict with other cached files?</t>
        </list>
				</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Garbage Collection">
        <t>What requirements are there for garbage collection? i.e. 
        removing stale content cache files.</t>
      </section>
    </section>


<!-- Revision history is mandatory -->
    <section title="Revision history">
      <t>Version 1.0 First Draft.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

<!-- Back matter is used for references and appendices which come after the references -->
  <back>
    <references title="Reference title">
<!-- Fill in references as needed -->
      <reference>
        <front>
          <title>Reference title</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Organization</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>
      </reference>

<!-- Repeat the aboven block if more references are needed -->
    </references>

<!-- Any section after this will become an appendix -->

    <section title="Definitions of the the Players">
      <t>This section lists and describes the players or roles
      involved in developing and running a Content Management
      System</t>
			<t>
      <list style="bullet">
        <t>Developer: Creates and maintains core and module code
        for general public release. May also create themes which
        are made available to others.</t>

        <t>Implementor: Installs and customizes Xaraya for clients.
        The customizations will be client specific such as
        modifying the BlockLayout templates to alter the look and
        feel of the site. Changes to core or module code will not
        always be rolled back into the Xaraya core.</t>

        <t>Admin: Looks after the day to day maintenance of an
        implemented site. Often a senior, technically competent
        user.</t>

        <t>Editor: Creates and approves articles and other content
        for publishing. Not necesarily technically minded.</t>

        <t>Author: A user who submits articles or other content for
        publication on a regular basis and would be trusted to
        maintain or amend existing content that they 'own'.</t>

        <t>Contributor or User: A visitor to the site. May or may
        not be logged in, may occasionally submit content, but will
        not take any further part in it's publication.</t>
      </list>
			</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
