<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xsl"?>
    <!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- <?rfc private='my private memo'?>  Produce a private memo rather than a Xaraya-standard --> 
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc number="0033" category="bcp">
  <!-- number: Fill in the number for the RFC -->
  <!-- obsoletes: Comma separated list of RFC numbers which this one obsoletes -->
  <!-- category: std=standard, bcp=best common practice, info=info, exp=experimental, historic=historic -->

  <!-- Front matter is used for identification of author and organization -->
  <front>
    <title>Upload Module</title>
    <author initials="MKA" surname="Altobelli" fullname="Marie Altobelli">
      <organization>Xaraya Development Group</organization>
      <address>
	<email>ladyofdragons@xaraya.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.xaraya.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2003"/>
    
    <!-- Initiating team for this RFC -->
    <workgroup>Project Management Committee</workgroup>

    <!-- List keywords for the RFC here -->
    <keyword>rfc</keyword>
    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- The abstract summarizes in one or two paragraphs the content of the RFC -->
    <abstract>
      <t>This RFC is to outline the details of the Uploads module.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <!-- The middle section is used for the actual content of the RFC -->
  <middle>
    <!-- Introduction is mandatory -->
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>It has become obvious that there is a need for a centralized handler for upload files.
			This single module would allow users to handle upload security in a centralized location,
			and would allow module developers who utilize it to be sure that their modules would not leave
			holes in a user's website.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- One content section is mandatory -->
    <section title="List of requirements">
      <t>The following is a list of requirements for a central upload module</t>
			<list style="numbers">
			<t>Be as secure as possible for an uploads utility</t>
			<t>Be available to integrate with any module requiring upload capabilities</t>
			<t>Offer variations to security to enable use in different server environments</t>
			<t>Use the permissions schema to enable/disable uploads access</t>
			<t>Allow upload of binary and ascii files</t>
			<t>Read and return text from uploaded ascii files</t>
			<t>Save binary files to database as a blob</t>
			<t>Obscure uploaded files to increase safety</t>
			<t>Have an approval workflow process to identify dangerous uploads</t>
			</list>
    </section>

		<!-- One content section is mandatory -->
    <section title="Proposed Table Structure">
      <t>
			<artwork>
			CREATE TABLE xar_uploads (
        xar_ulid int(11) NOT NULL auto_increment,
        xar_ulmod varchar(32) NOT NULL default '',
        xar_ulmodid int(32) NOT NULL default '0',
        xar_uluid int(11) NOT NULL default '0',
        xar_ulfile varchar(254) NOT NULL default '',
        xar_ulhash varchar(254) NOT NULL default '',
				xar_ultype CHAR(1) DEFAULT 'F' NOT NULL, 
        xar_ulapp tinyint(3) NOT NULL default '0',
        PRIMARY KEY  (xar_ulid)
      ) TYPE=MyISAM;
			
			CREATE TABLE xar_uploadblobs (
        xar_ulid mediumint(9) NOT NULL default '0',
        xar_blob blob NOT NULL
      ) TYPE=MyISAM;
			</artwork>
			</t>
    </section>
		
    <section title="Proposed Functionality">
      <t>In order to integrate into any module effectively, I think that uploads should be a
			   core utility module, like categories.  It has a relatively small footprint, and has
				 much functionality that can extend across modules.  A module can make use of one or 
				 more functionalities of uploads, as needed.</t>
				 
			<t>Three main functionalities are encompassed in this module:</t>
			<list>
			<t>Uploading a file that is saved to a folder</t>
			<t>Uploading a file that is saved to the database</t>
			<t>Uploading a file whose contents are returned as a text variable</t>
			</list> 
			
			<t>Uploading a file that is saved to a folder:</t>
			<t>Using this method, the form control is passed to the uploads module.  The file is
			pulled from the temp folder using _$FILES and is_uploaded_file for maximum security.  
			The name of the file is scrambled through MD5 using a random salt obtained by time &amp; pid.  
			a URL to a placeholder page is passed back to the calling module.  The placeholder page 
			will notify someone who tries it that the file has not been approved, and to try back later.
			The site admin can then download it for examination, approve the file, and rename it back 
			to its original name or change the name and location of the file.  The file will be renamed 
	    through move to the new name.  At this point the placeholder URL if called will forward the 
			user to the actual file.</t>
			
			<t>Uploading a file that is saved to the database</t>
			<t>Using this method, the form control is passed to the uploads module.  The file is 
			pulled from the temp folder using _$FILES and is_uploaded_file for maximum security.  
			A record is added to the xar_uploads table, and the file is then inserted into the 
			xar_uploadblobs table.  A URL to a placeholder page is passed back to the calling module. 
			The placeholder page will notify someone who tries it that the file has not been approved, 
			and to try back later.  The site admin can then download it for examination and approve the file. 
			At this point the placeholder URL if called will open the file from the database.</t>
			
			<t>Uploading a file whos contents are returned as a text variable</t>
			<t>Using this method, a file is uploaded with the same specs as the file system method.  
			After the file goes through the validation process, it is opened and its contents are 
			read into a variable, which is passed back to the calling module.  An illegal read or 
			fault passes back false.</t>   
    </section>
		
    <!-- Revision history is mandatory -->
    <section title="Revision history">
      <t>2003-01-14 - initial submission</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!-- Back matter is used for references and appendices which come after the references -->
  <back>
    <references title="Reference title">
      <!-- Fill in references as needed -->
      <reference>
	<front>
	  <title>Reference title</title>
	  <author>
	    <organization>Organization</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date year="2002"/>
	</front>
      </reference>
      <!-- Repeat the aboven block if more references are needed -->
    </references>
    
    <!-- Any section after this will become an appendix -->
    <section title="Example appendix">
      <t>Any section which is present after the references will become an appendix</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
